<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title></title>
 <link href="/" rel="self"/>
 <link href=""/>
 <updated>2014-07-05T14:44:37-04:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Post to a Jekyll blog from an iPad</title>
   <link href="/web/2014/07/01/post-to-a-jekyll-blog-from-an-ipad.html"/>
   <updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>/web/2014/07/01/post-to-a-jekyll-blog-from-an-ipad</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/web/2014/06/13/why-i-moved-from-blogger-to-jekyll.html&quot; title=&quot;Why I moved from Blogger to Jekyll&quot;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed my move from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blogger.com&quot;&gt;Blogger&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll blog&lt;/a&gt; hosted on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. While I could create a new blog post, the inability to submit a post to my blog from an iPad was a negative of the migration. I noted this was not possible because there is currently no way to manage a GitHub repository on an iOS device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- update earlier post to include edit and link to this post --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several bloggers suggest alternatives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.garron.me/en/blog/blogging-from-ipad-jekyll-dropbox.html&quot; title=&quot;Blogging from the iPad with Jekyll&quot;&gt;Wait until you get home&lt;/a&gt; to submit the post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/04/01/remote-octopress-workflow/&quot; title=&quot;Remote Blogging with Octopress&quot;&gt;Use remote connection&lt;/a&gt; iOS software to connect to a Mac&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the iPhone only app &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/octopart/id592802548?mt=8&amp;amp;uo=4&amp;amp;at=10l9vL&quot;&gt;Octopage&lt;/a&gt; (I’m really not interested in running iPhone only apps on my iPad)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these options involve extra steps and software and while technically they allow me to post via an iPad, they are not optimal solutions. I think I have a better solution as it allows me to use the wonderful iOS text editor &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/editorial/id673907758?mt=8&amp;amp;uo=4&amp;amp;at=10l9vL&quot;&gt;Editorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my solution doesn’t require Editorial, its use streamlines my workflow. For those not familiar with this iOS software, Editorial includes a built-in web browser. This allows me to write and research all within the same app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; The iOS app &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/writing-kit-research-write/id426208994?mt=8&amp;amp;uo=4&amp;amp;at=10l9vL&quot;&gt;Writing Kit&lt;/a&gt; also has this capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editorial also includes a bookmarks manager within the editor to quickly launch sites. I will use both of these features as the basis for my all-in-one Jekyll blog posting solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a new user of GitHub and what some may already know, I recently discovered. You can add files to a GitHub repository using a web browser. GitHub includes a rudimentary browser based editor that you can use to create/edit code or text files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Editorial, I created a bookmark to my blog’s GitHub &lt;code&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; online directory as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-07-01-editorial-posts-bookmark.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-07-01-editorial-posts-bookmark.png&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I tap the Editorial bookmark, GitHub provides an online list of the &lt;code&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory within its built in web browser as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-07-01-jekyll-posts.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-07-01-jekyll-posts.png&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt;** symbol highlighted? That’s the secret sauce. If you click the **&lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; symbol, GitHub will present a new online form as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-07-01-jekyll-posts-form.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-07-01-jekyll-posts-form.png&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add the title of the post, copy the markdown from the Editorial text editor, return to the web browser and then paste the markdown code into the web based editor. Update the commit information at the bottom of the page (including optional notes) and finally click the &lt;code&gt;Commit new file&lt;/code&gt; at the bottom-right of the page. The post is now added to your blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s pretty simple. Given Editorial’s extensibility through the built in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; interpreter, I have to wonder if this process can be automated via an Editorial workflow. Maybe some enterprising programmer out there can figure this one out. Doubtful I’ll have time to do so. Still, that’s a pretty easy solution that allows me to use Editorial and my iPad as a complete Jekyll blog posting solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have another solution? Drop it in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Why I moved from Blogger to Jekyll</title>
   <link href="/web/2014/06/13/why-i-moved-from-blogger-to-jekyll.html"/>
   <updated>2014-06-13T17:10:20-04:00</updated>
   <id>/web/2014/06/13/why-i-moved-from-blogger-to-jekyll</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;www.blogger.com&quot;&gt;Blogger&lt;/a&gt; was my blogging platform of choice for several years. Blogger was the host for my:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;personal blog: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com&quot;&gt;http://www.stevencombs.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tech blog: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docstechnotes.com&quot;&gt;http://www.docstechnotes.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LEGO blog: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bricksinmypocket.org&quot;&gt;http://www.bricksinmypocket.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the 2014 Memorial Day weekend, I decided to migrate two blogs (personal and tech) to a single &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; blog and host it on &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. You are reading this post on the new site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-06-13-stevencombs.site.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-06-13-stevencombs.site.png&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would not recommend every Blogger user make this transition; however, consider it if you have even basic knowledge of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Command_line&quot;&gt;command line&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CSS&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML5&quot;&gt;HTML5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You do not need to be a master in all of these skills to make the transition, but combine an understanding of the basics, online search skills and a willingness to learn from your mistakes and you will enjoy the transition. Your reward will be new skills and a better understanding of your blog &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backend&quot;&gt;backend&lt;/a&gt; than you ever had using Blogger. This post will not show you how to &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllbootstrap.com/&quot;&gt;set up a Jekyll blog&lt;/a&gt;, but rather provides my thoughts on why I made the transition from Jekyll to Blogger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Back to the 1990s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a very different blogging platform than Blogger; although you would be hard pressed to notice this visually. While most blogging platforms use a backend database to manage content, Jekyll takes a different approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a simple, blog-aware, static site generator. It takes a template directory containing raw text files in various formats, runs it through Markdown (or Textile) and Liquid converters, and spits out a complete, ready-to-publish static website suitable for serving with your favorite web server. Jekyll also happens to be the engine behind GitHub Pages, which means you can use Jekyll to host your project’s page, blog, or website from GitHub’s servers for &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who’ve been around the web and web programming for some time, you might consider static sites a return to the 1990s. In a way it is and I’ve found this to be a very good thing. Because Jekyll removes the database backend, I’ve noticed a huge increase not only in the speed of my site, but also a huge decrease in the time required to write, manage and post my content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-06-13-github-site-files.png&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an extremely rudimentary description of Jekyll. If you want more, I recommend you check out their &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/home/&quot;&gt;Welcome&lt;/a&gt; page. It’s loaded with some great information including a quick start guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;Benefits of Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While site speed would be reason enough to make the transition, there are other reasons. Below are my favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Cost:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Blogger for years, I am very familiar with the free model and its limitations. What I appreciate about Jekyll, when served on GitHub, is that there are very few limitations. GitHub provides free hosting and due to the nature of GitHub (code sharing), I have access to every bit of code on my site. Nothing is hidden and I am not crippled in any way from making changes (which as you can imagine has caused a few hiccups along the way). GitHub doesn’t even charge to attach a custom domain!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you do lose is some advanced web technology access such as Perl, Python, PHP, etc. With Jekyll on GitHub you are limited to HTML, CSS and Javascript. Let’s face it though, 95% of those who maintain a blog probably won’t use anything other than those three technologies. I find in my research and experimentation that you can do some amazing things with these three technologies alone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Markdown:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll lets you compose blog posts in several different markup languages such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LaTeX&quot;&gt;Latex&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; and it’s more feature rich sister, &lt;a href=&quot;http://fletcherpenney.net/multimarkdown/&quot;&gt;MultiMarkdown&lt;/a&gt;. I use Markdown for almost all my writing – including business/academic writing. I won’t go into the whys here, but if you are a Markdown user, you already get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being able to compose my posts natively in Markdown provides me with several benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legibility – even though Markdown uses some code to format text, it is extremely legible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed - I can quickly create and format a Markdown post and not worry about HTML code or heavy WYSIWYG tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Editors – I can use one of several good Markdown editors such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/editorial/id673907758?mt=8&amp;amp;uo=4&amp;amp;at=10I9LR&amp;amp;ct=iTunes&quot;&gt;Editorial&lt;/a&gt; on my iPad, &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/byword/id420212497?mt=12&amp;amp;uo=4&amp;amp;at=10I9LR&amp;amp;ct=iTunes&quot;&gt;Byword&lt;/a&gt; on my Mac or iPad, and &lt;a href=&quot;http:atom.io&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; on my Mac. I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/marked/id448925439?mt=12&amp;amp;uo=4&amp;amp;at=10I9LR&amp;amp;ct=iTunes&quot;&gt;Marked&lt;/a&gt; to preview my content before posting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search - Markdown files are simple text files. This allows content to be easily searched and the files quickly found using Spotlight or &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/alfred/id405843582?mt=12&amp;amp;uo=4&amp;amp;at=10I9LR&amp;amp;ct=iTunes&quot;&gt;Alfred&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portability – Markdown file content is easily reusable so I can repurpose my content in other documents and presentations. To reformat a Markdown post to a presentation, give &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/deckset-turn-your-notes-into/id847496013?mt=12&amp;amp;uo=4?at=10l9LR&quot;&gt;Deckset&lt;/a&gt; a shot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;Dropbox and GitHub:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Jekyll blog is hosted in a GitHub repository. On my Macs, I keep my synced GitHub repository in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://db.tt/11cphuY&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; folder. This keeps every file of my site synced from computer to computer as well as with my GitHub repository, complete with versioning inherent with both Dropbox and GitHub. Now that’s redundancy. Using Dropbox, I have access to any file on any computer or iOS device. I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/alfred/id405843582?mt=12&amp;amp;uo=4?at=10l9LR&quot;&gt;Alfred&lt;/a&gt; to quickly locate and edit a blog post and I can use tools like &lt;a href=&quot;http://atom.io&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/diet-coda/id500906297?mt=8&amp;amp;uo=4?at=10l9LR&quot;&gt;Diet Coda&lt;/a&gt; to edit the CSS/HTML5/Javascript files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only draw back currently is there is no way to make an edit and commit those edit to GitHub natively from my iPad without a remote connection to a Mac. If someone has a way around this, drop a comment below. This really isn’t a huge issue since I can make my commits/posts once I am back at one of my Macs, but it is the one thing that keeps me from being able to use my iPad Air exclusively to manage my blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_5&quot;&gt;Maintain a development version on your Mac&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can actually run Jekyll on your computer and host a development version of your site (or a live version if you have a Mac server available and configured). It’s easy to simply copy the Dropbox folder that contains your live site to a new folder, fire up the &lt;em&gt;Terminal&lt;/em&gt;, navigate to the folder and then issue the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course you need to ensure Jekyll is installed on your Mac and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/&quot;&gt;Jekyll installation documentation&lt;/a&gt; makes this a pretty quick and simple process. Once you have everything configured the way you want it, you simply copy the changes to your live directory and perform a GitHub commit. This is a great way to learn and try out new CSS/HTML5/Javascript technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_6&quot;&gt;Flexibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Utilizing static pages rather than a database to manage content provides an amazing amount of flexibility not possible with Blogger. For instance, with Blogger, every post and page requires the use of the same site theme. With Jekyll, I can throw styles out the window and create unique pages that are different from my site theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, let’s say I want to sell a car. I probably don’t want that page associated with my blog on a long term basis. It is, hopefully, a short term need. With Jekyll I can create a simple HTML page that provides information about the car for sale and then spiff it up a bit with some HTML5 and CSS. This page can then have it’s own unique landing point within my domain like &lt;code&gt;www.stevencombs.com/car-for-sale&lt;/code&gt;. This is not possible using Blogger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another flexibility example is the ability to have individual templates based on categories. If I have a post categorized &lt;em&gt;technology&lt;/em&gt;, I can have a unique graphic for every post within this category. Again, not possible with Blogger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_7&quot;&gt;Drawbacks of Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of its strengths, there are a few drawbacks to Jekyll. Below is a bullet list of, what I consider, minor issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of templates - Unlike Blogger, there is not an abundance of templates available. Jekyll just doesn’t have the user base of those two platforms. Be prepared to look like every other Jekyll blog unless you are ready to roll up your sleeves, dig deep and modify the default &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllbootstrap.com/usage/jekyll-theming.html&quot;&gt;Jekyll bootstrap theme’s&lt;/a&gt; CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning curve - To use Jekyll, you need to understand GitHub and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;. This doesn’t necessarily mean new &lt;em&gt;Terminal&lt;/em&gt; commands as there is a pretty fantastic GUI &lt;a href=&quot;https://mac.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Mac app&lt;/a&gt;. In my case, this was not a drawback, but rather a learning opportunity. For some though, this will be a “non-starter.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;You can’t post from iOS – I am unable to commit/post to my Jekyll site from an iOS device.&lt;/del&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/web/2014/07/01/post-to-a-jekyll-blog-from-an-ipad.html&quot;&gt;I now have a solution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No dashboard – Blogger provides an online dashboard to modify blog settings and to create posts/pages. Using Jekyll, this is done manually on a file by file basis. While I don’t consider this a drawback, many new bloggers will. Don’t go into Jekyll unless you are comfortable working without a GUI to manage and create posts for your blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_8&quot;&gt;Summing up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogger served its purpose for a time and was a very good choice for someone who did not want to be saddled down with monthly hosting fees; however, Jekyll and GitHub together is a home run. If you want to maintain your blog on the cheap (free), have full control over your site design, and have availability to a whole slew of text/code editing tools, you will appreciate the switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve warned, it does come with a learning curve; however, you’ve nothing to loose. You can keep your Blogger site and build your new site on the side. When you like your new site, just make it live! Porting content from your Blogger site to Jekyll is also pretty easy. The Jekyll site provides all the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/migrations/&quot;&gt;tools you need&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do make the switch, or you are already a Jekyll user, drop a comment below and share your site and experience. I would love to see what others are doing given that my site is, like my CSS and HTML5 skills, fairly rudimentary. Although I do like the custom images on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com&quot;&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt; I created using &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/idraw/id404705039?mt=12&amp;amp;uo=4?at=10l9LR&quot;&gt;iDraw&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Integrate Google+ comments into Blogger Template</title>
   <link href="/web/2014/04/14/problems-integrating-google-comments.html"/>
   <updated>2014-04-14T15:19:19-04:00</updated>
   <id>/web/2014/04/14/problems-integrating-google-comments</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;{Update: I no longer use Blogger; however, this was a popular post, so I am reposting for those who may need this information.}&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I migrated to a new Blogger template on my old blogging platform, one of the things I did not notice (and not sure how I didn&amp;rsquo;t) was that my comments were missing. I know the simple solution is to insert this small snippet into my custom Blogger template:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Google+ Comments --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;cmt_iframe_holder&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;expr:data-href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;data:post.canonicalUrl&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;expr:data-viewtype=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;data:post.viewType&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem was I didn&amp;rsquo;t know where to put it. I tried several locations and received a lot of errors. Others may have the same problem. Below are the steps from my solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://draft.blogger.com/&quot;&gt;Blogger in Draft&lt;/a&gt; (my preferred web interface for Blogger).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select Template from the left–hand menu.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the Edit HTML button to display your custom template.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click in the template window, tap &lt;code&gt;⌘+A&lt;/code&gt; to select the entire text and tap &lt;code&gt;⌘+C&lt;/code&gt; top copy the text to the clipboard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paste the text into a text file for safe keeping. I put mine in &lt;a href=&quot;http://brettterpstra.com/projects/nvalt/&quot;&gt;nvALT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy the code snippet above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search (&lt;code&gt;⌘+F&lt;/code&gt;) for a section of text similar to that found in my screen shot below. See apologies below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hit &lt;code&gt;↩&lt;/code&gt; a few times to provide space for the code snippet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paste the code snippet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the Save template button at the top of the page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If no errors, open another tab in your browser and view a blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do receive an error, immediately undo (&lt;code&gt;⌘+Z&lt;/code&gt;) and once again save your template. Try again in another location. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry if things go awry. You have a backup of your template in a text file. You did preform steps 4 and 5? Simply replace the botched up template with your pristine copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-pXfpvpca2QY/UyNkOyEo_3I/AAAAAAABPyk/ctc1nFZ4i_o/s1600/Google++Comments+in+Blogger+Code+Snippet.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-pXfpvpca2QY/UyNkOyEo_3I/AAAAAAABPyk/ctc1nFZ4i_o/s1600/Google++Comments+in+Blogger+Code+Snippet.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Click image for larger view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could be a more specific as to the location of the code snippet, but each custom template is different. Hope this helps someone. If it does, drop a comment below.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bullet Review – New Trent Airbender 2.0 for iPad Air</title>
   <link href="/apple/2014/03/06/Bullet-review-newtrent-airbender-2.html"/>
   <updated>2014-03-06T12:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>/apple/2014/03/06/Bullet-review-newtrent-airbender-2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had an upcoming business trip to take and I was on the lookout for a good portable keyboard case for my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00G2Y4WNY/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00G2Y4WNY&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=docstechnotes-20&quot;&gt;iPad Air&lt;/a&gt;. There are several keyboard cases on the market, and after reading numerous reviews, I chose the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00ET9YYS2/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00ET9YYS2&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=docstechnotes-20&quot;&gt;New Trent Airbender 2.0 Keyboard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Yw7R9FFE7UM/UxjU5FB8eqI/AAAAAAABPWA/fyXPHcSgotE/s1600/IMG_5350.JPG&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not the most sophisticated case on the market, you can check out my bullet review below to find out why it was the clear choice for my budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excellent functionality, protection and build quality for as little as $60&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vertical orientation functionality which is rare for an iPad keyboard case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good stability in both horizontal and vertical orientation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use case as separate stand and keyboard (see gallery below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separate iPad Air from keyboard easily and still have protection for the back of the iPad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keys for home, brightness, virtual keyboard, cut/copy/paste, media, keyboard layouts and lock screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Caps lock light&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast bluetooth connection and easy pairing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comfortable key positions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy transition from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005DLDTAE/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B005DLDTAE&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=docstechnotes-20&quot;&gt;Apple Keyboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rechargeable, via micro USB, battery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;{UPDATE}: Excellent shipping and packaging materials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configuration is a bit unwieldy and awkward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instructions are a bit vague&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bulky case (see Pros above)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key markings are not etched and you can see the sticker edges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No keyboard back-lighting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not as attractive as cases from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00EOE4G4E/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00EOE4G4E&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=docstechnotes-20&quot;&gt;Belkin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00EZ9XGE4/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00EZ9XGE4&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=docstechnotes-20&quot;&gt;Logitech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Photo Gallery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Yw7R9FFE7UM/UxjU5FB8eqI/AAAAAAABPWA/fyXPHcSgotE/s1600/IMG_5350.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-UZkkmCUFEqo/UxjU0r3z_SI/AAAAAAABPUk/4QtbvTyPdkM/s1600/IMG_5333.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-LJ-Vxu6eYX8/UxjU0iH3uSI/AAAAAAABPUo/yatDVWQYGOA/s1600/IMG_5335.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-So7u_olKVaY/UxjU1dWt53I/AAAAAAABPUs/5C8_lotVpkk/s1600/IMG_5337.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-HwnWeboH-js/UxjU1VzOZzI/AAAAAAABPU8/JUKwmQKQx1Y/s1600/IMG_5338.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mctvudaoLRA/UxjU2e_GwgI/AAAAAAABPVE/KRYvmqwe5qc/s1600/IMG_5340.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-OtBoJxUoKAM/UxjU2_Pw_QI/AAAAAAABPVQ/cc6X12pJoRE/s1600/IMG_5342.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-UgagLjE8tQc/UxjU3OM1e9I/AAAAAAABPVY/eWbHC_ii9KQ/s1600/IMG_5344.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-87473ehuCZc/UxjU3CDw_6I/AAAAAAABPVk/HVcWKzFdUgU/s1600/IMG_5345.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-l91s-ODuL60/UxjU4DVWWVI/AAAAAAABPVs/eVailS7Lzgw/s1600/IMG_5346.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-I8A_0SrS6wE/UxjU4olDutI/AAAAAAABPVw/sIcMXi5C1qg/s1600/IMG_5347.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-YQGVxvWi01g/UxjU4qTmBVI/AAAAAAABPV4/vBEKZMf2h6g/s1600/IMG_5348.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-jrAg-gdrBhY/UxjU2d-_uyI/AAAAAAABPVI/G_RQ2tEgC6s/s1600/IMG_5321.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sublime Text Arduino programming IDE on Peppermint OS</title>
   <link href="/linux/arduino/2014/01/11/Create-best-arduino-programming-ide.html"/>
   <updated>2014-01-11T12:00:39-05:00</updated>
   <id>/linux/arduino/2014/01/11/Create-best-arduino-programming-ide</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-P3kE77jeAh8/UtGX3D4GkbI/AAAAAAABOkE/G5rKnB8pqIA/s1600/PeppermintOS-SublimeText-Arduino.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;In a previous post I demonstrated the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/linux/2014/01/05/Install-arduino-ide-on-peppermint-os.html&quot;&gt;install of the Arduino IDE&lt;/a&gt; on a &lt;a href=&quot;http://peppermintos.com/guide/software/&quot;&gt;Peppermint OS 4&lt;/a&gt; install. Today I want to take this a bit further and show you how to create an Arduino programming environment that knocks the socks of the original Arduino IDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you begin, you must have Java and the official &lt;a href=&quot;http://arduino.cc/en/main/software&quot;&gt;Arduino IDE&lt;/a&gt; software installed on your Peppermint OS box. Directions are &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/RHa3f3&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Once that process is complete, click the link below to learn how you can use Sublime Text 2 and a package known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Robot-Will/Stino&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stino&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to upgrade your Arduino programming environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will use Peppermint OS; however, these instructions should work with most Debian based Linux distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Why use Sublime Text 2 and the Stino package?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into a long rant on why Sublime Text 2 is my go to text editor on both Linux and Mac. A quick Google search will yield many blog posts that handily take care of this task. Quickly though, Sublime Text 2 includes features that the original Arduino IDE simply does not, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;text snippets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;code completion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;document map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enhanced search and replace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;multiple selections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tabs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That last bullet, packages, is the vital component. It allows us to add additional features to the base install of Sublime Text 2. The Stino package simply adds the controls we need to write, compile and upload our code to an Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also configure a Mac with the same setup. My first use of Sublime Text 2 and the Stino package was on a Mac and the install is similar. Seasoned Mac users will be able to complete an install with relative ease. If there’s a need for a Mac version of this post, drop a comment below. And “yes,” this same setup can be accomplished on a Windows box. Please don’t ask me for instructions though. I haven’t had access to a Windows machine in over three years.&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;Install Sublime Text 2:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heart of our new enhanced Arduino IDE is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sublimetext.com/2&quot;&gt;Sublime Text 2&lt;/a&gt;. As the time of this writing, a beta version of Sublime Text 3 is available. These instructions will not work for this version; however, savvy Linux users can probably modify my instructions to get a functional install. Let’s begin and install Sublime Text 2 on Peppermint OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the &lt;em&gt;Terminal&lt;/em&gt; via mouse or the keyboard shortcut: &lt;code&gt;ctrl&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;alt&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;t&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type the command: &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install sublime-text–2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter your password at the prompt followed by &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peppermint OS will search for all dependencies and software necessary for the install.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some seasoned Linux users may wonder why we don’t need to install repositories (or server locations that contain the software). Peppermint OS already includes them! Yet another reason Arduino fans should consider Peppermint OS as their Linux distro of choice.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When prompted, allow the install by entering &lt;code&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; at the prompt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Load Sublime Text 2:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s verify our install of Sublime Text 2 and make sure things are operational.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose &lt;em&gt;Programming&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Sublime Text 2&lt;/em&gt; from the Peppermint OS start menu as shown in the image below. Sublime Text 2 will load.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-dkileqzsEzw/UtGYmz_ssAI/AAAAAAABOkM/Rd8K5qC9CGw/s1600/Programming-SublimeText2_menu_item-2.png&quot; height=&quot;388&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those familiar with basic text editors will find Sublime Text 2 familiar. The lack of icons and buttons may confuse new users. Hang in there and trust me. Once we get those Arduino controls in there, it will all begin to make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you are curious about Sublime Text 2 usage and features, let me suggest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLLnpHn493BHEYF4EX3sAhVG2rTqCvLnsP&quot;&gt;this series of videos&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Install the Sublime Text Package Manager:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a functional Sublime Text 2 install, its time to make it Arduino aware. We utilize the package feature of Sublime Text 2 to do this. Natively, Sublime Text 2 does not include a package manager; however, the folk(s) over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://sublime.wbond.net&quot;&gt;https://sublime.wbond.net&lt;/a&gt; have created the standard in Sublime Text package managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Package Manager&lt;/em&gt; makes it easy to add other features to Sublime Text 2 as you become more comfortable with its use in other activities besides Arduino programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;https://sublime.wbond.net/installation#st2&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to visit the Sublime Text 2 Package Control installation page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highlight and copy the appropriate code that is similar to the code found in the image below. Make sure you grab the code for Sublime Text 2 and not Sublime Text 3. My link will present the code you need by default.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-QWQoDR4lP1g/UtGYwg2OlgI/AAAAAAABOkU/x5hPH4DjRfQ/s1600/Install+Code.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;392&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Activate the Sublime Text 2 console using &lt;code&gt;ctrl&lt;/code&gt; + `&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paste the text copied from the web site into the console.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restart Sublime Text 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;Install the Stino Arduino package:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the install of the &lt;em&gt;Package Manager&lt;/em&gt; in the previous section, this is now an easy task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Activate the &lt;em&gt;Command Palette&lt;/em&gt; (shown in the image below) using &lt;code&gt;shift&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;command&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-lRdWogAr4lE/UtGY4xBX4-I/AAAAAAABOkc/Y3OlENWQ2jA/s1600/command+palette.png&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Activate the &lt;em&gt;Command Palette&lt;/em&gt; using &lt;code&gt;shift&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;command&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Type: &lt;code&gt;Install&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;Package&lt;/code&gt; and use arrow keys and select the &lt;em&gt;Install Package&lt;/em&gt; option.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hit &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt;. The status bar at the bottom of the page will display an animated prompt while it updates the repository listing as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-52jL6TZLYJM/UtGZSMxJGII/AAAAAAABOkk/Ei09r2wAC-A/s1600/animated_status_bar.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;An alphabetical list of packages appears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Type &lt;code&gt;arduino&lt;/code&gt;. The list will narrow down the available options.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use the arrow keys to select the &lt;em&gt;Arduino-like IDE&lt;/em&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hit &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Package Manager&lt;/em&gt; will download and install the package.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;Arduino&lt;/em&gt; menu item will appear on the right-hand side of the Sublime Text 2 main menu as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-7b_-lkOMmBM/UtGaTnhlLdI/AAAAAAABOkw/VYh0fa8hpbE/s1600/Stino_Arduino_Menu-2.png&quot; height=&quot;374&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_5&quot;&gt;Configure and use the Stino Arduino package:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stino&lt;/em&gt; package the location of the official Arduino IDE install. Stino is Sublime Text 2 conduit to that software and it’s libraries. Make sure you have the Arduino IDE installed before completing the steps below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select &lt;em&gt;Arduino&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Preferences&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Select Arduino Application Folder&lt;/em&gt; from the Sublime Text 2 main menu. A prompt will appear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Immediately press &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; and the prompt will display the home account file structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Navigate using either the keyboard or the cursor keys to the following location: &lt;code&gt;/usr/share/arduino/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt;. This will set the location of the Arduino IDE and its libraries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attach an Arduino board to your Peppermint OS box via a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B001TH7GUA?tag=docstechnotes-20&amp;amp;amp;camp=0&amp;amp;amp;creative=0&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as4&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B001TH7GUA&amp;amp;amp;adid=06HRGQC78A3T02GSA04C&amp;amp;amp;&quot;&gt;USB cable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t have an Arduino? Get a great deal on an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;field-keywords=Arduino&amp;amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;amp;tag=bricinmypockb-20&amp;amp;url=search-alias%3Delectronics&amp;amp;linkId=LISU5PL6NIEETUSF&quot;&gt;Arduino at Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Connect an Arduino to complete the final steps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select &lt;em&gt;Arduino&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Serial Port&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;/dev/???&lt;/em&gt; from the Sublime Text 2 main menu. There should be a single entry where ??? is a substitute for something similar to &lt;em&gt;ttyACM0&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select &lt;em&gt;Arduino&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Arduino AVR Boards&lt;/em&gt; from the Sublime Text 2 main menu and select the board attached to your computer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that wasn’t too bad. Now the moment we have all been waiting for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_6&quot;&gt;Compile and upload sample code:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we will enter, compile and upload our first program to an Arduino board. I will make things easy and include some sample code for you to use. The Arduino program below will blink the on-board LED.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy and paste this code into a new Sublime Text 2 document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pinMode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;OUTPUT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Save the code to any location you desire (Desktop maybe???) and give it the name &lt;em&gt;Blinky.ino&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Stino&lt;/em&gt; will compile the package and upload it to the Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You will have a blinky Arduino as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-93o7N_Cmtsw/UtGU0xseHMI/AAAAAAABOj4/QZnI8nAnE7A/s1600/Arduino_Blinky-9.jpg&quot; height=&quot;298&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are now ready to use the &lt;em&gt;Stino&lt;/em&gt; package to create an amazing new &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physical_computing&quot;&gt;physical computing&lt;/a&gt; project. And when you do, please share it in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_7&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New users to Linux have learned the basics of Linux software installation, Sublime Text 2 package management and Stino Arduino package use. In fact, if you “sorta/kinda” understood what were were doing, you have the skills to experiment with some other interesting installs and configurations. If nothing else, you now have installed on your Peppermint OS (or other Debian distro variant) what I consider to be the most powerful Arduino development platform available.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Install the Arduino IDE on Peppermint OS 4</title>
   <link href="/linux/arduino/2014/01/06/Install-arduino-ide-on-peppermint-os.html"/>
   <updated>2014-01-06T00:00:06-05:00</updated>
   <id>/linux/arduino/2014/01/06/Install-arduino-ide-on-peppermint-os</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-JWkcedZQv6k/Uss6UrZB9oI/AAAAAAABOg8/qhcYMT0zEXA/s1600/Loki+Blogs.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two things happened during the holiday break. Loki and I reacquired our fascination with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/s/?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;field-keywords=arduino&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;amp;amp;sprefix=Arduino%2Caps%2C236&amp;amp;amp;tag=docstechnotes-20&amp;amp;amp;url=search-alias%3Delectronics&quot;&gt;Arduino&lt;/a&gt; and I also upgraded the operating system on my old Acer Aspire One from Chrome OS to &lt;a href=&quot;http://peppermintos.com/&quot;&gt;Peppermint OS 4&lt;/a&gt;. In an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docstechnotes.com/2009/07/install-arduino-on-ubuntu-netbook-remix.html&quot;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, I shared how to install the Arduino software on a netbook with Ubuntu Netbook remix 9.04. I thought these earlier instructions would assist me with an install on Peppermint OS 4. That was not the case. Not even the first step was correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will provide an update to that original post. Users of other Linux distributions should also find these instructions valuable and if you are using a Debian variant, they should work perfectly. After you hit the link below, you will find instructions for installing and using the Arduino software on Peppermint OS 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arduino Integrated Development Environment (IDE) requires Java. Peppermint OS 4 does not include Java as part of the default installation. Rather than using the official Oracle Java install, many Linux users recommend using the icedtea-plugin due to ease of install and regularity of updates. I will use this variation of Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open a Terminal window and enter the following: &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install icedtea-plugin&lt;/code&gt; ↩&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enter your root password and enter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; to confirm the installation. The install can take some time depending on your Internet connectivity as well as the speed of your computer. That&amp;rsquo;s it. Java should now be available on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Verify the install at:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you load the page in the default Peppermint OS 4 Chromimum browser, allow the Java plugin access to the page. You should then see a verification as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Cg55TDef-EA/Uss0X-_j9iI/AAAAAAABOf4/prFIjccMHPk/s1600/Java+Verification.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have the Java dependency complete, let&amp;rsquo;s install the Arduino IDE. This is VERY easy if you have ever installed software on a Linux box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using the same Terminal window you used above, enter the following: &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install arduino&lt;/code&gt; ↩&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enter your root password at the prompt and hit enter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; to accept the package installs. The install can take some time depending on your Internet connectivity as well as the speed of your computer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once complete, you will find the Arduino software icon in the Electronics&amp;nbsp;Program Menu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try it out our new Arduino IDE install.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the Arduino item in the Electronics menu. The Arduino IDE will not load the first time and the prompt below will appear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-3E9xwqUMbKc/Uss1DrNCbJI/AAAAAAABOgM/-g4fXHU5t8o/s1600/Permission+Checker.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click the Add button to add your account to the &amp;ldquo;dialout&amp;rdquo; group. This security step is required and gives your account rights to utilize the serial connections to upload code to an Arduino. Side note, this is another reason I love both Linux and Mac – additional security.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Peppermint OS will request authentication to add your account to the group. Enter your password and click Authenticate as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-iUODxxNkoxE/Uss1P2LlydI/AAAAAAABOgU/RAJd9mk8870/s1600/Authentication+Required.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although not prompted to complete this step, reboot. If you don&amp;rsquo;t do this and try and upload code, you may find yourself very frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a reboot, connect your Arduino to your Peppermint OS 4 enabled computer. My setup is shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/--gKVRu6X22s/Uss1auky3QI/AAAAAAABOgc/YOlkVzdaEVg/s1600/My+Setup.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the Arduino item in the Electronics menu to load the Arduino IDE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the Arduino model from the &lt;em&gt;Tools&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Board&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Select Model Type&lt;/em&gt; menu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the device connection from the &lt;em&gt;Tools&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Serial Port&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;/dev/???&lt;/em&gt; menu. Substitute &lt;em&gt;???&lt;/em&gt; with whatever serial port is displayed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NOTE: The latest version of the Arduino IDE for Linux automatically configures the correct port once it finds an attached device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Load the sample LED sketch from the &lt;em&gt;File&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Examples&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;01.Basics&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;Blink&lt;/em&gt; menu. An LED blinking program will load.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click the Upload button as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1FWWUJpA4Hw/Uss2MJwyIWI/AAAAAAABOgs/DQEwylyxnYs/s1600/Compile+and+Upload.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arduino IDE will compile the program (check for errors and convert to machine code) and then upload the code to the Arduino. Once upload is complete, the Arduino will blink the on-board LED every second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success! The Arduino IDE is installed and configured properly. Now get out there and create some cool new thing. If compelled, share your creation in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all there is to it. Linux use and acceptability has come a long way in the past few years and given the ease of this process, I can highly recommend a Linux box (or an old Acer Aspire netbook) as an Arduino development tool.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What is the number one job skill requested by employers?</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/12/06/Number-one-job-skill-requested-by-employers.html"/>
   <updated>2013-12-06T04:24:30Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/12/06/Number-one-job-skill-requested-by-employers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-oo72t0hV8oA/UqFOAadtXfI/AAAAAAABNVY/1oQuEMPCHac/%25255BUNSET%25255D.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;On December 12th and 13th 2013, I attended the Workforce Development Consortium Strategy Forum at the Lone Star College Conference Center in Houston Texas. The forum brings together several community college and industry leaders from ten states that are part of the Community College Workforce Consortium (CCWC). The goal is to discuss workforce needs and how community colleges can train, educate and develop the future workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first meeting and it has been enlightening. Read this post and take a look at what was determined to be the number one skill requirement of new employees as determined by the CCWC participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today, the employers present (Boeing being one) were given a list of about twelve skills that were culled from a national survey of employers. The CCWC employers present, about 20 or so, where asked by the college representatives to identify from the larger list the top three skills required of new employees. The top three were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Problem solving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leadership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The selection of these three was not an epiphany. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen these bubble up to the top in other surveys. The employers want community colleges to teach these skills. “Got it!” I thought to myself. We are working on these and have been for quite some time. The discussion continued. There was another skill industry needed community college to teach to their students and this skill, not listed on the original twelve, was even more important than the top three. That skill?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Show up to work and show up on time!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ouch!” I thought to myself. This is a “skill” that is hard to teach and one that students need to be successful in college as well. They really should have this skill before they come to us. Right? Where do they learn this? How do we modify this behavior? Those are great questions that I cannot answer. I&amp;rsquo;m a Technologist by trade, not a Psychologist. Have an idea? Let me know in the comments below and let&amp;rsquo;s discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Thank a Veteran Today!</title>
   <link href="/holiday/2013/11/11/Thank-a-Veteran-Today.html"/>
   <updated>2013-11-11T11:39:25Z</updated>
   <id>/holiday/2013/11/11/Thank-a-Veteran-Today</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe align=&quot;right&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;540px&quot; src=&quot;https://www.thunderclap.it/projects/6258-veterans-day-2013/embed&quot; width=&quot;250px&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;Once again the time has come for us to honor those that have sacrificed themselves so that we may enjoy the freedoms of this great land. While we officially recognize the contributions of our veteran’s twice a year, we should be grateful daily for their continued service and sacrifices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am especially grateful for those that served and still serve “down-range.” Every day they are in harms way, is a day we are able to sleep comfortably knowing that we are being protected by the best military in the world. A military staffed by volunteers willing to offer themselves in service to their country. Are you willing to make this sacrifice? If not, you should be especially grateful. Because if not for them, then who?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever your political bent: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Get out there and thank a veteran!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is because of their sacrifice that you get to enjoy and voice your political views without fear or retribution. Not willing to thank them? Put your viewpoints on the shelf as you don’t deserve the liberty they provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I add a special thanks to those who served by my side during my two military careers (Air Force and Army). Many friendships were made and I am happy that many of them still endure even after my 27-years of service. Happy Veteran’s Day Y‘all!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Turn your RaspberryPi into a development platform with Coder</title>
   <link href="/raspberrypi/2013/09/15/coder-turns-your-raspberrypi-into.html"/>
   <updated>2013-09-15T15:19:19-04:00</updated>
   <id>/raspberrypi/2013/09/15/coder-turns-your-raspberrypi-into</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My weekend project was to install &lt;a href=&quot;1&quot;&gt;Coder&lt;/a&gt; on a RaspberryPi. Coder is a Google hosted project that is a:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…free, open source project that turns a Raspberry Pi into a simple platform that educators and parents can use to teach the basics of building for the web. New coders can craft small projects in HTML, CSS, and Javascript, right from the web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, you will learn a bit more about my experience with this new development platform for the RaspberryPi, learn how to &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; into the distribution, and also view a couple of images from the install. Before I prattle on about with my thoughts, check out the video below. It will provide a good sense Coder and its functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/wH24YwdayFg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The developer claims that you can setup Coder on a RaspberryPi in less than 10 minutes. These minutes do not account for the time needed to burn the OS image to an SD card. Coder made this process simple though by providing a Mac installer in the download package. No need to use my &lt;a href=&quot;3&quot;&gt;popular, but lengthy, Terminal instructions&lt;/a&gt;. Took about 7 minutes for my iMac to transfer the OS to the SD card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the SD card preparation, it took me less than 5 minutes to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;install the SD card into the RaspberryPi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;connect my Mac to the ad-hoc RaspberryPi network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;configure the RaspberryPi Wi-Fi to connect my home network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reboot the RaspberryPi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reconnect my Mac to my home network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access the RaspberryPi on my Mac using the &lt;code&gt;http://coder.local&lt;/code&gt; url in the Chrome for Mac browser or for iOS (shown in the image below).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;view sample projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;review the sparse Settings
Coder provides the detailed install process on their web page. Below is a capture of the Wi-Fi process I used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I posted several screen captures taken during the install process on Google+. I have embedded that post below.
A nice feature I found, after a quick cursory exploration of the sample code, was the ability to export projects so they can be hosted on other platforms. Files are collected and placed in a .zip file for download to your Mac or PC. This feature makes the Coder/RaspberryPi configuration a very robust, basic and secure web development tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coder really is slick and I am very surprised how quickly I was able to setup this educational web development resource. I still have several questions I need to research (or if you know the answer, drop them in the comments below):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Can I ssh into the server?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update: It appears ssh is active and you can connect using the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh pi@local.coder&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;em&gt;password:&lt;/em&gt; use the Coder setup password&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;Is apt-get or yum supported to update the OS when updates are available?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coder uses the regular Debian distribution so &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; is available and ready to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Can I install additional software on the server and make the RaspberryPi multifunctional (this of course requires the answer to the first question to be “yes”)?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YES!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Is there the ability to activate PHP, Ruby, Python and other web development languages (they may already be in there)?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YES!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;Can I make this instance of Coder accessible outside of my home network?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have not tested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_5&quot;&gt;Can the server host my projects without revealing code?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have not tested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coder development is still very early. The version I installed was v0.4. Clearly there is more work and more features to be added; however, even in this infant state, Coder is a very capable tool to provide children, adults and coders alike with a very competent educational tool or web testbed. Update: I&amp;rsquo;m actually using this as my primary development distribution. I regularly update the OS and install additional developmental tools. I recently installed Ruby to give me an additional programming environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to get back to my &lt;a href=&quot;6&quot;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt; lessons! Now that I have a robust platform from which to try out my new found HTML/CSS/Javascript skills, I&amp;rsquo;m ready to try out some experimental projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Make mistakes, learn from them, and own them</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/08/27/Make-mistakes-learn-from-them-own-them.html"/>
   <updated>2013-08-27T18:51:22Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/08/27/Make-mistakes-learn-from-them-own-them</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-K-STTmTy85A/UeQtr9EnbnI/AAAAAAABKZk/mm-cxRSUl7s/s200/Mistakes+You+Cannot+Correct.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;Yesterday I began a series of lessons learned from my first year as a Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs (VCAA). Today I share lesson number two – mistakes.I’ll admit that our college does not have a robust training program for new VCAAs. My training program was a two day orientation with four other “newer” regional VCAAs. The sessions was beneficial, but as our moderator explained, that training would not prepare us for our new roles. We would make mistakes. He was correct, but that session did prove valuable. It gave me a cohort to share ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one thing I had that my new peers did not was my previous experience within the college – over twenty years. I’ve served at two other regional campuses and on numerous statewide committees. I was around when the college made the transition from vocational college to a comprehensive community college. I was one of the first to implement online education within a region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These experiences provide me with a large pool of colleagues, who also have many years of experience, to tap into. Many of them have even held the position of VCAA. It is easy for me to contact any one of them and ask for their advice, coaching and/or mentoring. Surely this large base of knowledge will keep me from making mistakes…right? The answer is of course “no” as you will discover after hitting the link below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the resources available to me, I made a mistake early on that affected my professional relationship with a couple of individuals. I won’t go into specifics here, but suffice it to say that we are not always given the opportunity to sit back and observe before we make changes. Leadership articles often suggest this is good practice – in theory; however, sometimes external forces, such as budget and institutional priorities, don’t allow it. I spent 27 years in the military, I was trained to make quick decisions and live with the results of those decisions. But the military also teaches its leaders to learn and manage from their mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone new to any position will make mistakes. What you cannot do is dwell on the mistakes. You made the decision, you made the mistake, and you may be able to correct it. Correction may involve a simple reversal of a decision or action. Another option may be to make another decision that lessens the effects of the first. If neither of these are an option, then you must live with the mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what action you take to lessen a mistake, you must learn from it. You learn by self-reflection (I journal and blog). While you review your mistake, try and understand the:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;process used to formulate the decision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;current implications of your decision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;future implications of your decision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These can be some tough nuts to crack; however, taking the time to sit back and analyze your mistake will stop you from quickly making the same mistake again and may even better prepare you to not make a different and/or similar mistake down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;“Here’s the real lesson…ADMIT your mistake!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to grow in your professional maturity? ADMIT your mistake! No, “ifs,” “ands” or “buts” about it. Integrity is key to your long term viability as a leader and decision maker. Integrity will ensure that your mistake does not back you into a professional corner. If you try and cover a mistake, you will do even more harm to the situation and potentially your career. You will also lose the trust of your supervisor, peers and subordinates. They will not trust a decision maker who cannot own up to their own mistakes or who refuses to learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you notice my mention of subordinates? You need to admit your mistakes not only to your superiors, but also your subordinates. You must do this in a way where you take complete responsibility. Do not throw someone else under the bus. I’ve seen this tactic used too many times. It begins with, “Yes, I made the mistake, but…” and that’s a “but” usually followed by blame of someone else. It doesn’t matter who was involved. As a leader, you have responsibility for your own mistake. Simply own the mistake and move on. You will be amazed at the level of respect you gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone have anything to add to this lesson? I’m not asking for specific instances, although those would probably prove interesting, but why not share your tips and tricks and share how you deal with mistakes. You can do this in the comments section below.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Like classic films? Check out TCM this September!</title>
   <link href="/entertainment/2013/08/11/Like-classic-films-Check-out-TCM-this-September.html"/>
   <updated>2013-08-11T16:50:56Z</updated>
   <id>/entertainment/2013/08/11/Like-classic-films-Check-out-TCM-this-September</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-SoR1QZl9xok/Uge2_ZI2szI/AAAAAAABLIQ/IDmvd1bftzo/s1600/TCM+Now+Playing+-+September+2013.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;We received our monthly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tcm.com/&quot;&gt;Turner Classic Movies (TCM)&lt;/a&gt; Now Playing magazine for September. I think Nikki and I need to take a month’s worth of vacation from work so we can enjoy what is an amazing collection of classic cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out these monthly highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kim Novak – collection of films from the great actress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Future Shock – 16 great Sci Fi Friday films&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunday’s with Hitch – 43(!) Hitchcock films spread over every Sunday in September&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of those great monthly highlights are three of my favorite ways to explore unknown cinema; TCM Underground, TCM Imports and Silent Sunday Nights.&amp;lt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not a subscriber or viewer (TCM is part of our basic package), you should be. Watching TCM is the equivalent of participation in a college film class that never ends. Your Professors are the great Robert Osborne and the very entertaining and knowledgeable Ben Mankiewicz. They even have a guest lecturer drop by on occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want the full-on educational experience, check out their textbook, &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/b4e4nv&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now Playing&lt;/em&gt; magazine&lt;/a&gt;. Full of articles from the hosts and guests like Martin Scorsese, the magazine got a bit of a refresh in September. Want to visit their campus as a guest student? Attend a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tcmcruise.com&quot;&gt;Turner Classic Movie Cruise&lt;/a&gt; (on our bucket list)! Now that’s a campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably the only channel that keeps me from cutting ties with my local cable provider. If I could only subscribe to one channel on cable, this would be it. My only request would be the ability to watch live or time shifted on my iPad mini or iPhone. I would pay for this service as I do my Netflix subscription. Allow me to stream this content on my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docstechnotes.com/2013/08/chromecast-unboxing-setup-and-usage.html&quot;&gt;Chromecast&lt;/a&gt; and “good-bye cable!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{**UPDATE - May 3, 2014:** TCM now offers an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docstechnotes.com/2013/12/2013-appvent-calendar-day-15-coderunner.html&quot;&gt;iPad app&lt;/a&gt; that allows live streaming and video on demand movies. It does require cable company authentication, but is sure is great to have access to TCM on the go!}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give TCM a try this month and I’m sure you will be hooked. There’s nothing like a good classic film when there are 300 other channels of reality television. Gotta run now. Need to clear off some recordings from the TiVo to make room for what is sure to be an amazing month of entertainment. If you are a TCM watcher, sound off in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New series - My first year as a regional academic officer</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/07/14/New-series-My-first-year-as-a-regional-academic-officer.html"/>
   <updated>2013-07-14T18:51:27Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/07/14/New-series-My-first-year-as-a-regional-academic-officer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-X1gYurcLgJc/UeLnhOCKIMI/AAAAAAABKX0/5ZP9sLTNbQQ/s200/Dean+-vs-+RAO.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;This month marks my first year as the chief academic officer, Vice Chancellor of Academic Affairs (VCAA), for the Columbus/Franklin region of Ivy Tech Community College. During this first year, I have learned much about my new role, the college and the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To celebrate my first year, I’ve decided to share some lessons learned. These lessons may (I write “may” because every situation is unique) be useful for new and even seasoned chief academic officers. Blogging/writing is a great way for me to reflect on this past year and my hope is that not only will these lessons be of value to others when shared, but it will also force me to spend additional time reflecting on the past year’s hits and misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand no one will read the entirety of my lessons at a single setting (heck, I don’t think there will be many people who will read a single lesson), so I will spread them out over a series of posts. I will do my best to get each lesson out there as soon as I can. I’ll also leave the comments section open for each post so readers (again, if any) can ask questions or even drop in your own experiences. It’s a short lesson that is hinted at in the image above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The dean’s role is “same, ’cept different” from that of the VCAA:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The role of a school dean and that of a regional academic officer are very similar. Many tasks required of a dean directly transfer to the role of Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;faculty management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;budget management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enrollment management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strategic planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;community outreach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;organization and productivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instructional/information technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember thinking, while reviewing the position description for the vacant VCAA in Columbus, “I can do that. It’s just an extension of my current role.” I was correct to a point. Sure I continue to manage these same tasks; however, the complexity of each is multiplied exponentially as the chief academic officer. So while both positions are similar in scope, they differ on scale. It’s the scale that can cause you to be out of touch with what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out of touch:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
As a dean, I felt as if I knew what was going on in the classroom. I understood faculty issues. I knew students and faculty by name. Now I often find myself asking, “what’s happening in our classrooms?” or “who is that faculty member?” There’s a level of disconnect from the faculty and students that I was not prepared for nor have I been able to easily correct. I was a faculty member for twenty years and even though I still hold my rank as Professor, I have not had the opportunity to teach during this past year. Being out of the classroom is a void that needs to be filled at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not knowing the name of a faculty member became an issue early on. During my first year I was accused of not saying “hello” to a faculty member at a public event. Quite honestly, I had only been in the position for two months and probably had not met the faculty member, or if I had, only once; however, that was not the expectation. Lesson learned! I can do something about that. So I grabbed a visual directory from our marketing folks and began studying it. Faculty who avoided me found an appointment in my office for a one-on-one. Those one-on-one meetings are extremely valuable. I did this as a dean and am flummoxed that I am only now realizing that I need to do this as a VCAA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sphere of Influence:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I’ve learned that many of those ideas I thought I would implement “if only I were the VCAA” were not feasible. Ivy Tech Community College is a state-wide system of campuses. While we have some regional autonomy, there are many statewide policy decisions that as an officer of the college I am required to enforce. The line between my regional role and my requirement to maintain our statewide curriculum and policy is thin - razor thin at times. The nice part about my current position is that if I disagree with a policy (which I often do), my voice is now heard. This is the first time in my higher education career that I have had that feeling. That doesn’t mean I can’t make regional changes though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meetings:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
One simple, but well received, change was to decrease the number of meetings for faculty. I want our faculty to have more time for their students and their craft. I have been to many a faculty meeting that was not productive nor a good use of my time. I didn’t want this for our faculty so I decided I would not prepare an annual faculty meeting schedule. We have no regularly scheduled faculty meetings, save for our very first meeting at the beginning of the semester. Meetings fall on our calendars only when we need them and only with the faculty who need to be there. When meetings do occur, they are well attended, productive, honest and open. One of my favorite compliments received this year was from a faculty member who said, “I like your meetings…I like your no B.S. style” – in other words they were telling me to not be a politician, but to be honest and make meetings useful. I can honestly say that I am much better at this as a VCAA than I was as a dean, but I still have a bit of work to do as we will see in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summing up:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
That does it for my first post where I discuss the cursory differences between being a dean and a regional academic officer. As is true with most of my writing, this isn’t a deep look into the nuances, but just a couple of quick thoughts. Be on the look out in the near future for the second lesson in the series and in the meantime, as I mentioned earlier, feel free to drop your comments below. I look forward to reading them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Create an ssh connection to a headless Raspberry Pi</title>
   <link href="/raspberrypi/apple/linux/2013/04/27/create-ssh-connection-from-your-mac-to.html"/>
   <updated>2013-04-27T07:10:09-04:00</updated>
   <id>/raspberrypi/apple/linux/2013/04/27/create-ssh-connection-from-your-mac-to</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You finally receive that Raspberry Pi you&amp;rsquo;ve been waiting for only to find that you don&amp;rsquo;t have an extra keyboard, mouse or monitor laying around. Yeah, you should have taken care of that prior to the purchase (or maybe you did and those items are on their way in a separate order), but does that mean you can&amp;rsquo;t fiddle with your new Raspberry Pi? Of course not. While waiting on the other devices, you can have a ton of fun learning about the new device while at the same time, learning a bit about Linux and remote connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-NjsjbCYtA8Y/UXwPS_XqaKI/AAAAAAABIlM/ztfeD2wMg-A/w770-h557-no/ssh+to+raspi.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Remote connection you ask?&amp;rdquo; Yep! You can run the Raspberry Pi headless. &amp;ldquo;Headless. What&amp;rsquo;s that? Something out of a zombie show?&amp;rdquo; Uh, no. Find out more about &amp;ldquo;headless mode&amp;rdquo; after the break and then read my step-by-step guide on how to setup this mode using a Mac and OS X. Warning, Terminal; commands ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Stuff you need&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, let&amp;rsquo;s make sure you have everything you need. Gather all the items below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mac computer connected to home network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raspberry Pi (any model, although model B gives you a bit more head room).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raspberry Pi power supply (I do not recommend using USB power from computer, but this will work in a pinch).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4GB or larger SD card (class 4 or better).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USB or internal SD card reader (Internal found on some MacBook Pros, Mac minis and iMacs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RJ45/Ethernet cable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will also need a Raspberry Pi OS distribution (or distro), I&amp;rsquo;ll recommend one a bit later. Before we dive in, below is the list of tasks we will perform. Each task will be described in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select an OS distro for the Raspberry Pi.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install an OS on SD card.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the Raspberry Pi to a network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boot up the Raspberry Pi.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine the address of the Raspberry Pi.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect to the Raspberry Pi via secure socket shell (ssh).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poke around the Raspberry Pi using ssh.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds complicated, but if you follow closely, and I haven&amp;rsquo;t botched up my directions, you should be able to hack around with your Raspberry Pi until the keyboard, mouse, and monitor arrive. You may even decide that you really don&amp;rsquo;t need these additional peripherals once you see what you can do without them. Alright, let&amp;rsquo;s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;Select an OS distro for the Raspberry Pi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may not be aware of this, but there are several operating system (OS) distributions (distros) available that work with the Raspberry Pi. For readers new to this whole concept, the OS is the software that allows the hardware to function and do &amp;ldquo;things.&amp;rdquo; Think Windows, OS X or Linux. A distro is simply a variation or flavor of the OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proprietary OSs like Windows or OS X do not have distros available. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linux.org/&quot;&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt;, on the other hand, has several. Linux is free and open source (all the programming code is open for review and modification) and there are many groups of programmers/foundations that create specialized distros for specific applications on the desktop, servers and embedded controllers. These features make Linux OS the perfect candidate for the Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raspberry Pi distros must be lightweight given the small amount of random access memory (RAM) available (256MB on the Model A and 512 MB on the Model B). We are also looking for a distro that supports all of the onboard components of the Raspberry Pi as well as a healthy list of external USB devices that you may want to connect later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for us, we don&amp;rsquo;t need to go hunting for an OS. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi download page&lt;/a&gt; provides a list of compatible distros that we can use. As good as this list is though, I am going to use and recommend a distro from another source; &lt;a href=&quot;http://adafruit.com/&quot;&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt;. Without getting into the entirety of Adafruit&amp;rsquo;s business, they are simply a provider of electronic devices, tutorials and software designed to teach electronics and provide the tools Makers and Hackers need to create amazing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of particular interest to us is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://learn.adafruit.com/adafruit-raspberry-pi-educational-linux-distro&quot;&gt;Adafruit Raspberry Pi Educational Linux Distro&lt;/a&gt; (as of this writing named Occidentalis and at &lt;a href=&quot;http://draft.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=2984947566836492313&quot;&gt;version 0.2&lt;/a&gt;). Here&amp;rsquo;s how Adafruit describes their distro:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our distro is based on &amp;ldquo;Wheezy&amp;rdquo; but comes with hardware SPI, I2C, one wire, and WiFi support for our wifi adapters. It also has some things to make overall hacking easier such sshd on startup (with key generation on first boot) and Bonjour (so you can simply ssh raspberrypi.local from any computer on the local network)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s that last line that makes this distro perfect for our project. I&amp;rsquo;ll explain this a bit later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Install an OS on an SD card&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a distro identified and we now need to install it on an SD card. There are many ways to do this. One of the more popular ways is to use Terminal commands. I have a very &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/apple/2009/05/27/create-bootable-usb-drive-osx&quot;&gt;popular post that describes this process&lt;/a&gt; in detail but it can be quite daunting for someone new to Linux and terminal commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this task easier, we are going to use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://alltheware.wordpress.com/2012/12/11/easiest-way-sd-card-setup/&quot;&gt;RPi-sd card builder v1.2&lt;/a&gt;. This application makes it easy to install a distro (in .img format) on an SD. Let&amp;rsquo;s get started:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file is 2.6GB so be prepared to wait a bit. I was unable to locate a torrent of the file. A torrent would speed the download significantly so it might be worth checking before you download.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place the SD card into the internal or external USB SD card reader on your Mac.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If asked to format your SD card, do nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch RPi-sd – RPi-sd will prompt you to choose the Occidentalis.img file downloaded earlier as shown in the image below:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-yAAekyttYGI/UXwI8U3mArI/AAAAAAABIks/HzrEKBVm4pc/s400/Choose+Image.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locate and select the distro image file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the Choose button – RPi-sd will ask you to verify that the SD Card is connected as shown in the image below:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-NyClIrY5-Vw/UXwI8OT85rI/AAAAAAABIkk/enIvVKcAXyk/s400/SD+Card+Connected.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RPi-sd will display a selection window as shown below– choose the SD card (if you only have one SD card attached, it will be the only listed option).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-YscPa5uHDmc/UXwI8ID7qPI/AAAAAAABIko/Q7nJPpx3BKs/s400/Select+SD+Card.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the Mac&amp;rsquo;s administrators password when prompted and select the OK button - RPi-sd will eject the SD Card automatically and then prompt you to wait.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click Continue - RPi-sd will display a gear, but no status, in the menu bar to indicate that the process is underway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once RPi-sd install process is complete, it will remount the SD card indicating the SD card is ready.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received a script error and worried my distro did not install on the SD card; however, when I tried the SD card in the Raspberry Pi, it worked fine so ignore this error if it appears and give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Connect the Raspberry Pi to a network&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have an OS on the SD card, we are about ready to fire up our new Raspberry Pi. Before we do, we need to connect it to our home network:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure the Raspberry Pi is NOT connected to a power source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert the SD card into the Raspberry Pi - the slot is on the bottom and may not be readily apparent to new users (there&amp;rsquo;s an image below to guide new users).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect an RJ45 cable to the Raspberry Pi.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the other end of the RJ45 cable to your home router - if you don&amp;rsquo;t have convenient access to your home router, follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docstechnotes.com/2013/04/and-in-weve-got-yet-another-new-look.html&quot;&gt;these directions&lt;/a&gt; to connect the ethernet cable to your Mac&amp;rsquo;s available ethernet port instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-x4G34sHG9V0/UXwO1nDLF3I/AAAAAAABIlE/qKeh0Re-vP4/s400/Ports.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are now ready to boot up the Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;Boot up the Raspberry Pi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Raspberry Pi does not include a power button. You plug it in, it&amp;rsquo;s on. Let&amp;rsquo;s cross our fingers and do this now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect a USB power cable to the micro USB port on the Raspberry Pi
Once you connect the power cable, you should see a series of lights blinking (their location is indicated in the previous image).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since no monitor is connected, you will not have an indication that the Raspberry Pi boot process is complete. The normal boot time for this distribution is about 30 seconds, but wait 60 seconds for this first boot. In some cases you may notice that the lights cease to blink, however; this is not a clear indication the boot process is complete; so stick to time rather than blinking lights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only clear way to know if the Raspberry Pi is operational is to hook up a monitor, but that would defeat the purpose of what we are trying to do. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, you&amp;rsquo;ll know if everything works in the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_5&quot;&gt;Determine the address of the Raspberry Pi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose the Adafruit linux distro for the Raspberry Pi for a specific reason. Below is a salient line from the distro description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also has some things to make overall hacking easier such sshd on startup (with key generation on first boot) and Bonjour (so you can simply &lt;code&gt;ssh raspberrypi.local&lt;/code&gt; from any computer on the local network).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally to connect via ssh, you need an IP address. This isn&amp;rsquo;t too difficult to determine; however, the Adafruit distro removes this requirement. As soon as the Raspberry Pi starts up, a service built into the distro, called Bonjour, obtains the IP address from a router and announces the computer on the network as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;raspberrypi.local&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what IP address the router assigns the Raspberry Pi, as long as you are on the same local network (attached to the same router in our case), you can use the &lt;code&gt;raspberrypi.local&lt;/code&gt; address to connect rather than an IP address. Slick and very convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_6&quot;&gt;Connect to the Raspberry Pi via secure socket shell (ssh)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try and connect to our Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the Mac, launch Terminal. The Terminal app is in Applications / Utilities folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminal will present you with a bit of text and a flashing cursor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type &lt;code&gt;ssh pi@raspberrypi.local&lt;/code&gt; and follow it with a tap of the  key (or ↩) - you will be prompted for the Raspberry Pi password (Don&amp;rsquo;t panic, just keep following along).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type &lt;code&gt;raspberry&lt;/code&gt; followed by ↩ and if the password is correct, you will receive text similar to the following:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Linux raspberrypi 3.6.11+ #371 PREEMPT Thu Feb 7 16:31:35 GMT 2013 armv6l

The programs included with the Debian GNU/Linux system are free software; the exact distribution terms for each program are described in the individual files in /usr/share/doc/copyright.

Debian GNU/Linux comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY, to the extent permitted by applicable law.

Type &#39;startx&#39; to launch a graphical session

Last login: Wed Apr 24 16:16:48 2013 from imac.local

pi@raspberrypi $_
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re in! You now have access to your Raspberry Pi via the Terminal app and ssh. With this access there&amp;rsquo;s a whole bunch of fun you can have. In fact there is too much fun to describe in this blog post, but I&amp;rsquo;ll give you a couple of quick commands in the next section to get you going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_7&quot;&gt;Poke Around the Raspberry Pi Using ssh&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After your connection to the Raspberry Pi via ssh, you probably thought to yourself, &amp;ldquo;now what?&amp;rdquo; Here are a few Terminal commands you can use to hack around a bit. Type these commands and then follow each with a quick tap of ↩.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEADS UP: After you have made a successful connection to your headless Raspberry Pi, you will notice a prompt encouraging you to load a graphical user interface using the terminal command &lt;code&gt;startx&lt;/code&gt;. This will not work using ssh so don&amp;rsquo;t attempt it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; – List the contents of the current directory. Give it a try and you will see the following listing (that is, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t gone off on your own at this point).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Desktop python_games&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; – Changes the current directory. For instance, try &lt;code&gt;cd Desktop&lt;/code&gt; and now use the &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; command. You can now view the contents of the Desktop folder. It should be very similar to the listing below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;debian-reference-common.desktop lxterminal.desktop scratch.desktop

idle3.desktop midori.desktop

idle.desktop python-games.desktop&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd..&lt;/code&gt; – Changes the directory back up one level. Try this now and you will move out of the Desktop folder and back to the original location. You can verify this using the ls command again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo raspi-config&lt;/code&gt; – Loads the Raspi-Config program as shown in the image below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-CoNY1uPJOzA/UXwIJMfNZ8I/AAAAAAABIkc/3j1CK-q-7Z8/s400/Raspi-Config.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you will notice after hitting ↩ is that you must enter a password. This is a requirement of the &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;; command that prefaces the &lt;code&gt;raspi-config&lt;/code&gt; command. Think of this as Linux&amp;rsquo;s way of ensuring that you really want to mess around with configuration files that could cause your Raspberry Pi to become inoperable. You already know the password. It is the same password you use to log into the Raspberry Pi. As a reminder, the password is &lt;code&gt;raspberry&lt;/code&gt;. After you enter he password hit ↩ again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the listing above, this app is used to modify things such as keyboard layout, timezone, and overscan. You can poke around in this a bit, but I recommend that you only modify those things you understand. Other options will make sense as you become more familiar with your Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s stop there for now, but this is just the beginning of the fun and exciting world of the command line. Seriously, there is some really cool stuff you can do. We&amp;rsquo;ve become entirely too reliant on a graphical user interface and there&amp;rsquo;s a since of freedom when you know you can simply hack into a terminal window and make some pretty interesting things happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_8&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See, getting a Raspberry Pi running headless isn&amp;rsquo;t as painful as you might have thought and I guarantee is was more fun than you thought it would be. If you were like me, you got a warm fuzzy feeling the first time you realized you were actually connected to your little Raspberry Pi and that you could control the device without a physical keyboard or mouse connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this may win the prize for my longest blog post, although my blog post &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/apple/2009/05/27/create-bootable-usb-drive-osx&quot;&gt;Create a bootable USB drive&lt;/a&gt; is awfully close. Given the length, and my inability to edit my own writing, please drop a comment below if you find errors. I would also love to read about your experiences, so drop those too. Happy ssh&amp;#39;ing!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A productivity primer for higher education administrators</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/03/03/A-productivity-primer-for-higher-education-administrators.html"/>
   <updated>2013-03-03T23:49:23Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/03/03/A-productivity-primer-for-higher-education-administrators</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-cEkUuUsA4g4/UTJSV25O7nI/AAAAAAABG2U/-uETIC_O5yM/s200/Empty+Inbox.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;We conduct cabinet meetings on our campus each Monday. Our Chancellor develops the agenda and leads these discussions between our regional academic administrators. Typically these meetings are a simple sharing of information between our team leaders. On occasion we invite college and community leaders to meet with the team to understand important initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A unique twist is that once a month, the Chancellor asks a cabinet member to provide a professional development activity. The cabinet member does not have to personally conduct the activity. They can farm it out to someone on their team or bring in someone from the community. This month, the task falls to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I have a large number of faculty on our Academic Affairs team that I can ask to lead a session, given that I am new to the cabinet, I felt it appropriate that I take my turn at bat. Folks who know me can probably predict the topic of my presentation (or have read the title of this post). I have this odd obsession. I constantly refine my productivity workflow. I’ve gone through a countless number of tools and processes to find a system that works for me in my given environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my presentation I share some tools to get my fellow administrators thinking about their own productivity workflow. There is not a one-size fits all solution. Everyone has their own specific needs. My presentation provides some simple and advanced tools for consideration. It’s an eclectic mix. You can check out my slides and links to all the tools I mention below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of my presentation is &lt;em&gt;Productivity Tools Primer&lt;/em&gt;. The focus of the presentation is two-fold. This presentation is around 30 minutes and was presented to the cabinet on March 4th, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a primer, I quickly provide a bunch of tools I find useful day-in and day-out. I have many other tools I would love to share, but with only 30 minutes, I focus on the obvious and then discuss a couple of concepts that most likely none of the cabinet will use. My intention is not to encourage them to use these tools, but rather to consider other advanced options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, a review of the slides and the links below are not enough for readers of this blog post to glean all concepts. For that you need to hear the entire presentation. If you are interested in an expanded presentation &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:steven.combs@gmail.com&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;389&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1al8NGIUJwU_KPH0Zu72V5ie38ahYqqvWHC3YGGGNVcw/embed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; width=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Slide 1 - Title&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/&quot;&gt;StevenCombs.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;Slide 2 - Get a System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0142000280/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0142000280&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=bricinmypockb-20&amp;amp;linkId=7TLAVZ6TY6BY355Q&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Getting Things Done&lt;/em&gt; by David Allen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.davidco.com/&quot;&gt;GTD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Slide 3 - Inbox Zero&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://inboxzero.com/&quot;&gt;Inbox Zero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Slide 4 - Evernote Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/&quot;&gt;Evernote Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;Slide 5 - Evernote Computer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/evernote/id406056744?mt=12&quot;&gt;Evernote Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/download/get.php?file=Win&quot;&gt;Evernote Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://apps.microsoft.com/webpdp/app/evernote/5aba7f8c-318f-42aa-9590-b1fc31e5cba6&quot;&gt;Windows Touch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_5&quot;&gt;Slide 6 - Evernote Mobile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://appstore.com/evernote/evernote/&quot;&gt;Evernote iOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://market.android.com/details?id=com.evernote&quot;&gt;Evernote Android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://appworld.blackberry.com/webstore/content/1700&quot;&gt;Evernote Blackberry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.windowsphone.com/en-US/apps/db21927d-f292-e011-986b-78e7d1fa76f8&quot;&gt;Evernote Windows Phone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_6&quot;&gt;Slide 7 - Evernote Extension&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/download/get.php?file=SafariExtension&quot;&gt;Safari&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/extensions/detail/pioclpoplcdbaefihamjohnefbikjilc##&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/firefox/addon/evernote-web-clipper/&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/webclipper/##&quot;&gt;Bookmarklet for other browsers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_7&quot;&gt;Slide 10 - Evernote Trunk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://trunk.evernote.com/&quot;&gt;Evernote Trunk on the Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_8&quot;&gt;Slide 11 - Evernote Notebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/Ork4J&quot;&gt;Evernote Notebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_9&quot;&gt;Slide 12 - Freemium/Premium?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/premium/&quot;&gt;Evernote Premium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_10&quot;&gt;Slide 13 - Pocket on the Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/&quot;&gt;Pocket on the Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/safari/&quot;&gt;Pocket for Safari&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/chrome/&quot;&gt;Pocket for Chrome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/firefox/&quot;&gt;Pocket for Firefox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/q3PYR&quot;&gt;Pocket for other browsers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_11&quot;&gt;Slide 14 - Pocket Apps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/desktop/&quot;&gt;Pocket Desktop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/iphone/&quot;&gt;Pocket iOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/android/&quot;&gt;Pocket Android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/windowsphone/&quot;&gt;Pocket Window Phone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/blackberry/&quot;&gt;Pocket Blackberry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_12&quot;&gt;Slide 15 - RSS Feeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://reader.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt; - deprecated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://newsify.co/&quot;&gt;Newsify for iOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_13&quot;&gt;Slide 16 - Find a Feed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/reader/view/##directory-page/1&quot;&gt;Google RSS Search&lt;/a&gt; - deprecated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theverge.com/&quot;&gt;The Verge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_14&quot;&gt;Slide 17 - Google Drive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://drive.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_15&quot;&gt;Slide 18 - Waze (Social Nav)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.waze.com/&quot;&gt;Waze with links to Apps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_16&quot;&gt;Slide 19 - Plain Text&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.barebones.com/products/bbedit/&quot;&gt;BBEdit for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://brettterpstra.com/projects/nvalt/&quot;&gt;nvALT for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://notepad-plus-plus.org/&quot;&gt;Notepad++ for Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.secondgearsoftware.com/elements/&quot;&gt;Elements for iOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.kooklab.epistle&amp;amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Epistle for Android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_17&quot;&gt;Slide 20 - Markdown&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fletcherpenney.net/multimarkdown/&quot;&gt;MultiMarkdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://multimarkdown.com/&quot;&gt;MultiMarkdown Composer for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.barebones.com/products/bbedit/&quot;&gt;BBEdit for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://markedapp.com/&quot;&gt;Marked for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_18&quot;&gt;Slide 21 - Addendum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smilesoftware.com/TextExpander/&quot;&gt;TextExpander for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://textexpanderwindows.com/&quot;&gt;Text Expander Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.google.com/p/autokey/&quot;&gt;Autokey for Linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alfredapp.com/&quot;&gt;Alfred for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.launchy.net/&quot;&gt;Launchy for Windows, Mac and Linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See something useful in the slides and/or the list above? Want to add your own productivity tips to assist my fellow higher education administrators? Drop a comment below. I’m always looking for new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Indiana legislation all faculty should understand</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/01/15/Indiana-legislation-all-faculty-should-understand.html"/>
   <updated>2013-01-15T19:55:02Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/01/15/Indiana-legislation-all-faculty-should-understand</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-uJv26_0PsEc/UIl-2GvgphI/AAAAAAABDK0/nFSTYPaxMJ8/s200/StateLegislation.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;On January 15th, 2013, our Regional Board of Trustees met. I am on the agenda to discuss the changes that will occur within the state with regard to transfer of general education credits among the public institutions. As I read the two pieces of legislation, House Enrolled Act No. 1220 (Credit Creep) and Senate Enrolled Act No. 182 (Common Course Numbering within the Core Transfer Library), the thought struck me that all Indiana higher education faculty (and parents for that matter)&amp;nbsp;should be aware of these initiatives and understand their implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legislation is not difficult to read; however, I need to provide an Executive Summary for the board, so I thought I may as well share my outline. My bullets are more concise and a bit more “bottom line up front.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Transfer Changes Board Report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two important pieces of legislation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;House Enrolled Act No. 1220 (Credit Creep)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Senate Enrolled Act No. 182 (Common Course Numbering within the Core Transfer Library)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Details:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HEA 1220:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each public institution will review all programs and reduce associate degrees to 60 credit hours and baccalaureate degree to 120 credit hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If institutions cannot meet these requirements, they must document and justify the reason (accreditation, certification, etc) in a proposal to the commission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No deadline specified in the legislation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SEA 182:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create and maintain a common course numbering system for the core transfer library (CTL) of general education competencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each public institution will map their unique CTL course numbers to a new common course numbering system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not later than December 1st, 2012, the state institutions, in conjunction with the Higher Learning Commission, will provide a report on statewide transfer of the general education core&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The core will be competency based and at least 30 credit hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Institutions will work together to create the Transfer General Education Core (TGEC) via the State Transfer and Articulation Committee (STAC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Further, the institutions will establish a way to document completion of the competencies on student transcripts – in the case of Ivy Tech Community College, it will be the Technical Certification (TC) in General Studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After May 15th, 2013 a student who completes the TGEC will not be required by another state institution to complete additional courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students who do not complete the TGEC prior to transfer, will complete the remainder of the requirements at the new institution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students who receive an associate of art or associate of science degree meet the minimum required 30 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.in.gov/legislative/bills/2012/HE/HE1220.1.html&quot;&gt;House Enrolled Act No. 1220&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.in.gov/legislative/bills/2012/SE/SE0182.1.html&quot;&gt;Senate Enrolled Act No. 182&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.transferin.net/&quot;&gt;TransferIN.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Community college quality versus cost</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/01/14/Community-college-quality-versus-cost.html"/>
   <updated>2013-01-14T21:38:03Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/01/14/Community-college-quality-versus-cost</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-58b-dlaZFUI/UPRsGGTDRHI/AAAAAAABFq0/11iWjBLyWR8/s200/Screen+Shot+2013-01-14+at+3.34.48+PM.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;Community colleges have several stigmas. One in particular is a sticky-wicket. That being cost. We strive to maintain a low cost for our students. We pride ourselves on being the most affordable college in the state. Then THAT question pops up, “How can a program that costs so little have quality?” I’ve heard this referred to as the Wal-Mart syndrome. Sure you can go and buy the same product and save a few bucks, but is the entire experience worth the time spent? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our community, we face this question regularly and it is compounded by the fact that we have a university partner next door – literally! We share a campus, parking lot, library and even adjunct faculty; however, if you were to survey our community, most would probably state that the quality and rigor of the product next door was greater and of better value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the regional academic officer for our campus, I am always taken aback be these claims. I know them to be inaccurate. From my days teaching at a four-year institution, I know my rigor and quality did not change as soon as I hit the community college door. More perplexing is that these comments often come from folks who have no experience with our product, culture or student body. They have a university experience and that is “just better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an effort to get the word out, our Chancellor prepared an op ed piece to better communicate our product and message. You can find it after the click below. I like what he has to say and I bet that when people read the piece they will be surprised by the quality of our programs and students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After your review, feel free to drop a comment and add your thoughts to the debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ivy Tech Quality Is Second To None&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
By Dr. John Hogan&lt;br&gt;
Chancellor, Ivy Tech Community College  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ivy Tech Community College is celebrating its 50th anniversary this year. We’re certainly proud of our heritage – but equally proud of how far we’ve come as an institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ivy Tech has grown to become the largest singly accredited community college in the nation. We are the largest post-secondary institution in the state. More freshmen are enrolled at Ivy Tech (18,564) than at Indiana University Bloomington (4,695), Purdue University West Lafayette (3,434), Ball State University (3,159), Indiana State University (3,175), and IUPUI (3,106) combined. Forty-one percent of the state’s freshman class is enrolled at Ivy Tech Community College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to providing the front door to higher education, through which students can earn an associate degree for less than half the cost of the first two years at most universities and then continue to work toward a bachelor’s degree at the university of their choice, Ivy Tech also provides educational instruction of the highest quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud of our faculty. Many hold doctorates in their respective fields. All other full-time faculty teaching our freshman and sophomore level classes are required to hold no less than a master’s degree in the field in which they teach. Our adjunct professors possess full academic credentials and also work in their fields. This provides students an opportunity to learn from professionals currently in the workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence of high quality is incontrovertible. For example, Ivy Tech’s RN students complete a two-year associate of science degree, then sit for the NCLEX licensure exam. Four-year nursing program graduates take the same exam. Columbus nursing graduates passed this exam at a rate of 96% in the first quarter and 98% in the second. These are among the very highest marks in the state, including those from four-year universities! Columbus surgical technology graduates passed their licensure exam at a rate of 100% for the second straight year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to provide students with an education with credits that transfer, institutions must be accredited. Ivy Tech is accredited by the North Central Association, which oversees accreditation of colleges and universities in 19 states. The process of attaining and maintaining accreditation is rigorous. As a result of the high quality of instruction at Ivy Tech and the fact that its programs are accredited, the state’s research universities all accept Ivy Tech credits and continue to partner with us to create even more pathways for Ivy Tech graduates who want to pursue bachelor’s degrees and further their education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The School of Art and Design holds program accreditation from one of the most stringent and prestigious bodies in academe, the National Association for Schools of Art and Design. Our program is one of only seven other community colleges in the nation to receive this accreditation. Our paramedic science program was the very first in south central Indiana and among Ivy Tech’s 14 regions to receive recognition from its accrediting body, the Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Education Programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are equally proud of our students and graduates. Research has shown that Ivy Tech graduates who transfer as juniors to universities are more successful than those who started at the university as freshmen. Our graduates have gone on to become knowledgeable and dedicated leaders in their fields. Last year, over 800 area residents transferred university credit from Ivy Tech in Columbus, a number that nearly doubles every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our sister institutions have come to realize that the rigor at Ivy Tech is no less than that which students would experience at their university. Our students handle the same responsibilities as do their students—they write research papers, attend lectures, run experiments, give speeches, and do homework. They also create friendships, have fun, learn from one another, participate in clubs, play intramural sports, and develop a love for Ivy Tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be no secret that Ivy Tech is the most affordable college in Indiana. But offering a more affordable education doesn’t equate to offering a lower quality education. Our mission is to offer a high quality education at an affordable price for individuals in our service area. We have striven to do just that and believe that we have succeeded. We look forward to continuing to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Apple TV in the classroom</title>
   <link href="/presentations/higher-education/apple/2013/01/14/Apple-TV-Out-of-the-living-room-and-into-the-classroom.html"/>
   <updated>2013-01-14T19:51:19Z</updated>
   <id>/presentations/higher-education/apple/2013/01/14/Apple-TV-Out-of-the-living-room-and-into-the-classroom</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Monday, October 22nd, I was the presenter for a local brown-bag at the Columbus Learning Center for the three institutions of higher education on our shared campus: Ivy Tech Community College, IUPUC and Purdue College of Technology. The topic of my presentation is the use of the TV in the Classroom. See, even Vice Chancellors can stay current in the use of instructional technologies!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post provides the slides used for that presentation as well as the presentation outline. If you have something to add or a comment about the content, please drop in a comment after the post. Check out the entire presentation content after the break below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Docs Presentation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;389&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/embed?id=1Ywc5m3WcT-Ldl0YASB2FqBRnZ91X2auxKxNWiD0DAmY&amp;amp;start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; width=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presentation Notes: TV - &lt;em&gt;Out of the Living Room and into the Classroom&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agenda (slide 2):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This 45 minute presentation will discuss the Apple TV and its use in the classroom. Major topics include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why Apple TV (TV)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remote Control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Out of the Box Capabilities and Demonstration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AirPlay Demonstration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networking Requirements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Questions and Discussion ♫&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background music before presentation provided by TV Radio, Classical, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.radionomy.com/en/radio/a1900-classical&quot;&gt;A1900 Classical&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why an TV (slide 3):&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ubiquitous nature iOS devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Student friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ease of use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WirelessCost (Entire secure setup for around $250)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hardware (slide 4–5):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Below is a list of the hardware you may need based on your classroom:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/YWrer&quot;&gt;Apple TV, $99&lt;/a&gt; - the subject of our presentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/ztiSV&quot;&gt;ATV Pro, $45&lt;/a&gt; - converts from HDMI to RGB and audio for older projectors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/IYnEq&quot;&gt;HDMI Cable, 2 for $10&lt;/a&gt; - newer projectors will only require the HDMI cable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remote Control (slide 6):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
You can control the Apple TV with the following devices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple Remote (included with TV)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/BGuAf&quot;&gt;Remote app, Free&lt;/a&gt; for iPhone/iPod Touch/iPad (iOS devices)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out of the Box Capabilities (slide 7) and Demonstration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Without a connection to any other device, the TV provides the following features to enhance instruction (brainstorming time!):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moves/TV Shows/Music from the Apple Store&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to iTunes content on other computers (iTunes required on local network)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Netflix &amp;amp; Hulu Plus (subscription required)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MLB.TV, NBA &amp;amp; NHL (subscription required)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TrailersYouTubeVimeoPodcasts - Personal favorite for education is access to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ted.com/talks&quot;&gt;TED Talks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Radio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photo Stream and Flickr&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wall Street Journal Live&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More to come from Apple…all apps can be removed from the homescreen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AirPlay Demonstration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
AirPlay is the process of transmitting audio, video and apps to the TV. The following are discussed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iOS Devices (iPhone and iPad) - AirPlay Music (Music app) and Video (YouTube app) demonstrations from iPhone 4S, Mirroring (iPhone 4S or greater or new iPad required) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/skitch/id490505997?mt=8&quot;&gt;Skitch&lt;/a&gt; demonstration from iPhone 4S&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://draft.blogger.com/goo.gl/L6L23&quot;&gt;PlayTo for Android&lt;/a&gt; - No device mirroring (to achieve mirroring, the device must be “rooted” and the appropriate app downloaded from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://play.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OS X Integration - Basic connection functionality built into OS X Mountain Lion only&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://airparrot.com/&quot;&gt;AirParrot for OS X&lt;/a&gt; - Adds AirPlay to all Macs and adds additional functionality such as full desktop (scaled), extended desktop and by applicationA quick word about security - Passcode can be set and device connected cannot be bumped by another device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network Requirements:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The TV has the following network requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All devices must be on the same network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wi-Fi and Wired connections supported&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;802.11n preferred for wireless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network traffic affects performance and a dedicated classroom network using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/pOsCC&quot;&gt;$99 AirPort Express&lt;/a&gt; would be preferable. This layout will also decrease interference with other classrooms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions and Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Enhance Course Materials with iTunes U</title>
   <link href="/presentations/higher-education/apple/2013/01/10/Enhance-Course-Materials-with-iTunes-U.html"/>
   <updated>2013-01-10T01:09:10Z</updated>
   <id>/presentations/higher-education/apple/2013/01/10/Enhance-Course-Materials-with-iTunes-U</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hot on the heels of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/2012/10/tv-out-of-living-room-and-into-classroom.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Apple TV: “Out of the Living Room and into the Classroom”&lt;/em&gt; presentation&lt;/a&gt;, I have prepared another entitled, &lt;em&gt;Enhance Course Materials with iTunes U&lt;/em&gt;. This presentation was held on January 10th, 2013 from 12:00 - 1:00PM in Poling Hall, Room 201 on the Ivy Tech Columbus campus. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DmCzV7LBG-k/UO35pceB4_I/AAAAAAABFog/GBBJDrZtvpA/s400/iTunes+U.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, you will find my presentation outline that includes all the links (and a few more) shared during my 45 minute talk. As always, feel free to add comments or ask questions using the comments section at the bottom of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Welcome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About the presentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who are the Mac, iPad or iPhone users in the room?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who are the PC users in the room?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;iTunes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gateway to iTunes U&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/itunes&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt; available for Mac and PC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iTunes features include:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Music - search, purchase and download music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movies - search, purchase and download movies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV Shows - search, purchase and download TV Shows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;App Store - search, purchase and download iOS apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Books - search, purchase books to read in iBooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcasts - search and subscribe to podcasts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iTunes U - search and subscribe to educational content (the main topic of today’s conversation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link to iTunes content to share online or within a course management system system such as Blackboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locate and create a link demonstration - the secret sauce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;iTunes U&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gateway to amazing, and free, instructional resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessible through iTunes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content from a wide variety of K–12 and higher education providers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review all content entirely before adding to your own course materials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/itunesu/&quot;&gt;Follow iTunes U on twitter&lt;/a&gt; to learn about new content additions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn more on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/education/itunes-u/&quot;&gt;Apple iTunes U page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Sample iTunes U Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at some unique iTunes U content available for your course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/highlights/id420424352?mt=10&quot;&gt;Duke University Libraries Ad Views&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/origins-american-animation/id386017694?mt=10&quot;&gt;Library of Congress – Origins of American Animation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/hidden-treasures-at-library/id391498646?mt=10&quot;&gt;Library of Congress – Hidden Treasures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/early-films-edison-companies/id386017464?mt=10&quot;&gt;Library of Congress – Early Films from the Edison Companies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;iTunes U Course Manager&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free. browser based, online content management system to consolidate iTunes U and traditional course resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunesu.itunes.apple.com/coursemanager/&quot;&gt;iTunes U Course Manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supplement your traditional course materials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to maintain and manage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does not include collaboration or assessment tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iTunes U Course Manager demonstration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-50PS6YdCD0Q/UO4RHIQ0O6I/AAAAAAABFpA/JiN-D_td6Bw/s400/iTunes+U+Course+Manager.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_5&quot;&gt;iBooks Author&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional companion product to iTunes U Course Manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ibooks-author/id490152466?mt=12&quot;&gt;Mac App Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple to use electronic book authoring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interactive components to enhance content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self publish!!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iBooks OS X &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-euUasrKRgCY/UO4QUu-p20I/AAAAAAABFow/fnqhOHtrpq4/s400/iBooks+Author.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_6&quot;&gt;iTunes U iOS App&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It all comes together for the student in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/itunes-u/id490217893?mt=8&quot;&gt;iTunes U iOS app&lt;/a&gt; for iPhone and iPad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provides access to course content including:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Course information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Course overview&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Instructor information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Course outline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; About the course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Posts - formatted weekly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Notes - consolidated and can be shared from the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Course notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audio/Video notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Materials - consolidated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Videos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Books&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iTunes U iOS app demonstration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/--LYkiCxfaHA/UO4SqS0vIOI/AAAAAAABFpU/FKwecMw4xW0/s400/iTunes+U+iOS.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_7&quot;&gt;iBooks iOS App&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to the entire collection of books in the iTunes store&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students use&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ibooks/id364709193?mt=8&quot;&gt;iBooks&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;to view the course textbook on an iPhone or iPad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iBooks demonstration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-QWx8snREerQ/UO4SqZwFZxI/AAAAAAABFpY/LzTLr0Nk-SM/s400/iBooks+iOS.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_8&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its free, so give it a try&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include a few resources from iTunes U within your current course materials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slowly add resources to a closed course within the iTunes U Course Manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finalize and publish your course for students to access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self publish your own textbook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drop a comment below and share your experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_9&quot;&gt;Questions and Discussion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional Resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/education/resources/&quot;&gt;Apple educational resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/education/itunes-u/&quot;&gt;Apple iTunes U page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://edseminars.apple.com/itunesu_webcast_series/&quot;&gt;iTunes University WebCast series:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunesu.itunes.apple.com/enroll/E36-Q43-5WC!&quot;&gt;My Agricultural Data Management demonstration course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bookmark/Share this page: &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/Lzivh&quot;&gt;http://goo.gl/Lzivh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review – The Unofficial LEGO Builder’s Guide 2nd Edition</title>
   <link href="/lego/2012/12/09/book-review-unofficial-lego.html"/>
   <updated>2012-12-09T07:12:12-05:00</updated>
   <id>/lego/2012/12/09/book-review-unofficial-lego</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PmxKja42FPM/UMUCGXYfaQI/AAAAAAABExA/EMH2na1uhV8/s200/BimP+Book+Review+Graphic.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;As most folks know, I am a huge fan of the first edition of Allan Bedford&amp;rsquo;s wonderful The Unofficial LEGO Builder&amp;rsquo;s Guide. Back when Nikki and I were still hosting the BimPCast, we had Allan join us to discuss his new book in BimPCast 24. Wanna listen to our discussion? Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/JMFZS&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine my thrill when I learned Allan was in the process of updating the book to a second edition. Further imagine my thrill when No Starch press contacted me and asked if I would be interested in a review copy. &amp;ldquo;Of course!&amp;rdquo; I replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what changes did Allan need to make to the first edition? The book was already a treasure trove of LEGO building goodness and although it was six years old, it was not a book I consider &amp;ldquo;out of date.&amp;rdquo; Turns out that there was room to make this book even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after the click below, let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at the new edition, discuss whether first edition owners should upgrade and if the book remains the de facto standard for any self respecting AFOL&amp;rsquo;s bookshelf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Book Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; The Unofficial LEGO Builder&amp;rsquo;s Guide: Second Edition
&lt;strong&gt;Publication Date:&lt;/strong&gt; November 2012&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Allan Bedford
&lt;strong&gt;Illustrator:&lt;/strong&gt; Eric Albrecht
&lt;strong&gt;Publisher:&lt;/strong&gt; No Starch Press
&lt;strong&gt;Retail Cost:&lt;/strong&gt; $24.95
&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/F8Nou&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Paper:&lt;/strong&gt; $15.35&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/0zsrU&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Kindle:&lt;/strong&gt; $9.95&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Editorial Note:&lt;/strong&gt; My review will focus on the changes from the first to the second edition. There are many other reviews online that review the text as if it is a first edition. I believe most of our readers will want to know whether they should upgrade to this new edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;In Full Color&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-6srvFQEblxM/UMUC4PkMAGI/AAAAAAABExQ/y-fO5dFz-_g/s1600/Screen+Shot+2012-12-09+at+4.28.38+PM.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s begin our review with the major change that is immediately apparent when comparing to the first edition – the use of full color. There is even a banner in the upper right-hand of the title page to highlight this new change. One of the only suggestions I had for the first edition was to include color to make it easier to understand the models and techniques. I was very happy to see this occur in this new edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The images aren&amp;rsquo;t simply a reprint from the first edition, they are newly rendered images courtesy of Eric &amp;ldquo;Blakbird&amp;rdquo; Albrecht. The image updates are bright and colorful. The paper stock used is slick to ensure the images are crisp and clear. The image below provides a quick sample of a before and after page, or close approximation since the pagination is different for this new version. You will immediately notice how much easier the tube, in figure 3.5, is to visualize with color and the enhanced photo realistic rendering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-SNwSBpiesfg/UMUF9fVhucI/AAAAAAABExg/Ryix_vH6ZqQ/s640/BW-Color+Comparison.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click for larger view
What makes these images even more amazing is that Eric created and rendered these images using mostly free software. I won&amp;rsquo;t give away his secrets, since they are listed in the back of the book, but suffice it to say that these tools provide some amazing results that can be duplicated by AFOLs everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Another Obvious Visual Change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-xNCEBcOOXlA/UMUCP10ub1I/AAAAAAABExI/-KYjgvniO5A/s320/Book+Thickness+Comparison.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;Another noticeable difference between the two versions is the thickness of the book and the number of pages. Both of which you would expect to be greater in a second edition; however, that is the complete opposite for this text. The second edition is thinner, lighter and has fewer pages. The first edition contains 319 pages and the second 221 pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the reader might immediately assume that 100 pages of content were removed (we will look at this in the next section below), the change in page count is also attributed to a more efficient layout, a change in paper stock thickness and the removal of excess words to make sentences more concise. Overall the book is easier to read and much more attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Content Updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look a bit more at the content. Allan reduced the book from 13 chapters to 10 chapters. The chapters removed include: Technic, sorting and storage, and making and using LEGO tools. I completely understand the decision to remove the Technic line since those elements are really for a differing hobbyist and No Starch has &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/OataZ&quot;&gt;The Unofficial LEGO TECHNIC Builder&amp;rsquo;s Guide&lt;/a&gt; available (review coming soon). I can even live with the exclusion of the LEGO tools chapter; however, I thought sorting and storage to be one of the best chapters in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/1593270542/ref=as_li_ss_til?tag=bricinmypockb-20&amp;amp;camp=0&amp;amp;creative=0&amp;amp;linkCode=as4&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1593270542&amp;amp;adid=12N7PPCN8KKXDVAVMZ5G&amp;amp;&quot;&gt;the first edition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorting and storage is an oft discussed topic in the AFOL community and while there is no one answer for every hobbyist, the inclusion of Allan&amp;rsquo;s thoughts in the first edition at least gave someone new to the hobby options to consider. I will miss this chapter and will retain my first edition specifically for this information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned in the previous section that Allan employed some efficiencies in writing style and clarity. As an example of what I mean, take a look at the line below from the first edition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Although not the most common way to build, and usually not the sturdiest, at times, stacking bricks one on top of the other is necessary.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sentence is 25 words and 139 characters. Now look at this sentence in the second edition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Although not the most common or sturdiest way to build, stacking bricks one on top of the other can be necessary.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new, more readable, sentence comes in at 21 words and 114 characters. As you can see, with rewrites such as these, the page count was bound to be less and the content easier to read. I applaud Allan and his editorial team for thoroughly scrubbing the text and making it more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;Recommendation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are an AFOL or a BimP reader, you probably already own the first edition and are asking yourself whether you need to upgrade to the second edition. Normally, I would dissuade you from a second edition for a book such as this; however, in this case I&amp;rsquo;m making an exception. I highly encourage you to purchase this new edition. You will find it easier to read and more attractive. The color will also make it a great conversation piece for your coffee table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to share your old book or simply don&amp;rsquo;t want multiple copies of the majority of the information, hand the first edition down to a younger family member or someone new to the hobby. Before you do though, I recommend you make a copy of the sorting and storage information from chapter 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t own this book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/F8Nou&quot;&gt;a purchase is a &amp;ldquo;no-brainer.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; This book is perfect for the old and new builder alike. It teaches the basics of building (structure, scale, planning, and technique) that every hobbyist will find of value when finalizing their own &amp;ldquo;my own creation&amp;rdquo; (MOC). It also serves as a wonderful reference when you find yourself looking for inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve done it again Allan. You&amp;rsquo;ve created the definitive book on the basics of LEGO building. How are you gonna top this one? Gotta go. I have a tub of bricks and elements calling my name.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Thanksgiving, community colleges, and changing lives</title>
   <link href="/holiday/higher-education/2012/11/21/Thanksgiving-community-colleges-and-changing-lives.html"/>
   <updated>2012-11-21T23:17:49Z</updated>
   <id>/holiday/higher-education/2012/11/21/Thanksgiving-community-colleges-and-changing-lives</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first Thanksgiving in my new role as Vice Chancellor for
Academic Affairs. While reflecting on this yesterday, I decided to send
out the following e-mail to all of the faculty within our region:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faculty,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you head off for the Thanksgiving holiday, I wanted to let you know how much I appreciate everything you do for our students. For some this is a very difficult time of year and this can hold especially true for our students as they struggle their multiple commitments. What often happens though, is that we sometimes forget to recognize those co-workers around us who struggle as well. If you know of someone within your academic area who needs support, I do hope you will reach out to them this holiday season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what am I thankful for? Being a part of this campus and having the opportunity to serve each of you as we strive to change the lives of our students. Thank you for letting me (sic) a part of your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steven&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally I struggle when sending out mass email to faculty. I consider whether the message is relevant, beneficial, and/or productive. Once I write a message, I often go over it numerous times as I know that the English faculty are out there picking it apart for grammatical and spelling errors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an industrial background and do not have
what I would call, exceptional writing skills, as is evident by my exclusion of a word in the last line. On this occasion though, I didn’t want my message to seem contrived, but  heart felt. I decided to stream of conscious this one and just let it flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feedback from the faculty has been positive, but my absolute favorite of the bunch was from a faculty member who mentioned that they decided to go to a food bank to make a donation after they read my message. When they spent time talking with folks, they found out that several of our students were recipients of these donations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what community college service is all about folks. Changing lives and making a difference. To all of my fellow community college faculty, staff and administrators:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Happy Thanksgiving!&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The College of 2020 is a must read for administrators</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/10/25/The-College-of-2020-is-a-must-read-for-higher-education-administrators.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T19:06:28Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/10/25/The-College-of-2020-is-a-must-read-for-higher-education-administrators</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-b5Hdx01Axn4/TgJt8-Ac0MI/AAAAAAAA3CQ/dl9SQ6f62bI/s200/Screen+shot+2011-06-22+at+6.33.55+PM.PNG&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;{UPATE: This content originally appeared on a previous blog I maintained.} Before the summer of 2011 academic retreat, we were asked to do a bit of homework. Each member is to read “The College of 2020: Students” by Martin Van Der Werf and Grant Sabatier. Before I continue, you can review the document yourself using this &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/8PZBS&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This document is a Chronicle Research Services publication. There is no need to read the entire document, the Executive Summary provides the salient points. You can then dive into those areas that interest you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I read this report, I understood the need for higher education administrators and faculty to read this document, but it also struck me that this documents is a required read for parents and possibly even advanced early teens who are just now considering their higher education options. It provides some excellent insights about the future of higher education curriculum/programs, instructional technologies and finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, higher educations is changing and this document prepares us for some certain truths, of which the most interesting to me are presented below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;College tuition will rise - was there ever any question?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online education enrollment will continue to rise - again, pretty obvious?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students will look for data organizers/collectors/miners as their instructors, not orators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Community Colleges will thrive because of their cost and open access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students will require anytime enrollment instead of the traditional academic calendar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For-profit colleges will continue to become more popular as their costs become more aligned with their public competitors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give the document a closer read for the reasons why as well as the specifics. This document is due an update. With a publication date of June 2009, there is not doubt that since that time we have seen significant changes to the landscape of higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m of course always interested in your thoughts, so drop me a comment below if you’ve taken the time to read this document and have some insights.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>“O zephyr winds which blow on high...</title>
   <link href="/entertainment/2012/10/25/O-zephyr-winds-which-blow-on-high.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T19:00:40Z</updated>
   <id>/entertainment/2012/10/25/O-zephyr-winds-which-blow-on-high</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;{UPDATE: This is a repost from another blog. As those who know me can attest, I’m a bit of a sci-fi geek and love to reminisce about days of old. So enjoy this somewhat quirky post on this Saturday morning}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_CLU_mny_beA/TKCcn5YiohI/AAAAAAAAl54/ObfUckpETq0/s200/isis-flying.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;&amp;hellip;lift me now so I can fly.” Do you remember which 70s super-powered hero uttered this phrase to take flight? No? Then see if this one refreshes your memory, “Oh mighty Isis!” That’s right, a couple of years before Lynda Carter’s Wonder Woman hit the airwaves, there was another female superhero protecting teens and southern California from evil and personal injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her name was &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Secrets_of_Isis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Isis&lt;/a&gt; and after the link below, I take some time to reminisce about those early Saturday mornings shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2007, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000QQDEZG?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;tag=giveusoneminute-20&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000QQDEZG&quot;&gt;The Secrets of Isis: The Complete Series&lt;/a&gt; was released on DVD. Somehow I missed the release; although, I am not sure I would have shelled out cash for the collection. About a year ago, I became aware that the series was available on DVD and placed them into my Netflix queue. As a matter of fact, I put them at the bottom of my queue thinking I would relive some childhood memories at some point down the road. It wasn’t a priority above other items in my queue. Then something happened. A couple of days ago I was reviewing my queue and noticed that the series was now available as an instant streaming option. I couldn’t wait. I turned on the Sony Bravia (Netflix streaming built in – way cool) and loaded up the first episode. “Oh my.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-right: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_CLU_mny_beA/TKCi32pp62I/AAAAAAAAl6U/zMv8hjxrkaA/s200/isis2.jpg&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;hat, “Oh my,” is both good and bad. The good is that the series is just as I remember it as a child. JoAnna Cameron, in a dual role as Isis and Andrea Thomas (Chemistry Teacher for a southern California high school), does a great job channeling the mythical superhero. The bad is that she has to deal with 70s special effects technology, simple scripts, and horrible acting by her co-stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horrible acting does have a plus side – lots of humor for today’s viewers. Take for example a situation where a teen walks past a sign that says, “Danger, hidden mine shaft.” Bet you can’t guess what happens next! And when it does, the facial reaction of the actress falling down the shaft is priceless. Check out the episode entitled, Year of the Dragon for this laugh. Before you ask, there’s no Kung-Fu in this episode. That would be far too violent for Saturday morning television in the 70s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Isis is a mixed bag, there is some real nostalgia here and I found myself enjoying my trip back to the 70s. There are episodes including crossovers from Captain Marvel (you know, the boy who turns into a superhero by uttering the word, Shazam!) and the show really does get better with each episode, if only slightly. The last two episodes of season 2 and the series, &lt;em&gt;Now You See It&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;Now You Don’t&lt;/em&gt;, really are the pinnacle of the show and demonstrate what this show could have become with a couple of more seasons and a bigger budget. It was not to be. For some unknown reason, Isis only received two seasons and three guest shots on its sister show Shazam! Even though the popularly of the show and the character was growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_CLU_mny_beA/TKCr2CCmWAI/AAAAAAAAl7A/8Zgr2Z1z1Zk/s200/51EMJBYGD8L._SL500_AA300_.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;Isis does have a legacy though. Fans all over the web reminisce about the show, the actress and its weekly moral story (as was evident during my research for this post). A decade later, Isis appeared in a cartoon called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B000GETUC4?tag=bricinmypockb-20&amp;amp;amp;camp=213381&amp;amp;amp;creative=390973&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as4&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000GETUC4&amp;amp;amp;adid=0VSQM1A20N5AF0EVCP67&amp;amp;amp;&quot;&gt;Space Sentinels&lt;/a&gt;. She eventually made her way to DC Comics universe alongside her television co-hero Captain Marvel, now called Shazam. She later appeared in a somewhat modified version of herself in a season 10 episode of Smallville. Too bad JoAnna Cameron was not asked back for a cameo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are you waiting for? Grab that remote to your Netflix enabled device and get to adding The Secrets of Isis to your instant queue. After watching a few episodes, stop back by and let me know what you thought? Did it bring back memories, a smile or a laugh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s one more Isis incantation that saved the day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeper of the winds swirling o&amp;#39;er, smoke those robbers out the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh my&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Successful academic professional development sessions</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/10/25/Tips-for-a-successful-academic-professional-development-activity.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T18:53:56Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/10/25/Tips-for-a-successful-academic-professional-development-activity</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ijvM6gdoAEQ/UBLcgazaLFI/AAAAAAAA_TQ/LDWANWYI-Xk/s200/Professional+Development+Graphic.001.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;Within the past year, our statewide community college system has hired five of fourteen new regional academic officers (RAOs) and we have another on the way in September. Given this large number of new RAOs, it was decided by the Provost’s office that they would conduct a &lt;em&gt;new RAO training session&lt;/em&gt;. This session would occur at our Central Office location and be coordinated/planned by our Provost’s office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be the first to admit, that I usually groan when I hear that someone is planning my professional development; however as it turns out, this session was probably the best professional development activity I have attended in my twenty years with the college and surely beats the sessions I’ve attended in the military. My thoughts were echoed by my four peers in a recent e-mail conversation, so it must be true.“Why,” you may ask? What was the secret sauce? Let me share my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Timing is everything.&lt;/strong&gt; Our session was an overnight trip; however we began late the in the morning (to allow for the varying travel times due to the geographic locations of the campuses) and ended early afternoon the next day. Given all of our busy schedules and the topics selected, this amount of time was perfect. It was not rushed, and not so long that we began thinking, “I really need to get back to my campus as I have more important things to do.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attendee driven agenda.&lt;/strong&gt; About a month prior, all attendees were asked what topics we wanted to “discuss.” A combined list of the top items were placed on the agenda. This could have turned into a “here’s what we THINK you need” as is often the case in so many professional development activities. Thankfully, we had input on what topics actually mattered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Discuss” being the operative word.&lt;/strong&gt; As I mentioned above, we were asked what we wanted to discuss. There was no preaching, no force feeding of the cool-ade. This was an opportunity to put the key topics on the table and discuss. I don’t believe during the whole time, anyone spent more than 5 minutes in a soliloquy. A topic was quickly introduced and then it was discussion time. And there was plenty of it. Often it was lively and spirited, which leads me to my next point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vegas rules apply.&lt;/strong&gt; We had a little fun with this “what happens in Vegas stays in Vegas” statement. We were in a small room, doors closed and we agreed up front that there were no topics off the table. RAOs, especially new ones, need a safe place to &lt;strike&gt;vent&lt;/strike&gt; discuss the issues. This was our place to discuss those uncomfortable and often difficult topics. Many comments began with “Vegas rules apply, but…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effective moderator.&lt;/strong&gt; Our moderator, the Vice President for Academic Affairs for the college, was a previous RAO. On top of that, he was an excellent facilitator. He could have been an “instructor” who laboriously worked his way through the material with nary a chance for interaction. Instead he took a true&amp;nbsp;facilitator’s&amp;nbsp;role and kept us and our guest speakers on track while providing time for feedback and discussion. He is also very approachable and cares about the college and about helping us succeed. You felt the passion he had for academic affairs and for mentoring/coaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Much food consumed.&lt;/strong&gt; Lunch/Dinner/Breakfast/Lunch were provided along with copious amounts of coffee, soda and water. It’s those little things that keep you refreshed. Food breaks along the way allowed the discussions to veer “off topic” and often get to the real issues. Our dinner at a local establishment allowed our social bonds to strengthen. Of course, I had to tack on an extra mile or two to my run afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology allowed.&lt;/strong&gt; While we were sensitive not to overstep our bounds by reading our e-mail/tweets/texts/etc, technology was not outlawed. Everyone understood that our jobs often require a quick checkin and answer back to our home campuses. All of us had our technology (mine was a new Nexus 7 tablet, but that’s another blog post) on the table and there were often discussions where that technology came in handy to research trends, policy, curriculum and the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peer group created.&lt;/strong&gt; Sure I could call upon several of the other more experienced college academic officers for advice; however, now I have a core group of peers who probably have a better handle on my current challenges and as we mature in the position together, will better understand these challenges going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what did I learn from this RAO training? To put it succinctly, a lot and not all of it about being an RAO. The focus on this post was not so much what I learned to become successful as an RAO (I’m still a bit fuzzy about this one), but rather what I learned that made this professional development activity successful. I plan to reflect on this post further and implement as many of these strategies as I can to ensure productive professional development activities for our regional faculty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you attended a productive professional development activity lately? Tell me about it in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Education by the numbers</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/10/25/Education-by-the-numbers.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T18:52:58Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/10/25/Education-by-the-numbers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-cXVqrOxIT2c/UEawCtCkJcI/AAAAAAABBao/F0KH9iseYGU/s200/Numbers.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;Since beginning my new higher education administrative role, I’ve been inundated by numbers of every type. Almost every professional document I read, or meeting I attend, contains some percentage, amount, cost or goal. Some of them are redundant and insignificant while others I find interesting or valuable. Let me present the most interesting numbers that have presented themselves to me in the past couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1000&lt;/strong&gt;: The goal our Chancellor has identified as the total number of student who transfer from our institution to a four-year institution by 2015. Great goal and hope we can reach this one. We have several initiatives in the hopper and hope to blog about some of these soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17.83%&lt;/strong&gt;: The decrease in our region’s student FTE from this same time last year (after we drop non-pays/attends). This is significant and is the cause of many of our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/2012/07/hard-budget-times-are-not-necessarily.html&quot;&gt;financial challenges&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$380,000&lt;/strong&gt;: The cost to remodel the President’s Office at Purdue University.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; No wonder the community college is the most affordable higher education in the state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$1.7 billion&lt;/strong&gt;: Total 2012–13 Indiana state appropriations for higher education.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; An increase of &lt;strong&gt;.03%&lt;/strong&gt;. As our President put it today, the budget is flatlined from last year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6%&lt;/strong&gt;: Percentage of the &lt;strong&gt;$1.7&lt;/strong&gt; billion that will be distributed among those colleges and universities that meet certain performance goals. No, I have not seen these goals yet, but will be researching very soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;488,964&lt;/strong&gt;: Number of K–12 students in Indiana on free or reduced lunches.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; That’s almost &lt;strong&gt;50%&lt;/strong&gt; of the students.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are just few numbers that were discussed today during a recent regional academic officer’s meeting. There were others, as I found while perusing my notes, but these were the digits I found most interesting, striking, confusing or worrisome. I’ll keep my eyes open in the future for other numbers and when I do find more of interest, I’ll try and remember to consolidate them and add to a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indystar.com/article/20120904/NEWS/120904020/Gov-Mitch-Daniels-halts-renovation-of-Purdue-president-s-office?odyssey=tab%7Cmostpopular%7Ctext%7CFRONTPAGE&quot;&gt;IndyStar&lt;/a&gt; ↩&lt;br&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.in.gov/che/files/Table_1_Historical_Summary_of_Appropriations_for_Indiana_Higher_Education_(1984-85_to_2012-13&quot;&gt;IN.gov&lt;/a&gt;.pdf) ↩&lt;br&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stats.indiana.edu/profiles/profiles.asp?scope_choice=a&amp;amp;county_changer=18000&amp;amp;button1=Get+Profile&amp;amp;id=2&amp;amp;page_path=Area+Profiles&amp;amp;path_id=11&amp;amp;panel_number=1&quot;&gt;Stats Indiana&lt;/a&gt; ↩&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Got caught, did you?</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/10/25/Got-caught-did-you.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T18:47:40Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/10/25/Got-caught-did-you</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-H-sPawAMu2E/UGNVUhc3d1I/AAAAAAABCPE/zRx-H2V283s/s320/We+Take+Your+Class+-+Offline.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;Take a gander at the article below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.insidehighered.com/quicktakes/2012/09/26/we-take-your-class-goes-offline&quot;&gt;&amp;lsquo;We Take Your Class&amp;rsquo; Goes Offline&lt;/a&gt; | Inside Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you are not familiar with the site, they promise, or rather promised, to “take” your online course for you and deliver an A at the end of the semester. All this for the low, low price of – an undisclosed fee. Learn my thoughts on this “endeavor” in this post.
&amp;lt;!&amp;ndash;more&amp;ndash;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My particular favorite snippet is this quote from from the proprietor, known simply as Kevin. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“the site was not all that lucrative and with the added attention garnered last week, he decided to take it down…he does not think sites like We Take Your Class are a problem; the problem, he believes, is that education is structured in a way that makes it easy to cheat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher Education makes it easy to cheat? Just how is the structure designed to facilitate cheating? I sure would like to have a better understanding of this theory since faculty worldwide are vigilant when it comes to maintaining academic integrity and rigor. Maybe Kevin can parlay this into a thesis or dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My take on this whole situation is that &lt;em&gt;We Take Your Class&lt;/em&gt; simply got caught and that is why they shut down. Kevin was probably (and again, this is purely conjecture on my part so enjoy my fictional tale) a student trying to capitalize on what he thought would be a high demand service. He wanted to be the next Mark Zuckerberg and was willing to sell his Web 2.0 soul to get there. And is Kevin really the site owner? He could be a disgruntled client? We don’t really know, so lets not be too hard on him. No, let’s since he was willing to become the spokesman for this very questionable site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also can’t help but wonder if the site had clients. What student would actually use this service? Come to think of it, would any client really receive said service? If no services were rendered or even if they were unhappy with the service provided, where would they go? They would not be quick to litigate as that would result in an admission of their own guilt and lead to probable expulsion.  Can you tell that I am very dubious with regard to this whole endeavor?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Becoming lean during tough budget cycles</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/07/28/Becoming-lean-during-tough-budget-cycles.html"/>
   <updated>2012-07-28T00:20:02Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/07/28/Becoming-lean-during-tough-budget-cycles</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-z7dOYiDPVxo/UASGpbHYsPI/AAAAAAAA-uY/dzo9twLy7yI/s200/Calculator-Red.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;Recently, the only thing being discussed on our campus on a daily basis is our budget, or lack thereof. In our case we have to balance a budget where our deficit includes too many zeros. The reason for our budget reduction – lack of enrollment. I won’t even begin to formulate a guess on the reasons for this occurrence as there are entirely too many variables to nail it down to a single one.  I even joke with fellow administrators that I “picked the wrong time to move from the faculty to become a full-time administrator.” I’m half joking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I have found is that there truly is a negative and optimistic way to look at our situation (my wife will tell you that I am too optimistic). Let’s look at the negatives first and end with a few positives (I think my wife is correct).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All too often a review of the budget will panic the masses. Will this review result in the lose of equipment/personnel/programs? The rumor mill begins and spins out of control. In our case, the administration is as transparent as we can be (we still have too many unknowns); however, the faculty and staff learn about “budget” meetings and the rumors begin. And as we all know, most rumors and panic attacks come from the unknown; however, I’ve come to realize that no matter how transparent you are, the human nature of some personality types will always conjure up and disseminate the worst rumors possible. It’s a Catch 22 situation. There is no way to fix this. “It is, what it is,” as a recent colleague so eloquently stated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the “glass half full” division, I have found the budget exercises very beneficial since I am new to this campus and a new academic officer as well. The level of detail when discussing personnel/faculty/programs would have never occurred without this “crisis.” The talk amongst the administrative team is enlightening. Early in my new career I’ve had the opportunity to hear the historical reasons about how positions and programs were created, the good and the bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also observed how our leadership team works under a crisis. I was happy to find that they are a tight knit group. Even when they have disagreements, they are extremely professional and collegial. What strikes me as even more encouraging is that several of us on the team are new to the campus and have been welcomed with open arms. Some are even new to higher education. It is not that often that you find this type of administrative environment, let alone when working through such a difficult time. I’m proud of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we get into the specifics of the budget we have discovered some inefficiencies in some processes; especially within my area of academic affairs. While these findings won’t initially save us a few of those zeros, in the end, these inefficient holes will be plugged. This should reduce the workload of some of our faculty and staff. I often hear that we overwork our folks. I tend to agree with them and it is my hope that we will free up some of their precious time for other more important student focused tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we will probably come out of this budget year more lean, efficient, frugal, and with an enhanced fiduciary responsibility to our state tax payers. When we find these savings, we do something our college is proud of; we keep the cost and tuition of higher education lower than any other institution in the state. This alone makes this process worth the sweat and time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What I did...</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/07/10/What-I-did.html"/>
   <updated>2012-07-10T07:00:13Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/07/10/What-I-did</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;{**UPDATE:** This is a blog post from another site I wrote while serving as the Dean of the school of Applied Science and Engineering Technology. Those of you who know me now, will read the last full paragraph with a bit a bewilderment. Don’t worry, I did too.}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular higher education blogger, Dean Dad (real name unknown to protect the guilty), recently wrote a blog post entitled, &lt;a href=&quot;http://suburbdad.blogspot.com/2011/01/professor-in-suit.html&quot;&gt;A Professor in a Suit&lt;/a&gt; and I thought it apt that I share his thoughts with those couple of you who follow this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dean Dad does a good job of answering the question, “what do you do?” This is a question asked by many of my friends and family. They understand the faculty role (“you teach huh?”) but often don’t entirely understand a Dean’s dual role as faculty/administrator and the associated pitfalls of this balancing act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dean Dad is apparently (again, he is very vague) an Academic Dean for some unidentified community college in the mid-west. My role as a school Dean; where a school is a smaller academic branch of the college containing specific and associated disciplines, differs slightly. As a school Dean, I have less influence on college administrative policy as I focus my energies on smaller school related issues such as students, personnel management, development, instruction and curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy my role and I am not inclined, nor professionally ready, to move out of it anytime soon. In the meantime, I assert that I am in the best position I’ve ever held in higher education. Teaching was a blast and there are often times I envy Nikki in her role as an instructor, but as I grow older, and hopefully a bit wiser, I find that I want to stretch my legs a bit. Time will tell if I’ve made the correct decision. Thankfully, academia is gracious and they often welcome their administrators back to the faculty.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>And here’s how we are gonna save some cash</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/07/06/And-here%E2%80%99s-how-we-are-gonna-save-some-cash.html"/>
   <updated>2012-07-06T20:20:57Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/07/06/And-here’s-how-we-are-gonna-save-some-cash</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ivy Tech will save an estimated $800,000 by purchasing OEM printer supplies and entering long-term agreements according to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.insideindianabusiness.com/newsitem.asp?id=54526&amp;amp;utm_source=feedburner&amp;amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+IIB-Headlines+%28Headlines+-+Inside+INdiana+Business+with+Gerry+Dick%29&quot;&gt;Inside INdiana Business with Gerry Dick&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In addition to the office supplies and multi-purpose agreement with PDME, Ivy Tech has, after a highly competitive RFP process, established a multi-year agreement for premium compatible and OEM toner and ink cartridges with Indianapolis-based ICC Business Products, a family-owned small business that has been serving Indiana businesses since 1930.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The College expects to save more than 50 percent on the cost of printer toner and ink cartridges by shifting purchases from OEM (Original Equipment Manufacturer) toners to high quality premium compatible (remanufactured) printer toners with ICC. And through the robust RFP process, Ivy Tech was able to obtain excellent price levels for printer toners and ink cartridges.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one makes sense and it is good to see that the money we save will return to the state. Now if I can just convince them to outsource our email/calendaring to Google Apps for Education. I could then save them thousands!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mac mini Media Center (MmMC) software winner</title>
   <link href="/apple/2012/03/13/we-have-mac-mini-media-center-mmmc.html"/>
   <updated>2012-03-13T15:19:19-04:00</updated>
   <id>/apple/2012/03/13/we-have-mac-mini-media-center-mmmc</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been asked by a few, &amp;ldquo;What media center software do you use?&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;ve been quite coy with my answer because up and until now, I&amp;rsquo;ve not been able to determine a clear and definite winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-ClmRWvS4OVs/Tjrnz1e0j3I/AAAAAAAA3Io/VDuOltF_sgE/s200/Boxed+Mac+Mini.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well today I am happy to go on record and make a decision. Hit the link below to find out which media center software I use on my MmMC. Keep in mind that this is not a formal review of all media center software, but I do hit some highlights from each as I qualify why I feel my selection is the best. Read my selection by hitting the link below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let me start by listing the three media center software that were under consideration and briefly talk about why two of them were dropped out of contention:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Boxee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boxee &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.boxee.tv/2011/12/26/boxee-1-5-fall-software-update/#.Tyms3ZZSQbk&quot;&gt;recently announced&lt;/a&gt; that they were no longer going to support the PC platform past version 1.5. They will instead focus their development dollars on their &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/ef8S1&quot;&gt;Boxee Box&lt;/a&gt; and other set-top devices. While I spent several, and I mean several, hours configuring Boxee to work on the MmMC, I was never quite sure that this would be my software of choice. It was often buggy and on several occasions would cause the MmMC to hang and/or require a reboot. Since the PC platform is dead, I have have removed it from the MmMC and it is no longer in consideration. One down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;XBMC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up next for consideration is XBMC. XBMC is the original media center software for the Mac and has an extremely large and loyal Mac fan base. It has a beautiful interface that is very &amp;ldquo;tweakable&amp;rdquo; although cumbersome. The large user community means that you can easily find answers to your support questions. With the recent beta version release of &lt;a href=&quot;http://xbmc.org/natethomas/2012/01/22/xbmc-11-0-eden-beta-2-available-now/&quot;&gt;XBMC 11.0: Eden Beta 2&lt;/a&gt;, XBMC expands on its ease of use and configurability options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XBMC includes an add-ons capability to further expand the feature set or easily consume other web-based media such as YouTube, TWiT, Crackle, etc. Add-ons are also provided that will tag video, display captioning and download some incredible background images that add to the overall media center experience. XBMC is gorgeous! It is also very good and for some may be just what they are looking for. I really want to like XBMC, but until they add some features, I feel there is a better solution and that is Plex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Plex&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a huge Plex fan and it is my choice for Mac mini media center software. As a side note, there are also versions available for Windows and Linux if you are so inclined. Plex is based on the XBMC platform and is a fork of that open source code. That is important to note as all the core features you find in XBMC are also available in Plex (save for an new Airplay feature in XBMC that is sorely missing in Plex, but I have a hack for that below). However, the coders at Plex have really taken the concept of content access several steps further. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into the Plex features by asking a series of questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-SvwFe3pXg1c/Tzl7lFl_ceI/AAAAAAAA5Og/FFoRNNdDOtc/s400/Plex+Screen+Shot.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Can I watch video and listen to audio on my MmMC on the go?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s iOS and Android app for that. These apps automatically tunnel through the Internet to your home MmMC and actually stream, via transcoding, your content to those devices. So even if the video on your MmMC isn&amp;rsquo;t encoded properly, the Plex Media Server will take care of the dirty work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start streaming your content, &lt;a href=&quot;https://my.plexapp.com/&quot;&gt;create a Plex account&lt;/a&gt;. Take that account information and plug it into the preferences on your Plex Media Center MmMC install. Ensure that you have the Plex Media Server software installed and running. This is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/4bYSm&quot;&gt;separate download&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/RASeJ&quot;&gt;Plex Media Center application&lt;/a&gt;. Configure the Plex Media Server to start upon MmMC boot-up so that your content is always available. Fire up your mobile app. Plug in your username and password on those devices and voila. You now have anywhere access to MmMC content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-jYfBamSfa-0/Tzl7x574bjI/AAAAAAAA5Oo/bflv4xo4E7k/s320/Photo+Feb+03,+16+09+28.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video streamed to the Kindle Fire and iPad is gorgeous if you are on your local network. If you are on 3G or a remote network, the video adjusts to your bandwidth automatically and may become a bit jittery or pixelated. Very watchable though. Quality also depends on your providers upload speeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;What about watching content on another Mac or PC?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need access to your content on another computer and not a mobile device, you install the Plex Media Center software, plug in your Plex account credentials and you can then use the Plex Media Center software on that computer to view the content on your MmMC. Except for a bit of latency, it&amp;rsquo;s almost like being back home. Now how cool is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can I watch on any other devices? (Recent addition to the original post)
You betcha and one of my favorites is watching on our &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/P4OQS&quot;&gt;Roku&lt;/a&gt;. If you search the Roku channels list, you will find the Plex app. It&amp;rsquo;s free! Just install it, run and it will search out any Plex Media Servers on your local network. Something I failed to mention earlier, that is especially appropriate here, is the fact that no matter which device you view content from, Plex remembers where you left off. So you can start watching on your MmMC, watch a bit more on your mobile device, and then finish up that episode or move on your &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/P4OQS&quot;&gt;Roku&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_5&quot;&gt;What about add-ons?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to add-ons, Plex also tops its competitors in number and functionality. Plex provides many more stable channels (read channels that actually work) to access content from several online video and audio providers (TWiT, Hulu, YouTube, Pandora, etc). For instance, I was not able to find a Netflix add-on in the default XBMC add-on channel listing; however, a very quick inspection in the Plex add-ons quickly revealed a Netflix channel that works (unlike my Boxee experience). If I am in error in these comments, I&amp;rsquo;m sure the passionate XBMC users out there will let me know. Now if there were only a &lt;a href=&quot;http://draft.blogger.com/www.tcm.com&quot;&gt;TCM&lt;/a&gt; channel. We do love those great old movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_6&quot;&gt;Can I view web content? You know, YouTube?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plex shines when you want to consume video you find on the web on your large HDTV. If you took the extra step above to create an online account, you can now use the &amp;gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://my.plexapp.com/queue/help&quot;&gt; Plex It!&lt;/a&gt; bookmarklet to post web video directly to your Plex queue. It works like this. You browse a site and find a video you don&amp;rsquo;t have time to watch or would rather see on a larger screen on the comfort of your couch (a movie trailer for instance). You select the Plex It! bookmarklet from your Chrome, or other browser, bookmarks. The bookmarklet will search out the embedded video and automatically add it to your queue. You can then fire up Plex on your MmMC at home, navigate to your queue, and then select the video to view. The queue is also available online, so you can watch from your browser late as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plex also provides a unique e-mail address that you can use to send video from your mobile devices. Simply e-mail the link of the page that includes the video to the unique address and Plex will parse out this information, locate the video and add it to your queue. These two features work well with &lt;a href=&quot;http://draft.blogger.com/www.vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://draft.blogger.com/www.youtube.com&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; currently. Other sites are hit and miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_7&quot;&gt;Can I share my content with friends and family?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very interesting feature is included when you create an online Plex account. You can share content with other Plex accounts. Think about that for a moment. Friends and family can also stream your content to their devices once you add them to your friends list. Plex even takes this a step further and allows you to specify which content is available to your friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-BIYUElEdVio/Tzl8DHXHUoI/AAAAAAAA5Ow/eeDwKTAlFHM/s320/My+Plex+Login.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_8&quot;&gt;Yeah, but can it AirPlay?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have an iOS device, you can locate video on that device and then send it to your MmMC. As mentioned, this ability is not built into Plex by default, but you can follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://forums.plexapp.com/index.php/topic/25356-airplayer-for-plex-how-to-install/&quot;&gt;these slightly geeky instructions&lt;/a&gt; to enable this feature. This hack only works for video currently, as the AirPlay audio specification apparently uses FairPlay DRM. Even though this is a hack, I have found it to be pretty stable. My hope is that as the new XMBC core code is folded into Plex, we will find the feature integrated in later versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_9&quot;&gt;So how does it look on your HDTV?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, Plex in its previous version (v9.3.4 and earlier) didn&amp;rsquo;t have the gorgeous XBMC interface, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plexapp.com/download/mac-download-new.php&quot;&gt;the new beta version&lt;/a&gt; (v0.9.5.2) has fixed this with a wonderful new default theme. The basic user interface is now attractive and very usable. You will need to tweak the interface settings a bit for your specific application, but this is easily accomplished. If you don&amp;rsquo;t like the built-in theme, you can download alternatives from within the software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_10&quot;&gt;Great features, but how does video look?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have my MmMC configured to output 720p rather than 1080p. I&amp;rsquo;ve done this for a several reasons. First, the MmMC doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to work as hard pushing pixels. Second, most of my Plex content is ripped from my DVD collection (SD 480p). Third, I often remote control the MmMC through the built in Mac screen sharing feature. The lower resolution provides a much smoother refresh rate that makes the MmMC easier to control remotely. Lastly, I don&amp;rsquo;t see a major difference in quality when viewing my content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that Plex spits out some great looking video with my setup based on my content formats. I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to find something it can&amp;rsquo;t view, save for an .mkv download – and those are always suspect. When trying out XBMC, I had a couple of files that I could hear, but not see. Boxee was worse. So once again, in my case, Plex had the leg up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_11&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go on and on about Plex and have really just hit the tip of the features iceberg; however, you owe it to yourself to download both the Media Center and Server software and give it a shot on your MmMC. The first time you fire up video on your iPhone or Kindle from the train, work, or school, you&amp;rsquo;ll be hooked. Plex, for now, is what I consider to be the best media center software for my MmMC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a question about my set up? Drop a comment below. Need me to describe a feature in a later post? I take requests so you can drop those below as well. You can also add to these Tech Notes by sharing your experiences with Plex, XBMC or Boxee. Found an error or three. Let me know because as I mention, I am my own worst editor.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Five ways to reduce iPhone or hotspot data usage</title>
   <link href="/apple/2011/05/20/five-ways-to-reduce-iphone-data.html"/>
   <updated>2011-05-20T06:11:12-04:00</updated>
   <id>/apple/2011/05/20/five-ways-to-reduce-iphone-data</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-6VdxGgIIbXA/TdamjsD0jMI/AAAAAAAA1SA/SpvuoUkcdr0/s200/Personal+Hotspot.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;While on a business trip this past week, I was stuck in a building that did not have Internet access for my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0047DVVZO/ref=as_li_ss_til?tag=bricinmypockb-20&amp;amp;amp;camp=213381&amp;amp;amp;creative=390973&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as4&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0047DVVZO&amp;amp;amp;adid=0ZYHMX9S4H9MPSGB0ZEM&amp;amp;amp;&quot;&gt;MacBook Air&lt;/a&gt;. This was an extreme productivity killer. Then I remembered that the latest iOS for iPhone 4 now contains the ability to create a personal hotspot similar to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/redirect.html?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;location=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.com%2Fs%3Fie%3DUTF8%26x%3D0%26ref_%3Dnb_sb_ss_sc_0_4%26y%3D0%26field-keywords%3Dmifi%26url%3Dsearch-alias%253Daps%26sprefix%3Dmifi%23&amp;amp;amp;tag=bricinmypockb-20&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&quot;&gt;MiFi units&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding the service was extremely easy using the AT&amp;rsquo;T iOS app and the charge was only an extra $20 per month. I thought this a fairly reasonable charge and was surprised that it was prorated for the current month, incurred no activation charge and added an extra 2GBs of data to my current 2GBs/month plan. It also appears that I can turn this service off at any time without any additional deactivation charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4GBs might sound like a lot of data, but I began looking at my data usage and found I was burning through this pretty quickly. Then I noticed a few things about my usage. It became apparent that I was not practicing good data conservation. I noticed some patterns and decided this was a good time for a Tech Note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll share a &lt;strike&gt;five&lt;/strike&gt; six ways you can dramatically reduce your data consumption when using the personal hotspot feature of the iPhone 4. Some of these tips also work well when using your iPhone alone and I&amp;rsquo;m sure these tips will also work for those of you using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/redirect.html?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;location=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.com%2Fs%3Fie%3DUTF8%26x%3D0%26ref_%3Dnb_sb_ss_sc_0_4%26y%3D0%26field-keywords%3Dmifi%26url%3Dsearch-alias%253Daps%26sprefix%3Dmifi%23&amp;amp;amp;tag=bricinmypockb-20&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&quot;&gt;MiFi units&lt;/a&gt;. Read the tips after the link below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{Update: I&amp;rsquo;ve already received an excellent suggestion in the comments and have modified the original five to six. If more suggestions are added, I&amp;rsquo;ll include them in the list.}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Five Six Ways to Reduce iPhone Personal Hotspot Data Consumption&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Use iPhoto or Image Capture on a Mac to transfer photos from the iPhone. It may seem quick and easy to e-mail those photos from your iPhone to your Mac, but that uses a bunch of data and it does so both ways (during the sending and during the receiving). This can result in a 2-4MB of data to transfer a single full-size image. That will add up quickly! So keep a USB data cable ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-qwHYByIBNHM/TdamifxAq6I/AAAAAAAA1R4/Scv8krr-x-0/s200/Notifications.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Turn off iPhone push notifications. Some push notifications are sent from your iPhone, other area sent from servers. Any movement of bits from a server to iPhone results in bandwidth consumption. Chances are you also have software on your Mac, such as FaceTab (Facebook in your menubar) or GrowlVoice (Google Voice in your menubar) that also push notifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you are receiving Facebook notices on your iPhone through the Facebook app and with FaceTab and on your hotspot connected Mac, you are doubling your data consumption. Turn off iPhone push notifications by tapping Settings / Notifications / Off. Remember to turn this back on after turning the personal hotspot off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-YWaVlPW7qfo/Tdamging-JI/AAAAAAAA1Rw/Fd6Xl-BqKTs/s200/Fetch+New+Data.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Turn off iPhone mail push notifications and fetch manually. This is a HUGE data and battery saver. When push notifications are on, the iPhone and e-mail Exchange/IMAP servers are regularly pinging each other to see if there is any new data to share. If there is, the iPhone mail app will immediately begin to download the message. When acting as a simple device on the go, this is a great feature. When using the iPhone as a hotspot, this can become a data sieve; leaking data all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, If push mail is on and you have Outlook or Mail.app running on your Mac, both your iPhone and the Mac e-mail client are downloading the same message and attachments. Therefore, each message costs you double the data. Kill this redundancy on the iPhone by tapping Settings / Mail, Contacts, Calendars / Fetch New Data / Push / Off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though push services are off, you will notice as the bottom of that settings screen that there are also Fetch time increment settings. Select the Manually option. This will stop the iPhone from checking for messages unless you tap on the iPhone Mail app. Remember to turn this back on after turning the personal hotspot off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-10VSZ3BKvOk/Tdamix69fuI/AAAAAAAA1R8/1y1ZfdhcrPo/s200/Pause+Synching.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. Turn off Mac &lt;a href=&quot;http://db.tt/11cphuY&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; syncing. This is a common sense tip that could just slip your mind. If you use &lt;a href=&quot;http://db.tt/11cphuY&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; for Mac, you know that it is constantly syncing files to the cloud. That&amp;rsquo;s great on a bandwidth unlimited Wi-Fi connection, but death to a bandwidth limited personal hotspot connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine if you placed a video in a dropbox folder while on a Wi-Fi network and the file didn&amp;rsquo;t complete the syncing process. You later connect to the personal hotspot. That file will begin syncing again and the data lose will be like a slow leaky toilet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move your pointer to the Dropbox icon in your menubar, right-click and chose, the Pause Syncing option. Remember to turn this back on when you are again connected to Wi-Fi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. Listen to iTunes rather than streaming services. This is a common sense tip, but worth mentioning. If, like me, you don&amp;rsquo;t have an iTunes library on your MacBook Air, remember, your iPhone is right next to you. Most, if not all of your media is probably on that device. You can listen to songs using headphones or the tiny speaker in the iPhone, or you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docstechnotes.com/2011/05/dont-duplicate-your-macbook-air-and-ios.html&quot;&gt;follow my tip&lt;/a&gt; and play your iPhone music through your Mac speakers. Either way, avoiding services such as Pandora will save you a ton of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6. Turn off the Software Update automatic downloads. Reader Colin dropped this suggestion in the comments below and I thought it was important to include. See, your Mac may be downloading updates in the background without your knowledge. Mac computers are not as notorious as their Windows counterparts for frequency of software updates, but if you are on the personal hotspot and one or two updates hit, this can mean hundreds of Mbs in data consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To turn off the automatic downloads feature in Software Update, select Apple Menu () / System Preferences / Software Update. The Software Update system preferences screen will appear as shown in the image below. Ensure that the Download updates automatically option is NOT selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-f9_lwJRtgkw/TdfG1NBE9GI/AAAAAAAA1SU/7RzdvjwtvMw/s400/Automatic+Software+Updates.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it, &lt;strike&gt;five&lt;/strike&gt; six ways you can reduce iPhone personal hotspot data consumption. This is obviously not an all inclusive list, but rather a list to get you thinking about iPhone personal hotspot usage. Did I miss an obvious tip? Drop a comment below and add to this Tech Note as others have already done. If it&amp;rsquo;s a good tip, I&amp;rsquo;ll add it to this list and give you credit.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review – LEGO Technic Idea Book Series</title>
   <link href="/lego/2011/05/18/book-review-lego-technic-idea-book.html"/>
   <updated>2011-05-18T21:01:01-04:00</updated>
   <id>/lego/2011/05/18/book-review-lego-technic-idea-book</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-eTSxXIb8fVM/TdW70hRgFWI/AAAAAAAA1RU/g2y-XvwTBoU/s200/BimPBookReviewSimpleMachines.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;The kind folks over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nostarch.com/&quot;&gt;No Starch&lt;/a&gt;, and Travis specifically, were kind enough to send me review copies of the&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/s/?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;link_code=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&amp;amp;search-alias=aps&amp;amp;field-keywords=%20LEGO%20Technic%20Idea%20Book&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/s/?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;link_code=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&amp;amp;search-alias=aps&amp;amp;field-keywords=%20LEGO%20Technic%20Idea%20Book&quot;&gt;LEGO Technic Idea Book &lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;l=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;series by Yoshihito Isogawa. As past readers know, I am very fond of the No Starch line of LEGO books with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Unofficial-LEGO-Builders-Guide/dp/1593270542?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;link_code=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&quot;&gt;Alan Bedford&amp;rsquo;s Unofficial LEGO Builder&amp;rsquo;s Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;l=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=1593270542&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; my absolute favorite of all time. Given their past performance with LEGO books, I was excited to read and give this series a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been about a month since I received the books and I&amp;rsquo;ve finally had some time to sit down with this three volume series and develop a full BimP review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Series Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the specifics of the series. There are three books in the LEGO Technic Idea Book series and each is written by Isogawa. The books in the series include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple Machines – A primer into the world of simple LEGO building and systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wheeled Wonders – Add wheels and watch your systems roll!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fantastic Contraptions – More complicated systems that exploit advanced building techniques and elements.
All three books build in complexity from easy to advanced. Each book is approximately 150 pages. The books are printed on high quality paper with color images throughout. These color images are more important that you might initially think; as I will explain a bit later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The retail cost for each book is $19.95. You can find &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/s/?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;link_code=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&amp;amp;search-alias=aps&amp;amp;field-keywords=%20LEGO%20Technic%20Idea%20Book&quot;&gt;each book online at Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;l=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; for about $12.00. At full price, each book is a pretty good bargain. At $12.00, each book is an outstanding bargain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;First Glance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the reader will notice almost immediately, when browsing the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/LEGO-Technic-Idea-Book-Machines/dp/1593272774?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;link_code=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&quot;&gt;sample pages online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;l=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=1593272774&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; or while visiting their favorite brick and mortar book store, is that there is a dearth of text. The inside front cover fold contains more text than the pages that describe the models presented. This lack of text is also evident when reading the back cover as shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-SVOSciFnvDQ/TdW76JFNG2I/AAAAAAAA1RY/_48UIvDR88c/s320/BackofBook.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the image, where text on the back cover usually describes the contents of a book, this series instead uses images to present the concepts included within each book in the series. The concepts are identified by a series of icons which resemble the app icons found on modern smart phones. These icons are duplicated within the book. They are super-sized in the upper-left corner to make it easy for the reader to find each section by flipping the pages. You can see an example of this in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-ynHgGGz8T0E/TdW78lIl6iI/AAAAAAAA1Rc/28hAQBwibrU/s320/InsideIcons.png
&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The books do contain text. There are two-pages at the front of the book that includes an Introduction, Join the Discussion, Note to Parents and Information About the LEGO Technic Idea Series sections. Each section is identical in all three books in the series. When I first read this section, I thought the Note to Parents a bit odd. I assumed the demographic for these books was the Adult Fans of LEGO (AFOL). After I spent more time turning the pages I changed my assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course these books would be good for children. Better yet, they would be perfect for parents and children to work through together. Learning and/or sharing the basic concepts not only of LEGO construction, but also the concepts of mechanical, electrical and pneumatic design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot; http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-uqHNwTsiwj4/TdW79QTiJiI/AAAAAAAA1Rg/zpztZTJ3MVA/s200/SamplewithColors.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier I mentioned that the color pages were important. Isogawa uses color to assist with the process of identifying the various LEGO elements needed as well as how to assemble each model. Take a look at the image to the right for instance. As you can see, the multi-color elements make it easy to distinguish individual elements and how they connect. Using part of the same color would cause elements to blend and make it hard to distinguish between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using multi-color elements also allows the author to exclude a comprehensive parts list for each model. Omitting this listing provides more space for models and ideas. It&amp;rsquo;s, quite frankly, a brilliant way to present models. I am left wondering where Isogawa obtained many of these multi-color parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s the final BimP take on this series? The bottom line is that this series will make a wonderful addition to my library of LEGO related books. I&amp;rsquo;m also going to go out on a limb here and classify these as must have books for any self-respecting AFOL or LEGO enthusiasts of any age. Every reader is guaranteed to find new ideas and concepts that will supplement or improve their own creations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novel use of images and icons is very creative, modern and useful. This system makes it easy to locate concepts by quickly looking at the back of a book in the series, and then quickly flipping the pages until I find the icon. I then open the page and review one of the many options provided. Even without the use of this icon system, I find browsing through these books just pure fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No book is perfect so here are a couple of things I would like to recommend. First, I wish No Starch would package the entire series into a single hard bound volume. It would make a wonderful coffee table book for AFOLs. Second, while not as bad as other books, I like a spine that allows the book to stay flat when opened without breaking the binding. This should be required of all LEGO books. Both of these suggestions are cosmetic though. They nit-pick and wishful think an otherwise wonderful series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Final Recommendation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following quote by Isogawa is present near the front of each book and sums up the series in two sentences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This book is full of little seeds for ideas. It is you who will cultivate those seeds so they grow into wonderful masterpieces.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This series is not about the models, although many of them are fabulous, it is about the ideas they spark for your own creations. If you are looking for a book to build a specific model, look elsewhere. If you are looking for a book that spurs your imagination or provides basic LEGO mechanical, electrical and pneumatic concepts, look no further. You will find gem after gem of ideas and concepts that will drive your LEGO creations to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Unofficial-LEGO-Builders-Guide/dp/1593270542?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;link_code=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&quot;&gt;Alan Bedford&amp;rsquo;s book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=bricksinmypoc-20&amp;amp;l=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=1593270542&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; is still the reigning king of the LEGO books on my shelf, I now have the reigning queen. Like Alan&amp;rsquo;s book, this is a series of books I will refer to and browse regularly. They are beautiful books that I can spend hours just pouring through. I can emphatically state that no self-respecting LEGO fan should exclude this series from their library. Is it really that good Steven? Yes, it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what about it readers? Do you agree or disagree? Have a copy and want to discuss or not sure you want to purchase? Drop a comment below.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Fix Netflix error code 8156-6013 on a Mac</title>
   <link href="/apple/2011/04/11/Fix-netflix-error-code-8156-6013-on-mac.html"/>
   <updated>2011-04-11T15:19:19-04:00</updated>
   <id>/apple/2011/04/11/Fix-netflix-error-code-8156-6013-on-mac</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My new 11&amp;#39; MacBook Air was having problems streaming Netflix video this evening. Every time I tried to stream a video, I would receive a Netflix error code 8156-6013 followed by a &amp;ldquo;call technical support&amp;rdquo; message. It also stated that this was usually the result of migrating system settings from another Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-sZkFRYTgSSI/TaO_u7ExntI/AAAAAAAA0-U/hulYf-ocTps/s1600/Netflix+Error.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boy, they nailed that one. I had in fact used the Migration Assistant to setup my new MacBook Air by importing an account from my MacBook Pro. The error message then suggested that I contact their technical support team. Me? Wait on the phone? I think not. I&amp;rsquo;ll figure this one out myself. Read below how to fix this error without calling the Netflix Technical support team. Not that they are bad people mind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you a Windows user having the same issue? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://mike-thomson.com/blog/?p=210&quot;&gt;Mike Thomson&amp;rsquo;s post&lt;/a&gt; instead. Hit the link below for the Mac solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a three step process. The first step is to install the latest version of the Mac Silverlight plugin. The second is to delete the Silverlight DRM file. The third and final step is to reinstall a new DRM file. Let&amp;rsquo;s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Install the latest version of Silverlight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick caveat. These steps may not be necessary, but why take the chance. You should be running the latest version anyway for both performance and security reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a browser (Chrome, Safari, Firefox, etc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pound &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.microsoft.com/getsilverlight&quot;&gt;www.microsoft.com/getsilverlight&lt;/a&gt; in the address bar and hit the return key - the Silverlight download page will appear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the Mac download link as highlighted in the image below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-bcdIC9eFqUw/TaOs59NtpgI/AAAAAAAA0-A/p9I1TcNHMR0/s400/Silverlight+Mac+Version+Download.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the download is complete, double-click the Silverlight.dmg file to open the disk image - a window with the Silverlight.pkg file should appear as shown in the image below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-wylB-amLatw/TaOtQ1LI8-I/AAAAAAAA0-E/452X8v69DfI/s320/Silverlight+Disk+Image.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double-click the Silverlight.pkg and follow the normal file install procedures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eject the Silverlight disk image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trash the Silverlight disk image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;Remove the Silverlight DRM File&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably the step they really don&amp;rsquo;t want to publish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a Finder window (double-click on the Macintosh HD icon on the desktop).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigate to /Library/Application Support/Microsoft/PlayReady .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locate the &lt;em&gt;mspr.hds&lt;/em&gt; file as shown in the image below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ygYceK1TvM8/TaOuU2QZfPI/AAAAAAAA0-M/Xbua2vBVFZg/s320/mspr-hds+Silverlight+DRM+file.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drag the &lt;em&gt;mspr.hds&lt;/em&gt; file to the trash
{Update July 17th, 2011} Reader &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blogger.com/profile/01511647149280008563&quot;&gt;Vic&lt;/a&gt; said&amp;hellip;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To all the people saying you have no PlayReady folder&amp;ndash;I don&amp;rsquo;t see one either. It&amp;rsquo;s just invisible. Go to it from Terminal.
user@zed:~ $ cd /Library/Application\ Support/Microsoft/PlayReady/
user@zed:/Library/Application Support/Microsoft/PlayReady $ ls
mspr.hds
user@zed:/Library/Application Support/Microsoft/PlayReady $ rm mspr.hds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Reinstall a new Silverlight DRM file&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This step is easy and is probably pretty self-evident, but I&amp;rsquo;ll include just to round out the instructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a browser (this time it must be a Netflix supported browser).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visit the &lt;a href=&quot;www.netflix.com&quot;&gt;Netflix&lt;/a&gt; web site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log into your account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visit your instant queue and load a title - it should take a bit longer than normal to begin the stream since this step revalidates your computer and creates a new DRM file on your Mac.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin watching your favorite 80s films!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That wasn&amp;rsquo;t so bad was it? And why would that require a phone call to Netflix Technical Support? I am at a loss why this isn&amp;rsquo;t simply on the Netflix support site. Maybe I missed it, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think so. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple process and one that every Mac/Netflix user needs to know. Well, the secret is out of the bag. No more phone calls.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Create bootable USB drive on Mac OS X</title>
   <link href="/apple/2009/05/27/Create-bootable-usb-drive-osx.html"/>
   <updated>2009-05-27T21:01:01-04:00</updated>
   <id>/apple/2009/05/27/Create-bootable-usb-drive-osx</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I frequently experiment with live images of other OSs and install them on my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/redirect.html?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;location=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.com%2Fs%3Fie%3DUTF8%26x%3D0%26ref%255F%3Dnb%255Fss%255Fgw%255F0%255F5%26y%3D0%26field-keywords%3Dacer%2520aspire%2520one%26url%3Dsearch-alias%253Daps%26sprefix%3DAcer%2520&amp;amp;amp;tag=giveusoneminute-20&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&quot;&gt;Acer Aspire One netbook&lt;/a&gt; (I&amp;rsquo;ve since settled on PepperMintOS). Instead of burning CD images, I have found that bootable USB drives are faster and more reliable. I also have a problem keeping up with my external USB CD drive. The images I use most frequently come in either .raw or .img formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these formats, here&amp;rsquo;s how I create a bootable USB drive using OS X and a couple of terminal commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WARNING!&lt;/strong&gt; Performing these steps will completely erase the contents of your USB drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REMEMBER:&lt;/strong&gt; You need a USB drive large enough to hold the image contents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Download an image to your Desktop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locate a disk image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re experimenting, Google these distros: Moblin, Fedora 10, Ubuntu, CentOS, and Mandriva. Remember, you are looking for live bootable images usually in the .img format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;Partition the USB drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; Not all USB drives are created equally. Some will function as bootable drives and some will not. You may have to experiment with different brands before you find one that works. My inexpesnive and trusty &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B007JR532C/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B007JR532C&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=bricinmypockb-20&amp;amp;linkId=G5YHW6IYGG4VIUHT&quot;&gt;SanDisk Cruzer 8Gb USB Drive&lt;/a&gt; works almost everytime, but I make no guarantees for your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fire up the &lt;em&gt;Disk Utility&lt;/em&gt; application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the options in order and as shown in the image below (click for larger view).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3563/3559673545_af90d2255c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the Apply button (READ WARNING AGAIN!!!) - the disk will be partitioned as free space and with no file format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Determine the USB drive device name&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert the USB drive into one of the USB slots.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fire up the &lt;em&gt;Terminal&lt;/em&gt; (I prefer the free &lt;a href=&quot;http://iterm.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;iTerm&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Terminal&lt;/em&gt; type: &lt;code&gt;diskutil list&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A list of all devices will be displayed as shown in the image below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locate the USB drive inserted and jot this info to paper or brain - in this example, highlighted below, the USB drive inserted is _/dev/disk2 _and was identified by the USB drive name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3365/3560244296_87b657e343.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Unmount the USB drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Terminal&lt;/em&gt;, type: &lt;code&gt;sudo umount /dev/disk2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the system password and press ↩.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DO NOT PHYSICALLY REMOVE THE DRIVE! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;Burn the image to the USB drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Terminal&lt;/em&gt;, type &lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt; and use the following format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo dd if=location/name.img of=/dev/disk2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example the command was formatted as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo dd if=/Users/stevencombs/Desktop/karmic-netbook-remix-i386.img of=/dev/disk2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toc_5&quot;&gt;Raw Support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example above an &lt;em&gt;.img&lt;/em&gt; image was used. If your image is in the &lt;em&gt;.raw&lt;/em&gt; format, use the following format for the dd command:In the example above an &lt;em&gt;.img&lt;/em&gt; image was used. If your image is in the &lt;em&gt;.raw&lt;/em&gt; format, use the following format for the dd command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo dd if=location/name.raw of=/dev/rdisk2 bs=1m&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OS X will begin burning the image to the USB drive (as indicated by the flashing USB drive light) and this operation can take several minutes depending on the &lt;em&gt;.img&lt;/em&gt; size and the write speed of the USB drive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once complete, the light will stop flashing the the terminal prompt will reappear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the USB drive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The USB drive is now ready to boot that laptop or desktop using the USB boot option. This same process can be used for most linux distributions. What I have not determined is how to easily do this with an &lt;em&gt;.iso&lt;/em&gt; file on a Mac. So if you have a tip for me regarding this process, drop me a comment and add to these notes.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Turn off IR reader on a Mac</title>
   <link href="/apple/2009/04/06/turn-off-ir-reader-on-mac.html"/>
   <updated>2009-04-06T23:45:23-04:00</updated>
   <id>/apple/2009/04/06/turn-off-ir-reader-on-mac</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a quick, yet very handy tip when that pesky Apple Remote activates Front Row (for old school Macs) or other apps on your Mac while controlling your Apple TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose Apple Menu / System Preferences&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose Personal / Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the Disable remote control infrared receiver checkbox as shown below&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3544/3497884375_ef9b58ddcf.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Disable Remote Control Infrared Receiver&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close System Preferences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it! Short and simple fix.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Markdown Test Post</title>
   <link href="/web/1999/01/01/markdown-test-post.html"/>
   <updated>1999-01-01T14:19:19-05:00</updated>
   <id>/web/1999/01/01/markdown-test-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;toc_0&quot;&gt;Git Atom Markdown Post Test&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I make numerous changes to the CSS on this blog to refine the conversion of my markdown posts to HTML. I use this post to view the effects made to the final rendering of the markdown files. This post includes the important HTML tags that are affected when Jekyll renders static pages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I update this page frequently with additional test content. You will notice that I include notes where I need code modifications/corrections as this is still a work in progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the bottom of this post for the raw markdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_1&quot;&gt;Text Highlights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;italicized&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This text is &lt;del&gt;strikethrough&lt;/del&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_2&quot;&gt;Superscripts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ft&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; - 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; - 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Need to create &lt;code&gt;#post.sub&lt;/code&gt; in CSS file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_3&quot;&gt;Image&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-07-01-editorial-posts-bookmark.png&quot; alt=&quot;This is a test image&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Need to create caption CSS (currently does not render)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_4&quot;&gt;Bullet List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com&quot;&gt;StevenCombs.com&lt;/a&gt; for my blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bullet 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bullet 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_5&quot;&gt;Numbered List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List item one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List item two&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_6&quot;&gt;Table&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Tables&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Are&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;Cool&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;col 3 is&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;right-aligned&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;$1600&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;col 2 is&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;centered&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;$12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;zebra stripes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;are neat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_7&quot;&gt;Inline Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use this command to update: &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get upgrade&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_8&quot;&gt;Code Block&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Ruby Getting Started with Programming&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Control flow examples&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Dr. Steven B. Combs, coding novice&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Do&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;times&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Hello. &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_9&quot;&gt;Block Quote&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetuer adipiscing elit. Donec gravida mauris id eros congue tincidunt. Nunc eget nulla non mi vehicula vehicula. Aenean sed erat. Suspendisse laoreet quam in massa. Sed risus. Nulla vulputate tincidunt lorem. Nulla ac purus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Etiam vulputate viverra neque. Sed semper, arcu eu lobortis congue, velit mauris scelerisque erat, congue porta odio dui ut nisl. Nunc imperdiet, ipsum et aliquam tempus, nibh neque semper metus, vitae cursus odio turpis sit amet nibh. Praesent eros est, laoreet eget, viverra in, laoreet in, magna. Praesent odio odio, iaculis dictum, pulvinar a, aliquam nec, libero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;toc_10&quot;&gt;Raw Markdown&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the raw markdown code for this page. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/stevencombs/stevencombs.github.io/blob/master/_posts/1999-01-01-markdown-test-post.md&quot;&gt;Fork this raw code on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;text language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;---
layout: post
title: Markdown Test Post
date: 1999-01-01 19:19:19
comments: false
category: web
---

# Git Atom Markdown Post Test

I use this file to test my CSS changes.

## Image

![This is a test image](http://www.stevencombs.com/images/posts/2014-07-01-editorial-posts-bookmark.png)

## Bullet List

Check out [StevenCombs.com](http://www.stevencombs.com) for my blog posts.

* Bullet 1
* Bullet 2

## Numbered List

1. List item one
2. List item two

## Strikethrough
~~This text has strikethrough~~

## Superscripts
ft&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt; - 1^(st) - 2^(nd)

## Table

| Tables        | Are           | Cool  |
| ------------- |:------------- | -----:|
| col 3 is      | right-aligned | $1600 |
| col 2 is      | centered      |   $12 |
| zebra stripes | are neat      |    $1 |


## Inline Code

Use this command to update: `sudo apt-get upgrade`

## Code Block

ruby
# Ruby Getting Started with Programming
# Control flow examples
# Dr. Steven B. Combs, coding novice
puts &amp;quot;Do&amp;quot;
10.times do
    print &amp;quot;Hello. &amp;quot;
end
puts &amp;quot;&amp;quot;

## Block Quote

&amp;gt; Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetuer adipiscing elit. Donec gravida mauris id eros congue tincidunt. Nunc eget nulla non mi vehicula vehicula. Aenean sed erat. Suspendisse laoreet quam in massa. Sed risus. Nulla vulputate tincidunt lorem. Nulla ac purus.
&amp;gt; 
&amp;gt; Etiam vulputate viverra neque. Sed semper, arcu eu lobortis congue, velit mauris scelerisque erat, congue porta odio dui ut nisl. Nunc imperdiet, ipsum et aliquam tempus, nibh neque semper metus, vitae cursus odio turpis sit amet nibh. Praesent eros est, laoreet eget, viverra in, laoreet in, magna. Praesent odio odio, iaculis dictum, pulvinar a, aliquam nec, libero.

## Raw Markdown

Here’s my raw markdown code should you want to duplicate on your page as well. 

[Fork this raw code on GitHub](https://github.com/stevencombs/stevencombs.github.io/blob/master/_posts/1999-01-01-markdown-test-post.md).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>