<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title></title>
 <link href="/" rel="self"/>
 <link href=""/>
 <updated>2014-05-17T23:37:22-04:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>What is the number one job skill requested by employers?</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/12/06/Number-one-job-skill-requested-by-employers.html"/>
   <updated>2013-12-06T04:24:30Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/12/06/Number-one-job-skill-requested-by-employers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-oo72t0hV8oA/UqFOAadtXfI/AAAAAAABNVY/1oQuEMPCHac/%25255BUNSET%25255D.jpg&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;On December 12th and 13th 2013, I attended the Workforce Development Consortium Strategy Forum at the Lone Star College Conference Center in Houston Texas. The forum brings together several community college and industry leaders from ten states that are part of the Community College Workforce Consortium (CCWC). The goal is to discuss workforce needs and how community colleges can train, educate and develop the future workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first meeting and it has been enlightening. Read this post and take a look at what was determined to be the number one skill requirement of new employees as determined by the CCWC participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today, the employers present (Boeing being one) were given a list of about twelve skills that were culled from a national survey of employers. The CCWC employers present, about 20 or so, where asked by the college representatives to identify from the larger list the top three skills required of new employees. The top three were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problem solving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leadership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The selection of these three was not an epiphany. I’ve seen these bubble up to the top in other surveys. The employers want community colleges to teach these skills. “Got it!” I thought to myself. We are working on these and have been for quite some time. The discussion continued. There was another skill industry needed community college to teach to their students and this skill, not listed on the original twelve, was even more important than the top three. That skill?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;show-up-to-work-and-show-up-on-time&quot;&gt;Show up to work and show up on time!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ouch!” I thought to myself. This is a “skill” that is hard to teach and one that students need to be successful in college as well. They really should have this skill before they come to us. Right? Where do they learn this? How do we modify this behavior? Those are great questions that I cannot answer. I’m a Technologist by trade, not a Psychologist. Have an idea? Let me know in the comments below and let’s discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Thank a Veteran Today!</title>
   <link href="/holiday/military/2013/11/11/Thank-a-Veteran-Today.html"/>
   <updated>2013-11-11T11:39:25Z</updated>
   <id>/holiday/military/2013/11/11/Thank-a-Veteran-Today</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;iframe align=&quot;right&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;540px&quot; src=&quot;https://www.thunderclap.it/projects/6258-veterans-day-2013/embed&quot; width=&quot;250px&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;Once again the time has come for us to honor those that have sacrificed themselves so that we may enjoy the freedoms of this great land. While we officially recognize the contributions of our veteran’s twice a year, we should be grateful daily for their continued service and sacrifices.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I am especially grateful for those that served and still serve “down-range.” Every day they are in harms way, is a day we are able to sleep comfortably knowing that we are being protected by the best military in the world. A military staffed by volunteers willing to offer themselves in service to their country. Are you willing to make this sacrifice? If not, you should be especially grateful. Because if not for them, then who?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Whatever your political bent,&amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #990000;&quot;&gt;get out there and thank a veteran!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; It is because of their sacrifices that you get to enjoy and voice your political views without fear or retribution. Not willing to thank them? Put your viewpoints on the shelf as you don’t deserve the liberty they provide.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, I add a special thanks to those who served by my side during my two military careers (Air Force and Army). Many friendships were made and I am happy that many of them still endure even after my 27-years of service. Happy Veteran’s Day Y‘all!</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Make mistakes, learn from them, and own them</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/08/27/Make-mistakes-learn-from-them-own-them.html"/>
   <updated>2013-08-27T18:51:22Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/08/27/Make-mistakes-learn-from-them-own-them</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-K-STTmTy85A/UeQtr9EnbnI/AAAAAAABKZk/mm-cxRSUl7s/s200/Mistakes+You+Cannot+Correct.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;Yesterday I began a series of lessons learned from my first year as a Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs (VCAA). Today I share lesson number two – mistakes.I’ll admit that our college does not have a robust training program for new VCAAs. My training program was a two day orientation with four other “newer” regional VCAAs. The sessions was beneficial, but as our moderator explained, that training would not prepare us for our new roles. We would make mistakes. He was correct, but that session did prove valuable. It gave me a cohort to share ideas.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one thing I had that my new peers did not was my previous experience within the college – over twenty years. I’ve served at two other regional campuses and on numerous statewide committees. I was around when the college made the transition from vocational college to a comprehensive community college. I was one of the first to implement online education within a region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These experiences provide me with a large pool of colleagues, who also have many years of experience, to tap into. Many of them have even held the position of VCAA. It is easy for me to contact any one of them and ask for their advice, coaching and/or mentoring. Surely this large base of knowledge will keep me from making mistakes…right? The answer is of course “no” as you will discover after hitting the link below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the resources available to me, I made a mistake early on that affected my professional relationship with a couple of individuals. I won’t go into specifics here, but suffice it to say that we are not always given the opportunity to sit back and observe before we make changes. Leadership articles often suggest this is good practice – in theory; however, sometimes external forces, such as budget and institutional priorities, don’t allow it. I spent 27 years in the military, I was trained to make quick decisions and live with the results of those decisions. But the military also teaches its leaders to learn and manage from their mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone new to any position will make mistakes. What you cannot do is dwell on the mistakes. You made the decision, you made the mistake, and you may be able to correct it. Correction may involve a simple reversal of a decision or action. Another option may be to make another decision that lessens the effects of the first. If neither of these are an option, then you must live with the mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what action you take to lessen a mistake, you must learn from it. You learn by self-reflection (I journal and blog). While you review your mistake, try and understand the:&lt;/p&gt;

* process used to formulate the decision.&lt;br /&gt;
* current implications of your decision.&lt;br /&gt;
* future implications of your decision.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These can be some tough nuts to crack; however, taking the time to sit back and analyze your mistake will stop you from quickly making the same mistake again and may even better prepare you to not make a different and/or similar mistake down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #999999; font-size: large;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-align: start;&quot;&gt;“Here’s the real lesson…ADMIT your mistake!&lt;/span&gt;”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to grow in your professional maturity? ADMIT your mistake! No, “ifs,” “ands” or “buts” about it. Integrity is key to your long term viability as a leader and decision maker. Integrity will ensure that your mistake does not back you into a professional corner. If you try and cover a mistake, you will do even more harm to the situation and potentially your career. You will also lose the trust of your supervisor, peers and subordinates. They will not trust a decision maker who cannot own up to their own mistakes or who refuses to learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you notice my mention of subordinates? You need to admit your mistakes not only to your superiors, but also your subordinates. You must do this in a way where you take complete responsibility. Do not throw someone else under the bus. I’ve seen this tactic used too many times. It begins with, “Yes, I made the mistake, but…” and that’s a “but” usually followed by blame of someone else. It doesn’t matter who was involved. As a leader, you have responsibility for your own mistake. Simply own the mistake and move on. You will be amazed at the level of respect you gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone have anything to add to this lesson? I’m not asking for specific instances, although those would probably prove interesting, but why not share your tips and tricks and share how you deal with mistakes. You can do this in the comments section below.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Like classic films? Check out TCM this September!</title>
   <link href="/entertainment/2013/08/11/Like-classic-films-Check-out-TCM-this-September.html"/>
   <updated>2013-08-11T16:50:56Z</updated>
   <id>/entertainment/2013/08/11/Like-classic-films-Check-out-TCM-this-September</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-SoR1QZl9xok/Uge2_ZI2szI/AAAAAAABLIQ/IDmvd1bftzo/s1600/TCM+Now+Playing+-+September+2013.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;We received our monthly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tcm.com/&quot;&gt;Turner Classic Movies (TCM)&lt;/a&gt; Now Playing magazine for September. I think Nikki and I need to take a month’s worth of vacation from work so we can enjoy what is an amazing collection of classic cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out these monthly highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kim Novak – collection of films from the great actress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Future Shock – 16 great Sci Fi Friday films&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sunday’s with Hitch – 43(!) Hitchcock films spread over every Sunday in September&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of those great monthly highlights are three of my favorite ways to explore unknown cinema; TCM Underground, TCM Imports and Silent Sunday Nights.&amp;lt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not a subscriber or viewer (TCM is part of our basic package), you should be. Watching TCM is the equivalent of participation in a college film class that never ends. Your Professors are the great Robert Osborne and the very entertaining and knowledgeable Ben Mankiewicz. They even have a guest lecturer drop by on occasion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want the full-on educational experience, check out their textbook, &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/b4e4nv&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now Playing&lt;/em&gt; magazine&lt;/a&gt;. Full of articles from the hosts and guests like Martin Scorsese, the magazine got a bit of a refresh in September. Want to visit their campus as a guest student? Attend a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tcmcruise.com&quot;&gt;Turner Classic Movie Cruise&lt;/a&gt; (on our bucket list)! Now that’s a campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably the only channel that keeps me from cutting ties with my local cable provider. If I could only subscribe to one channel on cable, this would be it. My only request would be the ability to watch live or time shifted on my iPad mini or iPhone. I would pay for this service as I do my Netflix subscription. Allow me to stream this content on my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docstechnotes.com/2013/08/chromecast-unboxing-setup-and-usage.html&quot;&gt;Chromecast&lt;/a&gt; and “good-bye cable!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE - May 3, 2014:&lt;/strong&gt; TCM now offers an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docstechnotes.com/2013/12/2013-appvent-calendar-day-15-coderunner.html&quot;&gt;iPad app&lt;/a&gt; that allows live streaming and video on demand movies. It does require cable company authentication, but is sure is great to have access to TCM on the go!} &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give TCM a try this month and I’m sure you will be hooked. There’s nothing like a good classic film when there are 300 other channels of reality television. Gotta run now. Need to clear off some recordings from the TiVo to make room for what is sure to be an amazing month of entertainment. If you are a TCM watcher, sound off in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New series - My first year as a regional academic officer</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/07/14/New-series-My-first-year-as-a-regional-academic-officer.html"/>
   <updated>2013-07-14T18:51:27Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/07/14/New-series-My-first-year-as-a-regional-academic-officer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-X1gYurcLgJc/UeLnhOCKIMI/AAAAAAABKX0/5ZP9sLTNbQQ/s200/Dean+-vs-+RAO.png&quot; /&gt; This month marks my first year as the chief academic officer, Vice Chancellor of Academic Affairs (VCAA), for the Columbus/Franklin region of Ivy Tech Community College. During this first year, I have learned much about my new role, the college and the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To celebrate my first year, I’ve decided to share some lessons learned. These lessons may (I write “may” because every situation is unique) be useful for new and even seasoned chief academic officers. Blogging/writing is a great way for me to reflect on this past year and my hope is that not only will these lessons be of value to others when shared, but it will also force me to spend additional time reflecting on the past year’s hits and misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand no one will read the entirety of my lessons at a single setting (heck, I don’t think there will be many people who will read a single lesson), so I will spread them out over a series of posts. I will do my best to get each lesson out there as soon as I can. I’ll also leave the comments section open for each post so readers (again, if any) can ask questions or even drop in your own experiences. It’s a short lesson that is hinted at in the image above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The dean’s role is “same, ’cept different” from that of the VCAA:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The role of a school dean and that of a regional academic officer are very similar. Many tasks required of a dean directly transfer to the role of Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;faculty management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;budget management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enrollment management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strategic planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;community outreach&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organization and productivity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;instructional/information technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember thinking, while reviewing the position description for the vacant VCAA in Columbus, “I can do that. It’s just an extension of my current role.” I was correct to a point. Sure I continue to manage these same tasks; however, the complexity of each is multiplied exponentially as the chief academic officer. So while both positions are similar in scope, they differ on scale. It’s the scale that can cause you to be out of touch with what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out of touch:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a dean, I felt as if I knew what was going on in the classroom. I understood faculty issues. I knew students and faculty by name. Now I often find myself asking, “what’s happening in our classrooms?” or “who is that faculty member?” There’s a level of disconnect from the faculty and students that I was not prepared for nor have I been able to easily correct. I was a faculty member for twenty years and even though I still hold my rank as Professor, I have not had the opportunity to teach during this past year. Being out of the classroom is a void that needs to be filled at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not knowing the name of a faculty member became an issue early on. During my first year I was accused of not saying “hello” to a faculty member at a public event. Quite honestly, I had only been in the position for two months and probably had not met the faculty member, or if I had, only once; however, that was not the expectation. Lesson learned! I can do something about that. So I grabbed a visual directory from our marketing folks and began studying it. Faculty who avoided me found an appointment in my office for a one-on-one. Those one-on-one meetings are extremely valuable. I did this as a dean and am flummoxed that I am only now realizing that I need to do this as a VCAA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sphere of Influence:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I’ve learned that many of those ideas I thought I would implement “if only I were the VCAA” were not feasible. Ivy Tech Community College is a state-wide system of campuses. While we have some regional autonomy, there are many statewide policy decisions that as an officer of the college I am required to enforce. The line between my regional role and my requirement to maintain our statewide curriculum and policy is thin - razor thin at times. The nice part about my current position is that if I disagree with a policy (which I often do), my voice is now heard. This is the first time in my higher education career that I have had that feeling. That doesn’t mean I can’t make regional changes though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meetings:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One simple, but well received, change was to decrease the number of meetings for faculty. I want our faculty to have more time for their students and their craft. I have been to many a faculty meeting that was not productive nor a good use of my time. I didn’t want this for our faculty so I decided I would not prepare an annual faculty meeting schedule. We have no regularly scheduled faculty meetings, save for our very first meeting at the beginning of the semester. Meetings fall on our calendars only when we need them and only with the faculty who need to be there. When meetings do occur, they are well attended, productive, honest and open. One of my favorite compliments received this year was from a faculty member who said, “I like your meetings…I like your no B.S. style” – in other words they were telling me to not be a politician, but to be honest and make meetings useful. I can honestly say that I am much better at this as a VCAA than I was as a dean, but I still have a bit of work to do as we will see in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summing up:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That does it for my first post where I discuss the cursory differences between being a dean and a regional academic officer. As is true with most of my writing, this isn’t a deep look into the nuances, but just a couple of quick thoughts. Be on the look out in the near future for the second lesson in the series and in the meantime, as I mentioned earlier, feel free to drop your comments below. I look forward to reading them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A productivity primer for higher education administrators</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/03/03/A-productivity-primer-for-higher-education-administrators.html"/>
   <updated>2013-03-03T23:49:23Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/03/03/A-productivity-primer-for-higher-education-administrators</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-cEkUuUsA4g4/UTJSV25O7nI/AAAAAAABG2U/-uETIC_O5yM/s1600/Empty+Inbox.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;137&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-cEkUuUsA4g4/UTJSV25O7nI/AAAAAAABG2U/-uETIC_O5yM/s200/Empty+Inbox.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;We conduct cabinet meetings on our campus each Monday. Our Chancellor develops the agenda and leads these discussions between our regional academic administrators. Typically these meetings are a simple sharing of information between our team leaders. On occasion we invite college and community leaders to meet with the team to understand important initiatives.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A unique twist is that once a month, the Chancellor asks a cabinet member to provide a professional development activity. The cabinet member does not have to personally conduct the activity. They can farm it out to someone on their team or bring in someone from the community. This month, the task falls to me. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;While I have a large number of faculty on our Academic Affairs team that I can ask to lead a session, given that I am new to the cabinet, I felt it appropriate that I take my turn at bat. Folks who know me can probably predict the topic of my presentation (or have read the title of this post). I have this odd obsession. I constantly refine my productivity workflow. I’ve gone through a countless number of tools and processes to find a system that works for me in my given environment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;During my presentation I share some tools to get my fellow administrators thinking about their own productivity workflow. There is not a one-size fits all solution. Everyone has their own specific needs. My presentation provides some simple and advanced tools for consideration. It’s an eclectic mix. You can check out my slides and links to all the tools I mention after the break below.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a name=&#39;more&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The title of my presentation is &lt;em&gt;Productivity Tools Primer&lt;/em&gt;. The focus of the presentation is two-fold. This presentation is around 30 minutes and was presented to the cabinet on March 4th, 2013.&lt;br /&gt;As a primer, I quickly provide a bunch of tools I find useful day-in and day-out. I have many other tools I would love to share, but with only 30 minutes, I focus on the obvious and then discuss a couple of concepts that most likely none of the cabinet will use. My intention is not to encourage them to use these tools, but rather to consider other advanced options.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Obviously, a review of the slides and the links below are not enough for readers of this blog post to glean all concepts. For that you need to hear the entire presentation (if you are interested in this or an expanded presentation &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:steven.combs@gmail.com&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;); however, you may find a nugget or two in there.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;389&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1al8NGIUJwU_KPH0Zu72V5ie38ahYqqvWHC3YGGGNVcw/embed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; width=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 1 - Title&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/&quot;&gt;StevenCombs.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 2 - Get a System&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/YYczm&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done by David Allen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.davidco.com/about-gtd&quot;&gt;GTD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 3 - Inbox Zero&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://inboxzero.com/&quot;&gt;Inbox Zero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 4 - Evernote Web&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/&quot;&gt;Evernote Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 5 - Evernote Computer&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/evernote/id406056744?mt=12&quot;&gt;Evernote Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/download/get.php?file=Win&quot;&gt;Evernote Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://apps.microsoft.com/webpdp/app/evernote/5aba7f8c-318f-42aa-9590-b1fc31e5cba6&quot;&gt;Windows Touch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 6 - Evernote Mobile&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://appstore.com/evernote/evernote/&quot;&gt;Evernote iOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://market.android.com/details?id=com.evernote&quot;&gt;Evernote Android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://appworld.blackberry.com/webstore/content/1700&quot;&gt;Evernote Blackberry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.windowsphone.com/en-US/apps/db21927d-f292-e011-986b-78e7d1fa76f8&quot;&gt;Evernote Windows Phone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 7 - Evernote Extension&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/download/get.php?file=SafariExtension&quot;&gt;Safari&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/extensions/detail/pioclpoplcdbaefihamjohnefbikjilc##&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/firefox/addon/evernote-web-clipper/&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/webclipper/##&quot;&gt;Bookmarklet for other browsers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 10 - Evernote Trunk&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://trunk.evernote.com/&quot;&gt;Evernote Trunk on the Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 11 - Evernote Notebook&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/Ork4J&quot;&gt;Evernote Notebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 12 - Freemium/Premium?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/premium/&quot;&gt;Evernote Premium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 13 - Pocket on the Web&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/&quot;&gt;Pocket on the Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/safari/&quot;&gt;Pocket for Safari&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/chrome/&quot;&gt;Pocket for Chrome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/firefox/&quot;&gt;Pocket for Firefox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/q3PYR&quot;&gt;Pocket for other browsers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Slide 14 - Pocket Apps&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/desktop/&quot;&gt;Pocket Desktop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/iphone/&quot;&gt;Pocket iOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/android/&quot;&gt;Pocket Android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/windowsphone/&quot;&gt;Pocket Window Phone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/apps/blackberry/&quot;&gt;Pocket Blackberry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;slide15-rssfeeds&quot;&gt;Slide 15 - RSS Feeds&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://reader.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://newsify.co/&quot;&gt;Newsify for iOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;slide16-findafeed&quot;&gt;Slide 16 - Find a Feed&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/reader/view/##directory-page/1&quot;&gt;Google RSS Search&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theverge.com/&quot;&gt;The Verge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;slide17-googledrive&quot;&gt;Slide 17 - Google Drive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://drive.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;slide18-wazesocialnav&quot;&gt;Slide 18 - Waze (Social Nav)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.waze.com/&quot;&gt;Waze with links to Apps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;slide19-plaintext&quot;&gt;Slide 19 - Plain Text&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.barebones.com/products/bbedit/&quot;&gt;BBEdit for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://brettterpstra.com/projects/nvalt/&quot;&gt;nvALT for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://notepad-plus-plus.org/&quot;&gt;Notepad++ for Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.secondgearsoftware.com/elements/&quot;&gt;Elements for iOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.kooklab.epistle&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Epistle for Android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;slide20-markdown&quot;&gt;Slide 20 - Markdown&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fletcherpenney.net/multimarkdown/&quot;&gt;MultiMarkdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://multimarkdown.com/&quot;&gt;MultiMarkdown Composer for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.barebones.com/products/bbedit/&quot;&gt;BBEdit for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://markedapp.com/&quot;&gt;Marked for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;slide20-markdown&quot;&gt;Slide 21 - Addendum&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;ved=0CEoQjBAwAQ&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fsmilesoftware.com%2Ftextexpander%2Fdownload.html&amp;amp;ei=teAzUe64F-qPyAHl4IDAAQ&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNGYvDj3XTzs5oyc97YflsgYv2B7sA&amp;amp;sig2=JYmyMxN_PqY1ZCwz-EtzNA&amp;amp;bvm=bv.43148975,d.aWc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TextExpander for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://textexpanderwindows.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Text Expander Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.google.com/p/autokey/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Autokey for Linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alfredapp.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alfred for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.launchy.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Launchy for Windows, Mac &amp;amp; Linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;See something useful in the slides and/or the list above? Want to add your own productivity tips to assist my fellow higher education administrators? Drop a comment below. I’m always looking for new ideas.</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Indiana legislation all faculty should understand</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/01/15/Indiana-legislation-all-faculty-should-understand.html"/>
   <updated>2013-01-15T19:55:02Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/01/15/Indiana-legislation-all-faculty-should-understand</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-uJv26_0PsEc/UIl-2GvgphI/AAAAAAABDK0/nFSTYPaxMJ8/s1600/StateLegislation.jpg&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-uJv26_0PsEc/UIl-2GvgphI/AAAAAAABDK0/nFSTYPaxMJ8/s200/StateLegislation.jpg&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Today our Regional Board of Trustees meet. My name is on the agenda to discuss the changes that will occur within the state with regard to transfer of general education credits among the public institutions. As I read the two pieces of legislation, House Enrolled Act No. 1220 (Credit Creep) and Senate Enrolled Act No. 182 (Common Course Numbering within the Core Transfer Library), the thought struck me that all Indiana higher education faculty (and parents for that matter)&amp;nbsp;should be aware of these initiatives and understand their implications.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The legislation is not difficult to read; however, I need to provide the Executive Summary for the board, so I thought I may as well share my outline for anyone interested. The bullets are more concise and may be a bit more “bottom line up front.” You can check out my summary in this post:&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a name=&#39;more&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Transfer Changes Board Report Two important pieces of legislation:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;House Enrolled Act No. 1220 (Credit Creep)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Senate Enrolled Act No. 182 (Common Course Numbering within the Core Transfer Library)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEA 1220:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Each public institution we review all programs and reduce associate degrees to 60 credit hours and baccalaureate degree to 120 credit hours&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If institutions cannot meet these requirements, they must document and justify the reason (accreditation, certification, etc) in a proposal to the commission&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;No deadline specified in the legislation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SEA 182:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create and maintain a common course numbering system for the core transfer library (CTL) of general education competencies&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Each public institution will map their unique CTL course numbers to a new common course numbering system&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Not later than December 1st, 2012, the state institutions, in conjunction with the Higher Learning Commission, will provide a report on statewide transfer of the general education core&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The core will be competency based and at least 30 credit hours&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Institutions will work together to create the Transfer General Education Core (TGEC) via the State Transfer and Articulation Committee (STAC)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Further, the institutions will establish a way to document completion of the competencies on student transcripts - in our case it will be the Technical Certification (TC) in General Studies&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;After May 15th, 2013 a student who completes the TGEC will not be required by another state institution to complete additional courses&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Students who do not complete the TGEC prior to transfer, will complete the remainder of the requirements at the new institution&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Students who receive an associate of art or associate of science degree meet the minimum required 30 hours&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.in.gov/legislative/bills/2012/HE/HE1220.1.html&quot;&gt;House Enrolled Act No. 1220&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.in.gov/legislative/bills/2012/SE/SE0182.1.html&quot;&gt;Senate Enrolled Act No. 182&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.transferin.net/&quot;&gt;TransferIN.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Community college quality versus cost</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2013/01/14/Community-college-quality-versus-cost.html"/>
   <updated>2013-01-14T21:38:03Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2013/01/14/Community-college-quality-versus-cost</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-58b-dlaZFUI/UPRsGGTDRHI/AAAAAAABFq0/11iWjBLyWR8/s1600/Screen+Shot+2013-01-14+at+3.34.48+PM.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-58b-dlaZFUI/UPRsGGTDRHI/AAAAAAABFq0/11iWjBLyWR8/s200/Screen+Shot+2013-01-14+at+3.34.48+PM.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;Community colleges have several stigmas. One in particular is a sticky-wicket. That being cost. We strive to maintain a low cost for our students. We pride ourselves on being the most affordable college in the state. Then THAT question pops up, “How can a program that costs so little have quality?”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I’ve heard this referred to as the Wal-Mart syndrome. Sure you can go and buy the same product and save a few bucks, but is the entire experience worth the time spent? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our community, we face this question regularly and it is compounded by the fact that we have a university partner next door – literally! We share a campus, parking lot, library and even adjunct faculty; however, if you were to survey our community, most would probably state that the quality (and rigor) of the product next door was greater and of better value.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As the regional academic officer for our campus, I am always taken aback be these claims. I know them to be inaccurate. From my days teaching at a four-year institution, I know my rigor and quality did not change as soon as I hit the community college door. More perplexing is that these comments often come from folks who have no experience with our product, culture or student body. They have a university experience and that is “just better.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In an effort to get the word out, our Chancellor prepared an op ed piece to better communicate our product and message. You can find it after the click below. I like what he has to say and I bet that when people read the piece they will be surprised by the quality of our programs and students.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After your review, feel free to drop a comment and add your thoughts to the debate.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;&lt;b&gt;Ivy Tech Quality Is Second To None&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;By Dr. John Hogan&lt;br /&gt;Chancellor, Ivy Tech Community College&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ivy Tech Community College is celebrating its 50th anniversary this year.  We’re certainly proud of our heritage – but equally proud of how far we’ve come as an institution.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ivy Tech has grown to become the largest singly accredited community college in the nation.  We are the largest post-secondary institution in the state.  More freshmen are enrolled at Ivy Tech (18,564) than at Indiana University Bloomington (4,695), Purdue University West Lafayette (3,434), Ball State University (3,159), Indiana State University (3,175), and IUPUI (3,106) combined.  Forty-one percent of the state’s freshman class is enrolled at Ivy Tech Community College.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In addition to providing the front door to higher education, through which students can earn an associate degree for less than half the cost of the first two years at most universities and then continue to work toward a bachelor’s degree at the university of their choice, Ivy Tech also provides educational instruction of the highest quality. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I am proud of our faculty.  Many hold doctorates in their respective fields.  All other full-time faculty teaching our freshman- and sophomore-level classes are required to hold no less than a master’s degree in the field in which they teach.  Our adjunct professors possess full academic credentials and also work in their fields. This provides students an opportunity to learn from professionals currently in the workforce. &lt;br /&gt;The evidence of high quality is incontrovertible.  For example, Ivy Tech’s RN students complete a two-year associate of science degree, then sit for the NCLEX licensure exam. Four-year nursing program graduates take the same exam. Columbus nursing graduates passed this exam at a rate of 96% in the first quarter and 98% in the second. These are among the very highest marks in the state, including those from four-year universities! Columbus surgical technology graduates passed their licensure exam at a rate of 100% for the second straight year.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In order to provide students with an education with credits that transfer, institutions must be accredited.  Ivy Tech is accredited by the North Central Association, which oversees accreditation of colleges and universities in 19 states.  The process of attaining and maintaining accreditation is rigorous.  As a result of the high quality of instruction at Ivy Tech and the fact that its programs are accredited, the state’s research universities all accept Ivy Tech credits and continue to partner with us to create even more pathways for Ivy Tech graduates who want to pursue bachelor’s degrees and further their education. &amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;The School of Art and Design holds program accreditation from one of the most stringent and prestigious bodies in academe, the National Association for Schools of Art and Design.  Our program is one of only seven other community colleges in the nation to receive this accreditation. Our paramedic science program was the very first in south central Indiana and among Ivy Tech’s 14 regions to receive recognition from its accrediting body, the Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Education Programs. &amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;We are equally proud of our students and graduates.  Research has shown that Ivy Tech graduates who transfer as juniors to universities are more successful than those who started at the university as freshmen.  Our graduates have gone on to become knowledgeable and dedicated leaders in their fields.  Last year, over 800 area residents transferred university credit from Ivy Tech in Columbus, a number that nearly doubles every year. &amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;Our sister institutions have come to realize that the rigor at Ivy Tech is no less than that which students would experience at their university.  Our students handle the same responsibilities as do their students—they write research papers, attend lectures, run experiments, give speeches, and do homework.  They also create friendships, have fun, learn from one another, participate in clubs, play intramural sports, and develop a love for Ivy Tech. &amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;It should be no secret that Ivy Tech is the most affordable college in Indiana.  But offering a more affordable education doesn’t equate to offering a lower quality education.  Our mission is to offer a high quality education at an affordable price for individuals in our service area.  We have striven to do just that and believe that we have succeeded.  We look forward to continuing to do so. &amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Apple TV - Out of the Living Room and into the Classroom</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/presentations/2013/01/14/Apple-TV-Out-of-the-living-room-and-into-the-classroom.html"/>
   <updated>2013-01-14T19:51:19Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/presentations/2013/01/14/Apple-TV-Out-of-the-living-room-and-into-the-classroom</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Monday, October 22nd, I was the presenter for a local brown-bag at the Columbus Learning Center for the three institutions of higher education on our shared campus: Ivy Tech Community College, IUPUC and Purdue College of Technology. The topic of my presentation is the use of the TV in the Classroom. See, even Vice Chancellors can stay current in the use of instructional technologies!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post provides the slides used for that presentation as well as the presentation outline. If you have something to add or a comment about the content, please drop in a comment after the post. Check out the entire presentation content after the break below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Docs Presentation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;389&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/embed?id=1Ywc5m3WcT-Ldl0YASB2FqBRnZ91X2auxKxNWiD0DAmY&amp;amp;start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; width=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presentation Notes: TV - &lt;em&gt;Out of the Living Room and into the Classroom&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agenda (slide 2):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This 45 minute presentation will discuss the Apple TV and its use in the classroom. Major topics include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why Apple TV (TV)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hardware&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remote Control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Out of the Box Capabilities and Demonstration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AirPlay Demonstration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Networking Requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Questions and Discussion ♫ _Background music before presentation provided by TV Radio, Classical, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.radionomy.com/en/radio/a1900-classical&quot;&gt;A1900 Classical&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why an TV (slide 3):&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ubiquitous nature iOS devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Student friendly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ease of use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WirelessCost (Entire secure setup for around $250)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hardware (slide 4–5):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Below is a list of the hardware you may need based on your classroom:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/YWrer&quot;&gt;Apple TV, $99&lt;/a&gt; - the subject of our presentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/ztiSV&quot;&gt;ATV Pro, $45&lt;/a&gt; - converts from HDMI to RGB and audio for older projectors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/IYnEq&quot;&gt;HDMI Cable, 2 for $10&lt;/a&gt; - newer projectors will only require the HDMI cable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remote Control (slide 6):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can control the Apple TV with the following devices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apple Remote (included with TV)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/BGuAf&quot;&gt;Remote app, Free&lt;/a&gt; for iPhone/iPod Touch/iPad (iOS devices)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out of the Box Capabilities (slide 7) and Demonstration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Without a connection to any other device, the TV provides the following features to enhance instruction (brainstorming time!):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moves/TV Shows/Music from the Apple Store&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Access to iTunes content on other computers (iTunes required on local network)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Netflix &amp;amp; Hulu Plus (subscription required)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MLB.TV, NBA &amp;amp; NHL (subscription required)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TrailersYouTubeVimeoPodcasts - Personal favorite for education is access to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ted.com/talks&quot;&gt;TED Talks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Radio&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo Stream and Flickr&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wall Street Journal Live&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More to come from Apple…all apps can be removed from the homescreen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AirPlay Demonstration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
AirPlay is the process of transmitting audio, video and apps to the TV. The following are discussed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iOS Devices (iPhone and iPad) - AirPlay Music (Music app) and Video (YouTube app) demonstrations from iPhone 4S, Mirroring (iPhone 4S or greater or new iPad required) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/skitch/id490505997?mt=8&quot;&gt;Skitch&lt;/a&gt; demonstration from iPhone 4S&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://draft.blogger.com/goo.gl/L6L23&quot;&gt;PlayTo for Android&lt;/a&gt; - No device mirroring (to achieve mirroring, the device must be “rooted” and the appropriate app downloaded from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://play.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OS X Integration - Basic connection functionality built into OS X Mountain Lion only&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://airparrot.com/&quot;&gt;AirParrot for OS X&lt;/a&gt; - Adds AirPlay to all Macs and adds additional functionality such as full desktop (scaled), extended desktop and by applicationA quick word about security - Passcode can be set and device connected cannot be bumped by another device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network Requirements:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The TV has the following network requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All devices must be on the same network&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wi-Fi and Wired connections supported&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;802.11n preferred for wireless&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Network traffic affects performance and a dedicated classroom network using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/pOsCC&quot;&gt;$99 AirPort Express&lt;/a&gt; would be preferable. This layout will also decrease interference with other classrooms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions and Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Enhance Course Materials with iTunes U</title>
   <link href="/presentations/higher-education/2013/01/10/Enhance-Course-Materials-with-iTunes-U.html"/>
   <updated>2013-01-10T01:09:10Z</updated>
   <id>/presentations/higher-education/2013/01/10/Enhance-Course-Materials-with-iTunes-U</id>
   <content type="html">Hot on the heels of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/2012/10/tv-out-of-living-room-and-into-classroom.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Apple TV: “Out of the Living Room and into the Classroom”&lt;/i&gt; presentation&lt;/a&gt;, I have prepared another entitled, &lt;em&gt;Enhance Course Materials with iTunes U&lt;/em&gt;. This presentation was held on January 10th, 2013 from 12:00 - 1:00PM in Poling Hall, Room 201 on the Ivy Tech Columbus campus. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DmCzV7LBG-k/UO35pceB4_I/AAAAAAABFog/GBBJDrZtvpA/s1600/iTunes+U.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;240&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DmCzV7LBG-k/UO35pceB4_I/AAAAAAABFog/GBBJDrZtvpA/s400/iTunes+U.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In this post, you will find my presentation outline that includes all the links (and a few more) shared during my 45 minute talk. As always, feel free to add comments or ask questions using the comments section at the bottom of this post.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a name=&#39;more&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;opening&quot;&gt;Opening&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Welcome&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;About me&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;About the presentation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Who are the Mac, iPad or iPhone users in the room?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Who are the PC users in the room?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;itunes&quot;&gt;iTunes&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Gateway to iTunes U&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/itunes&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt; available for Mac and PC&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;iTunes features include:  &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Music - search, purchase and download music&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Movies - search, purchase and download movies&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;TV Shows - search, purchase and download TV Shows&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;App Store - search, purchase and download iOS apps&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Books - search, purchase books to read in iBooks&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Podcasts - search and subscribe to podcasts&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;iTunes U - search and subscribe to educational content (the main topic of today’s conversation)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Link to iTunes content to share online or within a course management system system such as Blackboard&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Locate and create a link demonstration - the secret sauce&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;itunesu&quot;&gt;iTunes U&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Gateway to amazing, and free, instructional resources&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Accessible through iTunes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Content from a wide variety of K–12 and higher education providers&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Review all content entirely before adding to your own course materials&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/itunesu/&quot;&gt;Follow iTunes U on twitter&lt;/a&gt; to learn about new content additions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Learn more on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/education/itunes-u/&quot;&gt;Apple iTunes U page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;sampleitunesuresources&quot;&gt;Sample iTunes U Resources&lt;/h3&gt;Let’s take a look at some unique iTunes U content available for your course:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/highlights/id420424352?mt=10&quot;&gt;Duke University Libraries Ad Views&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/origins-american-animation/id386017694?mt=10&quot;&gt;Library of Congress – Origins of American Animation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/hidden-treasures-at-library/id391498646?mt=10&quot;&gt;Library of Congress – Hidden Treasures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/itunes-u/early-films-edison-companies/id386017464?mt=10&quot;&gt;Library of Congress – Early Films from the Edison Companies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;itunesucoursemanager&quot;&gt;iTunes U Course Manager&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Free. browser based, online content management system to consolidate iTunes U and traditional course resources&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunesu.itunes.apple.com/coursemanager/&quot;&gt;iTunes U Course Manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Supplement your traditional course materials&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Easy to maintain and manage&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Does not include collaboration or assessment tools&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;iTunes U Course Manager demonstration&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-50PS6YdCD0Q/UO4RHIQ0O6I/AAAAAAABFpA/JiN-D_td6Bw/s1600/iTunes+U+Course+Manager.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-50PS6YdCD0Q/UO4RHIQ0O6I/AAAAAAABFpA/JiN-D_td6Bw/s400/iTunes+U+Course+Manager.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;ibooksauthor&quot;&gt;iBooks Author&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Optional companion product to iTunes U Course Manager&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Free in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ibooks-author/id490152466?mt=12&quot;&gt;Mac App Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Simple to use electronic book authoring&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Interactive components to enhance content&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Self publish!!!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;iBooks OS X demonstration&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-euUasrKRgCY/UO4QUu-p20I/AAAAAAABFow/fnqhOHtrpq4/s1600/iBooks+Author.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;265&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-euUasrKRgCY/UO4QUu-p20I/AAAAAAABFow/fnqhOHtrpq4/s400/iBooks+Author.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;itunesuiosapp&quot;&gt;iTunes U iOS App&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;It all comes together for the student in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/itunes-u/id490217893?mt=8&quot;&gt;iTunes U iOS app&lt;/a&gt; for iPhone and iPad&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provides access to course content including:  &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Course information  &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Course overview&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Instructor information&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Course outline&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;About the course&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Posts - formatted weekly&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Notes - consolidated and can be shared from the app  &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;All notes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Course notes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Audio/Video notes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Book notes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Materials - consolidated  &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Videos&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Books&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Apps&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Images&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;iTunes U iOS app demonstration&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/--LYkiCxfaHA/UO4SqS0vIOI/AAAAAAABFpU/FKwecMw4xW0/s1600/iTunes+U+iOS.JPG&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/--LYkiCxfaHA/UO4SqS0vIOI/AAAAAAABFpU/FKwecMw4xW0/s400/iTunes+U+iOS.JPG&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;ibooksiosapp&quot;&gt;iBooks iOS App&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Access to the entire collection of books in the iTunes store&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Students use&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ibooks/id364709193?mt=8&quot;&gt;iBooks&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;to view the course textbook on an iPhone or iPad&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;iBooks demonstration&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-QWx8snREerQ/UO4SqZwFZxI/AAAAAAABFpY/LzTLr0Nk-SM/s1600/iBooks+iOS.JPG&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-QWx8snREerQ/UO4SqZwFZxI/AAAAAAABFpY/LzTLr0Nk-SM/s400/iBooks+iOS.JPG&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Its free, so give it a try&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Include a few resources from iTunes U within your current course materials&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Slowly add resources to a closed course within the iTunes U Course Manager&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Finalize and publish your course for students to access&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Self publish your own textbook&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Drop a comment below and share your experiences&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;questionsanddiscussion&quot;&gt;Questions and Discussion&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;additionalresources&quot;&gt;Additional Resources&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/education/resources/&quot;&gt;Apple educational resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/education/itunes-u/&quot;&gt;Apple iTunes U page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://edseminars.apple.com/itunesu_webcast_series/&quot;&gt;iTunes University WebCast series:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunesu.itunes.apple.com/enroll/E36-Q43-5WC!&quot;&gt;My Agricultural Data Management demonstration course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bookmark/Share this page: &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/Lzivh&quot;&gt;http://goo.gl/Lzivh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Thanksgiving, community colleges, and changing lives</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/holiday/2012/11/21/Thanksgiving-community-colleges-and-changing-lives.html"/>
   <updated>2012-11-21T23:17:49Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/holiday/2012/11/21/Thanksgiving-community-colleges-and-changing-lives</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first Thanksgiving in my new role as Vice Chancellor for
Academic Affairs. While reflecting on this yesterday, I decided to send
out the following e-mail to all of the faculty within our region:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Faculty,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Before you head off for the Thanksgiving holiday, I wanted to let you
know how much I appreciate everything you do for our students. For
some this is a very difficult time of year and this can hold
especially true for our students as they struggle their multiple
commitments. What often happens though, is that we sometimes forget to
recognize those co-workers around us who struggle as well. If you know
of someone within your academic area who needs support, I do hope you
will reach out to them this holiday season.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So what am I thankful for? Being a part of this campus and having the
opportunity to serve each of you as we strive to change the lives of
our students. Thank you for letting me (sic) a part of your team.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Steven&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally I struggle when sending out mass email to faculty. I consider
whether the message is relevant, beneficial, and/or productive. Once I
write a message, I often go over it numerous times as I know that the
English faculty are out there picking it apart for grammatical and
spelling errors. I come from an industrial background and do not have
what I would call, exceptional writing skills, as is evident by my
exclusion of word in the last line. On this occasion though, I didn’t
want my message to seem contrived, but rather heart felt. I decided to
stream of conscious this one and just let it flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feedback from the faculty has been positive, but my absolute favorite of
the bunch was from a faculty member who mentioned that they decided to
go to a food bank to make a donation after they read my message. When
they spent time talking with folks, they found out that several of our
students were recipients of these donations. That’s what community
college service is all about folks. Changing lives and making a
difference. To all of my fellow community college faculty, staff and
administrators:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Happy
Thanksgiving!&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The College of 2020 is a must read for administrators</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/10/25/The-College-of-2020-is-a-must-read-for-higher-education-administrators.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T19:06:28Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/10/25/The-College-of-2020-is-a-must-read-for-higher-education-administrators</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;76&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-b5Hdx01Axn4/TgJt8-Ac0MI/AAAAAAAA3CQ/dl9SQ6f62bI/s200/Screen+shot+2011-06-22+at+6.33.55+PM.PNG&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;{UPATE: This content originally appeared on a previous blog I maintained.} Before the summer of 2011 academic retreat, we were asked to do a bit of homework. Each member is to read “The College of 2020: Students” by Martin Van Der Werf and Grant Sabatier. Before I continue, you can review the document yourself using this &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/8PZBS&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This document is a Chronicle Research Services publication. There is no need to read the entire document, the Executive Summary provides the salient points. You can then dive into those areas that interest you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I read this report, I understood the need for higher education administrators and faculty to read this document, but it also struck me that this documents is a required read for parents and possibly even advanced early teens who are just now considering their higher education options. It provides some excellent insights about the future of higher education curriculum/programs, instructional technologies and finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, higher educations is changing and this document prepares us for some certain truths, of which the most interesting to me are presented below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;College tuition will rise - was there ever any question?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Online education enrollment will continue to rise - again, pretty obvious?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Students will look for data organizers/collectors/miners as their instructors, not orators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Community Colleges will thrive because of their cost and open access&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Students will require anytime enrollment instead of the traditional academic calendar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For-profit colleges will continue to become more popular as their costs become more aligned with their public competitors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give the document a closer read for the reasons why as well as the specifics. This document is due an update. With a publication date of June 2009, there is not doubt that since that time we have seen significant changes to the landscape of higher education. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m of course always interested in your thoughts, so drop me a comment below if you’ve taken the time to read this document and have some insights.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>“O zephyr winds which blow on high...</title>
   <link href="/entertainment/2012/10/25/O-zephyr-winds-which-blow-on-high.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T19:00:40Z</updated>
   <id>/entertainment/2012/10/25/O-zephyr-winds-which-blow-on-high</id>
   <content type="html">{UPDATE: This is a repost from another blog. As those who know me can attest, I’m a bit of a sci-fi geek and love to reminisce about days of old. So enjoy this somewhat quirky post on this Saturday morning} &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_CLU_mny_beA/TKCcn5YiohI/AAAAAAAAl54/ObfUckpETq0/s1600/isis-flying.jpg&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;151&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_CLU_mny_beA/TKCcn5YiohI/AAAAAAAAl54/ObfUckpETq0/s200/isis-flying.jpg&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;...lift me now so I can fly.” Do you remember which 70s super-powered hero uttered this phrase to take flight? No? Then see if this one refreshes your memory, “Oh mighty Isis!” That’s right, a couple of years before Lynda Carter’s Wonder Woman hit the airwaves, there was another female superhero protecting teens and southern California from evil and personal injury.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

Her name was &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Secrets_of_Isis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Isis&lt;/a&gt; and after the link below, I take some time to reminisce about those early Saturday mornings shows. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a name=&#39;more&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In 2007, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000QQDEZG?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=giveusoneminute-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000QQDEZG&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Secrets of Isis: The Complete Series&lt;/a&gt; was released on DVD. Somehow I missed that release then; although, I am not sure I would have shelled out cash for the collection. About a year ago, I became aware that the series was available on DVD and placed them into my Netflix queue. As a matter of fact, I put them at the bottom of my queue thinking I would relive some childhood memories at some point down the road. It wasn’t a priority above other items in my queue. Then something happened. A couple of days ago I was reviewing my queue and noticed that the series was now available as an instant streaming option. I couldn’t wait. I turned on the Sony Bravia (Netflix streaming built in – way cool) and loaded up the first episode. “Oh my.” &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_CLU_mny_beA/TKCi32pp62I/AAAAAAAAl6U/zMv8hjxrkaA/s1600/isis2.jpg&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;156&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_CLU_mny_beA/TKCi32pp62I/AAAAAAAAl6U/zMv8hjxrkaA/s200/isis2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;That, “Oh my,” is both a good and bad thing. The good is that the series is just as I remember it as a child. JoAnna Cameron, in a dual role as Isis and Andrea Thomas (Chemistry Teacher for a Southern California high school), does a great job channeling the mythical superhero. The bad is that she has to deal with 70s special effects technology, simple scripts, and horrible acting by her co-stars. But the horrible acting does have a plus side – lots of humor for today’s viewers. Take for example a situation where a teen walks past a sign that says, “Danger, hidden mine shaft.” Bet you can’t guess what happens next! And when it does, the facial reaction of the actress falling down the shaft is priceless. Check out the episode entitled, Year of the Dragon for this laugh. Before you ask, there’s no Kung-Fu in this episode. That would be far too violent for Saturday morning television in the 70s. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Although Isis is a mixed bag, there is some real nostalgia here and I found myself enjoying my trip back to the 70s. There are episodes including crossovers from Captain Marvel (you know, the boy who turns into a superhero by uttering the word, Shazam!) and the show really does get better with each episode, if only slightly. The last two episodes of season 2 and the series, Now You See It... and ...Now You Don’t,  really are the pinnacle of the show and demonstrate what this show could have become with a couple of more seasons and a bigger budget. It was not to be. For some unknown reason, Isis only received two seasons and three guest shots on its sister show Shazam! Even though the popularly of the show and the character was growing. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_CLU_mny_beA/TKCr2CCmWAI/AAAAAAAAl7A/8Zgr2Z1z1Zk/s1600/51EMJBYGD8L._SL500_AA300_.jpg&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_CLU_mny_beA/TKCr2CCmWAI/AAAAAAAAl7A/8Zgr2Z1z1Zk/s200/51EMJBYGD8L._SL500_AA300_.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Isis does have a legacy though. Fans all over the web reminisce about the show, the actress and its weekly moral story (as was evident during my research for this post). Isis appeared in a cartoon a bit later in the next decade called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B000GETUC4?tag=bricinmypockb-20&amp;amp;camp=213381&amp;amp;creative=390973&amp;amp;linkCode=as4&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000GETUC4&amp;amp;adid=0VSQM1A20N5AF0EVCP67&amp;amp;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Space Sentinels&lt;/a&gt;. She even eventually made her way to DC Comics universe alongside her television co-hero Captain Marvel. She later appeared in a somewhat modified version of herself in a season 10 episode of Smallville. Too bad JoAnna Cameron was not asked back for a cameo. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So what are you waiting for? Grab that remote to your Netflix device or your computer and get to adding The Secrets of Isis to your instant queue. After watching a few episodes, stop back by and let me know what you thought? Did it bring back memories, a smile or a laugh?  &lt;br /&gt;And here’s one more Isis incantation that saved the day: Keeper of the winds swirling o&#39;er, smoke those robbers out the door. Oh my...</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Tips for a successful academic professional development activity</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/10/25/Tips-for-a-successful-academic-professional-development-activity.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T18:53:56Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/10/25/Tips-for-a-successful-academic-professional-development-activity</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ijvM6gdoAEQ/UBLcgazaLFI/AAAAAAAA_TQ/LDWANWYI-Xk/s1600/Professional+Development+Graphic.001.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;     &lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ijvM6gdoAEQ/UBLcgazaLFI/AAAAAAAA_TQ/LDWANWYI-Xk/s1600/Professional+Development+Graphic.001.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ijvM6gdoAEQ/UBLcgazaLFI/AAAAAAAA_TQ/LDWANWYI-Xk/s200/Professional+Development+Graphic.001.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;Within the past year, our statewide community college system has hired five of fourteen new regional academic officers (RAOs) and we have another on the way in September. Given this large number of new RAOs, it was decided by the Provost’s office that they would conduct a &lt;i&gt;new RAO training session&lt;/i&gt;. This session would occur at our Central Office location and be coordinated/planned by our Provost’s office.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I’ll be the first to admit, that I usually groan when I hear that someone is planning my professional development; however as it turns out, this session was probably the best professional development activity I have attended in my twenty years with the college and surely beats the sessions I’ve attended in the military. My thoughts were echoed by my four peers in a recent e-mail conversation, so it must be true.“Why,” you may ask? What was the secret sauce? Let me share my thoughts:

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a name=&#39;more&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Timing is everything.&lt;/b&gt; Our session was an overnight trip; however we began late the in the morning (to allow for the varying travel times due to the geographic locations of the campuses) and ended early afternoon the next day. Given all of our busy schedules and the topics selected, this amount of time was perfect. It was not rushed, and not so long that we began thinking, “I really need to get back to my campus as I have more important things to do.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Attendee driven agenda.&lt;/b&gt; About a month prior, all attendees were asked what topics we wanted to “discuss.” A combined list of the top items were placed on the agenda. This could have turned into a “here’s what we THINK you need” as is often the case in so many professional development activities. Thankfully, we had input on what topics actually mattered.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;“Discuss” being the operative word.&lt;/b&gt; As I mentioned above, we were asked what we wanted to discuss. There was no preaching, no force feeding of the cool-ade. This was an opportunity to put the key topics on the table and discuss. I don’t believe during the whole time, anyone spent more than 5 minutes in a soliloquy. A topic was quickly introduced and then it was discussion time. And there was plenty of it. Often it was lively and spirited, which leads me to my next point.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Vegas rules apply.&lt;/b&gt; We had a little fun with this “what happens in Vegas stays in Vegas” statement. We were in a small room, doors closed and we agreed up front that there were no topics off the table. RAOs, especially new ones, need a safe place to &lt;strike&gt;vent&lt;/strike&gt; discuss the issues. This was our place to discuss those uncomfortable and often difficult topics. Many comments began with “Vegas rules apply, but…”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Effective moderator.&lt;/b&gt; Our moderator, the Vice President for Academic Affairs for the college, was a previous RAO. On top of that, he was an excellent facilitator. He could have been an “instructor” who laboriously worked his way through the material with nary a chance for interaction. Instead he took a true&amp;nbsp;facilitator’s&amp;nbsp;role and kept us and our guest speakers on track while providing time for feedback and discussion. He is also very approachable and cares about the college and about helping us succeed. You felt the passion he had for academic affairs and for mentoring/coaching.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Much food consumed.&lt;/b&gt; Lunch/Dinner/Breakfast/Lunch were provided along with copious amounts of coffee, soda and water. It’s those little things that keep you refreshed. Food breaks along the way allowed the discussions to veer “off topic” and often get to the real issues. Our dinner at a local establishment allowed our social bonds to strengthen. Of course, I had to tack on an extra mile or two to my run afterwards.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Technology allowed.&lt;/b&gt; While we were sensitive not to overstep our bounds by reading our e-mail/tweets/texts/etc, technology was not outlawed. Everyone understood that our jobs often require a quick checkin and answer back to our home campuses. All of us had our technology (mine was a new Nexus 7 tablet, but that’s another blog post) on the table and there were often discussions where that technology came in handy to research trends, policy, curriculum and the like.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Peer group created.&lt;/b&gt; Sure I could call upon several of the other more experienced college academic officers for advice; however, now I have a core group of peers who probably have a better handle on my current challenges and as we mature in the position together, will better understand these challenges going forward.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So what did I learn from this RAO training? To put it succinctly, a lot and not all of it about being an RAO. The focus on this post was not so much what I learned to become successful as an RAO (I’m still a bit fuzzy about this one), but rather what I learned that made this professional development activity successful. I plan to reflect on this post further and implement as many of these strategies as I can to ensure productive professional development activities for our regional faculty.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Have you attended a productive professional development activity lately? Tell me about it in the comments below.</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Education by the numbers</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/10/25/Education-by-the-numbers.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T18:52:58Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/10/25/Education-by-the-numbers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;150&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; id=&quot;blogsy-1347110770920.4292&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-cXVqrOxIT2c/UEawCtCkJcI/AAAAAAABBao/F0KH9iseYGU/s200/Numbers.png&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;Since beginning my new higher education administrative role, I’ve been inundated by numbers of every type. Almost every professional document I read, or meeting I attend, contains some percentage, amount, cost or goal. Some of them are redundant and insignificant while others I find interesting or valuable. Let me present the most interesting numbers that have presented themselves to me in the past couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1000&lt;/strong&gt;: The goal our Chancellor has identified as the total number of student who transfer from our institution to a four-year institution by 2015. Great goal and hope we can reach this one. We have several initiatives in the hopper and hope to blog about some of these soon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17.83%&lt;/strong&gt;: The decrease in our region’s student FTE from this same time last year (after we drop non-pays/attends). This is significant and is the cause of many of our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevencombs.com/2012/07/hard-budget-times-are-not-necessarily.html&quot;&gt;financial challenges&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$380,000&lt;/strong&gt;: The cost to remodel the President’s Office at Purdue University.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; No wonder the community college is the most affordable higher education in the state.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$1.7 billion&lt;/strong&gt;: Total 2012–13 Indiana state appropriations for higher education.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; An increase of &lt;strong&gt;.03%&lt;/strong&gt;. As our President put it today, the budget is flatlined from last year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6%&lt;/strong&gt;: Percentage of the &lt;strong&gt;$1.7&lt;/strong&gt; billion that will be distributed among those colleges and universities that meet certain performance goals. No, I have not seen these goals yet, but will be researching very soon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;488,964&lt;/strong&gt;: Number of K–12 students in Indiana on free or reduced lunches.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; That’s almost &lt;strong&gt;50%&lt;/strong&gt; of the students.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are just few numbers that were discussed today during a recent regional academic officer’s meeting. There were others, as I found while perusing my notes, but these were the digits I found most interesting, striking, confusing or worrisome. I’ll keep my eyes open in the future for other numbers and when I do find more of interest, I’ll try and remember to consolidate them and add to a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indystar.com/article/20120904/NEWS/120904020/Gov-Mitch-Daniels-halts-renovation-of-Purdue-president-s-office?odyssey=tab%7Cmostpopular%7Ctext%7CFRONTPAGE&quot;&gt;IndyStar&lt;/a&gt; ↩&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.in.gov/che/files/Table_1_Historical_Summary_of_Appropriations_for_Indiana_Higher_Education_(1984-85_to_2012-13).pdf&quot;&gt;IN.gov&lt;/a&gt; ↩&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stats.indiana.edu/profiles/profiles.asp?scope_choice=a&amp;amp;county_changer=18000&amp;amp;button1=Get+Profile&amp;amp;id=2&amp;amp;page_path=Area+Profiles&amp;amp;path_id=11&amp;amp;panel_number=1&quot;&gt;Stats Indiana&lt;/a&gt; ↩&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Got caught, did you?</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/10/25/Got-caught-did-you.html"/>
   <updated>2012-10-25T18:47:40Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/10/25/Got-caught-did-you</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-H-sPawAMu2E/UGNVUhc3d1I/AAAAAAABCPE/zRx-H2V283s/s320/We+Take+Your+Class+-+Offline.png&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; /&gt;Take a gander at the article below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.insidehighered.com/quicktakes/2012/09/26/we-take-your-class-goes-offline&quot;&gt;‘We Take Your Class’ Goes Offline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Inside Higher Ed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you are not familiar with the site, they promise, or rather promised, to “take” your online course for you and deliver an A at the end of the semester. All this for the low, low price of – an undisclosed fee. Learn my thoughts on this “endeavor” in this post.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My particular favorite snippet is this quote from from the proprietor, known simply as Kevin. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“the site was not all that lucrative and with the added attention garnered last week, he decided to take it down…he does not think sites like We Take Your Class are a problem; the problem, he believes, is that education is structured in a way that makes it easy to cheat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher Education makes it easy to cheat? Just how is the structure designed to facilitate cheating? I sure would like to have a better understanding of this theory since faculty worldwide are vigilant when it comes to maintaining academic integrity and rigor. Maybe Kevin can parlay this into a thesis or dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My take on this whole situation is that &lt;em&gt;We Take Your Class&lt;/em&gt; simply got caught and that is why they shut down. Kevin was probably (and again, this is purely conjecture on my part so enjoy my fictional tale) a student trying to capitalize on what he thought would be a high demand service. He wanted to be the next Mark Zuckerberg and was willing to sell his Web 2.0 soul to get there.  And is Kevin really the site owner? He could be a disgruntled client? We don’t really know, so lets not be too hard on him. No, let’s since he was willing to become the spokesman for this very questionable site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also can’t help but wonder if the site had clients. What student would actually use this service? Come to think of it, would any client really receive said service? If no services were rendered or even if they were unhappy with the service provided, where would they go? They would not be quick to litigate as that would result in an admission of their own guilt and lead to probable expulsion.  Can you tell that I am very dubious with regard to this whole endeavor?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Evansville, a look back…</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/08/28/Evansville-a-look-back.html"/>
   <updated>2012-08-28T13:53:04Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/08/28/Evansville-a-look-back</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spent the formative years of my higher education career as a junior faculty member to Program Chair for Ivy Tech Community College in Evansville, Indiana. Evansville was, and is, a great little town that grew significantly during my time there; however, if you really want to see how it has changed over the years, check out the video below. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/kHsaLXYGONg&quot; width=&quot;560&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Becoming lean during tough budget cycles</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/07/28/Becoming-lean-during-tough-budget-cycles.html"/>
   <updated>2012-07-28T00:20:02Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/07/28/Becoming-lean-during-tough-budget-cycles</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-z7dOYiDPVxo/UASGpbHYsPI/AAAAAAAA-uY/dzo9twLy7yI/s200/Calculator-Red.jpg&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;Recently, the only thing being discussed on our campus on a daily basis is our budget, or lack thereof. In our case we have to balance a budget where our deficit includes too many zeros. The reason for our budget reduction – lack of enrollment. I won’t even begin to formulate a guess on the reasons for this occurrence as there are entirely too many variables to nail it down to a single one.  I even joke with fellow administrators that I “picked the wrong time to move from the faculty to become a full-time administrator.” I’m half joking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I have found is that there truly is a negative and optimistic way to look at our situation (my wife will tell you that I am too optimistic). Let’s look at the negatives first and end with a few positives (I think my wife is correct).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All too often a review of the budget will panic the masses. Will this review result in the lose of equipment/personnel/programs? The rumor mill begins and spins out of control. In our case, the administration is as transparent as we can be (we still have too many unknowns); however, the faculty and staff learn about “budget” meetings and the rumors begin. And as we all know, most rumors and panic attacks come from the unknown; however, I’ve come to realize that no matter how transparent you are, the human nature of some personality types will always conjure up and disseminate the worst rumors possible. It’s a Catch 22 situation. There is no way to fix this. “It is, what it is,” as a recent colleague so eloquently stated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the “glass half full” division, I have found the budget exercises very beneficial since I am new to this campus and a new academic officer as well. The level of detail when discussing personnel/faculty/programs would have never occurred without this “crisis.” The talk amongst the administrative team is enlightening. Early in my new career I’ve had the opportunity to hear the historical reasons about how positions and programs were created, the good and the bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also observed how our leadership team works under a crisis. I was happy to find that they are a tight knit group. Even when they have disagreements, they are extremely professional and collegial. What strikes me as even more encouraging is that several of us on the team are new to the campus and have been welcomed with open arms. Some are even new to higher education. It is not that often that you find this type of administrative environment, let alone when working through such a difficult time. I’m proud of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we get into the specifics of the budget we have discovered some inefficiencies in some processes; especially within my area of academic affairs. While these findings won’t initially save us a few of those zeros, in the end, these inefficient holes will be plugged. This should reduce the workload of some of our faculty and staff. I often hear that we overwork our folks. I tend to agree with them and it is my hope that we will free up some of their precious time for other more important student focused tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we will probably come out of this budget year more lean, efficient, frugal, and with an enhanced fiduciary responsibility to our state tax payers. When we find these savings, we do something our college is proud of; we keep the cost and tuition of higher education lower than any other institution in the state. This alone makes this process worth the sweat and time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What I did...</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/07/10/What-I-did.html"/>
   <updated>2012-07-10T07:00:13Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/07/10/What-I-did</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;{&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; This is a blog post from another site I wrote while serving as the Dean of the school of Applied Science and Engineering Technology. Those of you who know me now, will read the last full paragraph with a bit a bewilderment. Don’t worry, I did too.}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular higher education blogger, Dean Dad (real name unknown to protect the guilty), recently wrote a blog post entitled, &lt;a href=&quot;http://suburbdad.blogspot.com/2011/01/professor-in-suit.html&quot;&gt;A Professor in a Suit&lt;/a&gt; and I thought it apt that I share his thoughts with those couple of you who follow this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dean Dad does a good job of answering the question, “what do you do?” This is a question asked by many of my friends and family. They understand the faculty role (“you teach huh?”) but often don’t entirely understand a Dean’s dual role as faculty/administrator and the associated pitfalls of this balancing act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dean Dad is apparently (again, he is very vague) an Academic Dean for some unidentified community college in the mid-west. My role as a school Dean; where a school is a smaller academic branch of the college containing specific and associated disciplines, differs slightly. As a school Dean, I have less influence on college administrative policy as I focus my energies on smaller school related issues such as students, personnel management, development, instruction and curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy my role and I am not inclined, nor professionally ready, to move out of it anytime soon. In the meantime, I assert that I am in the best position I’ve ever held in higher education. Teaching was a blast and there are often times I envy Nikki in her role as an instructor, but as I grow older, and hopefully a bit wiser, I find that I want to stretch my legs a bit. Time will tell if I’ve made the correct decision. Thankfully, academia is gracious and they often welcome their administrators back to the faculty.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>And here’s how we are gonna save some cash</title>
   <link href="/higher-education/2012/07/06/And-here%E2%80%99s-how-we-are-gonna-save-some-cash.html"/>
   <updated>2012-07-06T20:20:57Z</updated>
   <id>/higher-education/2012/07/06/And-here’s-how-we-are-gonna-save-some-cash</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ivy Tech will save an estimated $800,000 by purchasing OEM printer supplies and entering long-term agreements according to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.insideindianabusiness.com/newsitem.asp?id=54526&amp;amp;utm_source=feedburner&amp;amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+IIB-Headlines+%28Headlines+-+Inside+INdiana+Business+with+Gerry+Dick%29&quot;&gt;Inside INdiana Business with Gerry Dick&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In addition to the office supplies and multi-purpose agreement with PDME, Ivy Tech has, after a highly competitive RFP process, established a multi-year agreement for premium compatible and OEM toner and ink cartridges with Indianapolis-based ICC Business Products, a family-owned small business that has been serving Indiana businesses since 1930.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The College expects to save more than 50 percent on the cost of printer toner and ink cartridges by shifting purchases from OEM (Original Equipment Manufacturer) toners to high quality premium compatible (remanufactured) printer toners with ICC. And through the robust RFP process, Ivy Tech was able to obtain excellent price levels for printer toners and ink cartridges.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one makes sense and it is good to see that the money we save will return to the state. Now if I can just convince them to outsource our email/calendaring to Google Apps for Education. I could then save them thousands!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>